<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cordial confection, to strengthen their hearts whose courage begins to fail, by the armies late dissolving the Parliament. It is wrapt up in an epistolary discourse, occasionally written to Mr. Ro. Hamon, merchant, by Geo. Wither, Esq; about a week after the said Parliament was dissolved; and is thus communicated by a copy thereof, as very pertinent to these distracted times, and tending to preservation of the common-peace. for (other things of publick concernment, being inter-woven) it truly states the peoples cause (in plain expressions, suitable to the vulgar capacities) and frees it from many scandals. It contains an expedient, (hitherto not heeded, or neglected) whereby Charles Stuart may be settled in peace, if he please: whereby, we may have a better Parliament then we lost, or ever had: whereby, our armies may be kept constant to order, whilst they are needful, and in a short time quite disbanded: whereby, the peoples just freedoms may be recovered and perpetuated: whereby, not onely these nations, but all Christendome also, may be established in a righteous peace; and it hath neither destructive inlet, outlet, or false bottom.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E763_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866169</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96744)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E763[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cordial confection, to strengthen their hearts whose courage begins to fail, by the armies late dissolving the Parliament. It is wrapt up in an epistolary discourse, occasionally written to Mr. Ro. Hamon, merchant, by Geo. Wither, Esq; about a week after the said Parliament was dissolved; and is thus communicated by a copy thereof, as very pertinent to these distracted times, and tending to preservation of the common-peace. for (other things of publick concernment, being inter-woven) it truly states the peoples cause (in plain expressions, suitable to the vulgar capacities) and frees it from many scandals. It contains an expedient, (hitherto not heeded, or neglected) whereby Charles Stuart may be settled in peace, if he please: whereby, we may have a better Parliament then we lost, or ever had: whereby, our armies may be kept constant to order, whilst they are needful, and in a short time quite disbanded: whereby, the peoples just freedoms may be recovered and perpetuated: whereby, not onely these nations, but all Christendome also, may be established in a righteous peace; and it hath neither destructive inlet, outlet, or false bottom.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by James Cottrel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 23 Dec. 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hamon, Ro. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118433:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Cordial Confection, To ſtrengthen their Hearts whoſe Courage begins to fail, by the <hi>Armies</hi> late diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is wrapt up in An Epiſtolary Diſcourſe, Occaſionally written to Mr. <hi>Ro. Hamon,</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, by <hi>Geo. Wither,</hi> Eſq; about a week after the ſaid Parliament was diſſolv'd; and is thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by a Copy thereof, as very pertinent to theſe <hi>diſtracted times,</hi> and tending to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the <hi>COMMON-PEACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For (other things of Publick Concernment, being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven) it truly ſtates the <hi>Peoples Cauſe</hi> (in plain Expreſſions, ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Vulgar Capacities) and frees it from many ſcandals. It contains an <hi>Expedient,</hi> (hitherto not heeded, or neglected) <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Charles Stuart</hi> may be ſettled in Peace, if he pleaſe: <hi>whereby,</hi> we may have a better <hi>Parliament</hi> then we loſt, or ever had: <hi>whereby,</hi> our <hi>Armies</hi> may be kept conſtant to <hi>Order,</hi> whilſt they are needful, and in a ſhort time quite disbanded: <hi>whereby,</hi> the <hi>Peoples</hi> juſt Freedoms may be recovered and perpetuated: <hi>whereby,</hi> not onely theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> but all <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> alſo, may be eſtabliſhed in a <hi>Righteous Peace;</hi> and it hath neither deſtructive <hi>Inlet, Outlet,</hi> or <hi>Falſe Bottom.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 11.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When the Foundations are overthrown, what ſhall the Righteous do?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>James Cottrel,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118433:2"/>
            <head>A CORDIAL CONFECTION Againſt the fainting of the Heart in theſe diſtracted times: BEING The true Copy of an <hi>Epiſtolary Diſcourſe,</hi> written occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by Major <hi>George Wither</hi> to Mr. <hi>R.H.</hi> Merchant, in relation to the hazardous unſettlement of this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> by the late diſſolving of the <hi>Parliament, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctober</hi> 13. 1659. and compoſed the 24 day of the ſame <hi>October.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſam 39. and Job 32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I ſaid, I would keep my mouth with a Bridle, while the wicked are before me; I held my peace, even from good, till my ſorrow was ſtirred, and till my heart was hot within me; and then my muſings burned within me, and I ſpake with my tongue. <hi>Hear me, therefore: for (as Job 32.)</hi> I will neither accept any mans perſon, nor will I flatter; leſt my Maker take me away ſuddainly.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have learned, that, he who, <hi>judges a matter before he hears it,</hi> is culpable of that <hi>Folly,</hi> which makes him liable to <hi>ſhame:</hi> Therefore, when you lately demanded my Judgement concerning the <hi>Armies</hi> diſſolving the <hi>Parliament,</hi> on Thurſday laſt was ſennight, and what <hi>Conſequences</hi> I thought would probably enſue, I told you, That I would not anſwer to thoſe <hi>Queſtions,</hi> until I heard what <hi>Reaſons</hi> they themſelves allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for their Juſtification, and what <hi>proſecutions</hi> they thereupon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; neither of which, being to me known, I am not warranted to declare my opinion in relation to thoſe <hi>Demands;</hi> nor have I ſo high a conceit of my own Judgment, as to think I ſhall then be able to give a <hi>ſatisfactory anſwer:</hi> For, though I rightly pre-conjectured of many things heretofore, upon foregoing <hi>ſymptomes,</hi> which made it eaſie enough for any rational man to diſcern their <hi>Conſequences,</hi> without an <hi>extraordinary Revelation;</hi> yet my <hi>fore-ſight,</hi> at this time, is very dimme, as to conjecturing what that <hi>Action</hi> will produce; and, it will require a <hi>Metaphyſical Apocalypſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, leſt, before that ſhall be divulged by the <hi>Army,</hi> whereon rational <hi>Conjectures</hi> and <hi>Concluſions</hi> may be grounded (for, I pretend no higher) the <hi>Common-peace,</hi> or your <hi>private
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118433:3"/>Tranquillity</hi> may be diſturbed, by things feared or proſecuted, the mean while; I will hereby, give you an <hi>Accompt,</hi> upon what conſiderations I keep my own heart quiet, and from rendring thoſe things worſe, by <hi>prejudicacy,</hi> which I cannot make better by cenſuring what is acted or purpoſed beyond my <hi>sphere,</hi> how irregular or unwarrantable ſoever they do appear. This <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> I think my duty binds me unto, until I know certainly upon what <hi>Principles,</hi> or upon what <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> they are voluntarily executed, or unwillingly conſtrained; eſpecially when they are done by perſons, who have conſiderable <hi>Intereſts</hi> to hazard, and a repute of being conſcientious, rational, moral, pious and prudent men; and more eſpecially, in ſuch <hi>prevaricating times</hi> as theſe, wherein the <hi>ſincerity</hi> of ſome, and the <hi>Hypocriſies</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacies</hi> of others, do, as it were, compel <hi>GOD and Men</hi> to diſpenſe with their <hi>ordinary Laws;</hi> and when <hi>ancient Foundations,</hi> are made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to thoſe <hi>ends</hi> for which they were firſt ordained; even to be hinderances to the injoyment of <hi>humane ſociety,</hi> to the true <hi>worſhip of GOD,</hi> and to the <hi>ſafety of the people,</hi> through the petulancy, or arrogance, of ſome in power, who, by their adding of unſound <hi>Principles,</hi> or perverting of thoſe which are ſound, for a wrong uſe; or, by diſguiſing their <hi>Form,</hi> with unbeſeeming dawbings, or by raiſing upon them burdenſome <hi>Superſtructures;</hi> do employ themſelves for their private advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, in <hi>patching, pulling down,</hi> and <hi>re-building,</hi> as their <hi>ſelf-intereſts</hi> incline them, though it be to the overthrowing or endangering, of their <hi>well and ſafe being,</hi> for whoſe ſakes onely, thoſe <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> were laid.</p>
            <p>What induced them thereto, who were Actors in the late <hi>Innovation;</hi> or what they now deſigne to proſecute, and by what Rules or Means they hope to accompliſh it, we ſhall know when <hi>GOD</hi> and they pleaſe, if it be known to themſelves, whereof I am ſomewhat doubtful: But, whether they have done raſhly or adviſedly, warrantably or unwarrantably, the evident hazards wherein the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is at this preſent, being made greater then they were, as well by the diſtractions which that <hi>Breach</hi> hath unhappily occaſioned, as by thoſe preceding it, (to the encouraging of <hi>Domeſtick and Forraign Adverſaries</hi>) obligeth every <hi>Lover of his Country</hi> to apply himſelf, rather to thoſe endeavourings which are <hi>healing,</hi> and may probably ſecure it from their malicious <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments,</hi> who unqueſtionably ſeek the total deſtruction thereof, then to contribute to thoſe miſchievous <hi>Deſignes,</hi> by weakning our ſelves, through dividing our Power, and waſting it in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing thoſe who have been approved Friends to the ſame <hi>Cauſe</hi> which we own; and I hope will ſo continue, though they have wheeled about into an <hi>Extravagancy.</hi> For, it may be they have diſcovered ſome <hi>Stratagems,</hi> or <hi>Ambuſcadoes</hi> (not appearing to us) which may deſtroy <hi>them,</hi> and the <hi>peoples intereſt</hi> alſo, if not ſpeedily prevented; and thereupon conceived themſelves neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to that <hi>diverſion,</hi> and to proſecute a defence and ſettlement of the <hi>Common Cauſe,</hi> in another manner then heretofore, upon juſtifiable Conſiderations. If this be their <hi>Judgement</hi> in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (as the experience I have had of ſome of them, inclines me to hope) they are, at leaſt, <hi>excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable,</hi> if not altogether <hi>Blameleſs:</hi> and, as our <hi>Affairs</hi> now ſtand, I think it ſafer to keep our Friends by palliating their failings, then to make them our enemies by <hi>Exasperations;</hi> though we have another way, whereby we may be ſafe, notwithſtanding the <hi>Army</hi> ſhould quite deſert us; as I ſhall demonſtrate unto you hereafter: But I will firſt expoſtulate, and offer to conſideration, ſome things concerning <hi>Them</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> which their late attempt hath occaſioned me to weigh in my own heart.</p>
            <p>If it ſhall be objected, that they have heretofore been <hi>changeable,</hi> and do now again proceeed both contary to <hi>Order,</hi> and to their own <hi>Engagements, Declarations, Votes, Profeſſions</hi> and <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> thereby rendring many (even of their beſt Friends) to be jealous &amp; doubtful of their <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>conſtancy</hi> to that <hi>Cauſe</hi> which they have heretofore owned and vindicated; (which is true enough) An Anſwer in part, to that <hi>Objection,</hi> may be implyed toward the Extenuation thereof, by asking, what other <hi>Party,</hi> or <hi>Perſons impowred</hi> to ſerve the <hi>Publick</hi> in Place and Affairs of <hi>high Trust,</hi> hath not as much failed in like manner, and receded from former <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Reſolutions</hi> with connivence, when either they who ſhould have called them to an accompt for it, were as much guilty? or, when it could not be done without hazarding the <hi>Common Peace,</hi> in regard of the Delinquents power? Whether alſo it be not more agreeable to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and a good <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> to vary our <hi>Purpoſes,</hi> or counter-act to our former <hi>Engagements,</hi> then to proſecute them, when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118433:3"/>we find they will deſtroy that end, for which we firſt engaged? And whether we have not more cauſe to confide in thoſe without ſuſpect, who are changeable upon that ſcore, then in them who fooliſhly think it a point of honour, wilfully to perſevere in what they have promiſed, (right or wrong) though it be deſtructive to them unto whom their promiſes were made; yea, and to the <hi>Popular ſafety,</hi> againſt which no <hi>Promiſe</hi> or <hi>Engagement</hi> is obliging? What perſons intruſted have not been ſometimes inforced to mutability, either by <hi>emergent accidents,</hi> or by <hi>diſagreement</hi> among themſelves; or by the <hi>counter-actings,</hi> of thoſe to whom they were ſubordinate, or with whom they were co-ordinate, or by ſome other diſtinct power? But, though neither their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor their Conſcience, nor a <hi>real neceſſity</hi> inclined the <hi>Officers of the Army,</hi> to what hath been lately done; but, that a <hi>Souldier-like Indignation,</hi> onely provoked by the apprehenſion of ſome undeſerved <hi>affront</hi> or <hi>diſrespect,</hi> had raſhly tranſported them; yet, their and the <hi>publick interest</hi> are ſo complicated, that they being conſidered as men in whom <hi>humane infirmities</hi> are to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; and then, at this time, as <hi>(Cauſa ſine qua non)</hi> the perſons who have now the moſt viſible power of this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> in their hands; it would, at ſuch a <hi>Juncture of Affairs,</hi> evidence more <hi>madneſs</hi> (in my judgment) then <hi>prudence,</hi> not to comply with them in an amicable manner, to ſecure that which <hi>IS,</hi> rather then to deſtroy it, by quarrelling about that which <hi>IS NOT;</hi> and which was likely enough (as in effect it did) to have deſtroyed it <hi>Self,</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> and many other, if it had much longer continued.</p>
            <p>I will not defend any mans <hi>arregular actings,</hi> of whoſe <hi>Irregularities</hi> I know not the <hi>Motives;</hi> nor will I abſolutely condemn them: For, though it be my <hi>Principle,</hi> not wilfully to act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Rule, becauſe, I never had <hi>Motive</hi> internally, nor warrant externally ſo to do by any <hi>compulſive neceſſity,</hi> or otherwiſe: Nevertheleſs, I know there have been heretofore, and that poſſibly there may be now and hereafter, (when the people of <hi>GOD</hi> are in extraordinary ſtreights) ſuch impulſes of ſpirit inducing other men at ſome times, to extraordinary Executions, that I dare not judge them to be performed with an <hi>evil conſcience,</hi> or without Divine approbation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am not privy to the <hi>ſecret paſſages</hi> which are or may be betwixt <hi>GOD</hi> and the <hi>Proſecutors;</hi> and becauſe alſo, I finde, that the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt</hi> hath juſtified many in undertakings of that nature; as <hi>Phineas, Rahab, Jael,</hi> and others remembred in <hi>Holy Scripture;</hi> who were active, ſo repugnantly to common Rules of juſt proceeding, and to the literal ſence of Laws morally and ordinarily obliging; that, I ſhould have thought them worthy to have been condemned for <hi>Murther, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Truce-breaking,</hi> and barbarouſly <hi>infringing the Law of Hospitality,</hi> if the Spirit of <hi>GOD</hi> had not by <hi>Sacred Writ,</hi> informed me, that thoſe Proſecutions, were effects of their <hi>Faith.</hi> The example which many do take from theſe aforenamed, to precipitate themſelves into the like actings, by a deluding Spirit working upon their Corruptions, who read the Scriptures with an unſanctified heart, is nevertheleſs to be carefully heeded and a voyded; and there are many <hi>Symptomes</hi> and <hi>concemitant Circumſtances</hi> obſervable (ſome of which <hi>I</hi> have enumerated in one of my private <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes,</hi> heretofore made to <hi>Oliver</hi> late <hi>Protector</hi> upon occaſion offered) whereby, every man may diſcern infallibly, whether a <hi>good</hi> or an <hi>evil Spirit</hi> hath inclined him to ſuch <hi>undertakings:</hi> and <hi>I</hi> do believe, that there have been in theſe latter days, as well as heretofore, good cauſes why <hi>GOD</hi> ſhould vouchſafe extraordinary diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>I</hi> have been an <hi>Eye-witneſs,</hi> (and according to my underſtanding, a diligent <hi>Obſerver</hi> of what <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> have done in theſe latter times) by being conſtrained to reſide moſt part of my life, where Affairs of publick Concernment were managed; and was bound to that atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, which gave opportunity to be aſſured of what <hi>I</hi> have heard and ſeen; as alſo, to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon moved to publiſh Remembrances, bearing witneſs (for this, and for future Ages, as I believe) touching the Controverſies which <hi>GOD</hi> had with theſe <hi>Iſlands,</hi> during the Reigns of King <hi>Charles</hi> and his <hi>Father;</hi> with <hi>Memorials</hi> of the <hi>Prevarications</hi> that then were; of the Interchanges of <hi>Judgements</hi> and <hi>Mercies,</hi> whereby <hi>GOD</hi> viſited them; with timely Fore-warnings, of what hath ſince befallen that Family and theſe Nations, in many particulars, wherein <hi>GOD</hi>'s Juſtice is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, with what mind ſoever it was proſecuted by the Executioners thereof. <hi>I</hi> have likewiſe, for the moſt part, been continually <hi>Reſident,</hi> ever ſince the beginning of the Parliament laſt ſitting, and lately diſſolved, where <hi>I</hi> might and did, take notice of their moſt <hi>ſignal Tranſactions,</hi> (not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118433:4"/>without being made ſenſible of ſome of them.) <hi>I</hi> was perſonally known to the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them (as likewiſe to very many of the following (<hi>onventions</hi> called <hi>Parliaments</hi>) and had ſo many occaſions to know them, that few private perſons of my degree hath had experimentally a more perfect cognizance, of what they <hi>were,</hi> or of what they <hi>did:</hi> And, <hi>I</hi> do profeſs, in the fear of <hi>GOD,</hi> that I conceived, the few right-principled and conſcientions men among them, were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do ſo little <hi>good,</hi> and the reſt to act ſo much <hi>evil,</hi> that (as I have ſometimes publickly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated) I expected nothing from them, but an encreaſe of Confuſions, likely to produce inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Deſtruction; until the late Reſtoration of the firſt Parliament: on whom, I for a while hoped <hi>GOD</hi>'s extraordinary Mercy to them vouchſafed, might have ſo wrought, that it would have produced extraordinary good effects.</p>
            <p>But, that miraculous Reſtoration, was forgotten ſo quickly, by too many of them, that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced little of that fruit which was expected; though juſt proſecutions were (as I believe) ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly intented and endeavoured by ſome among them. Their needleſs neglect of common Juſtice to diſtreſſed Suppliants ready to periſh, and their groſs partiality was ſo apparent; their <hi>time</hi> ſo waſted by impertinencies; their <hi>proceedings</hi> otherwhile ſo ſlow, and another while ſo raſh; the <hi>Notions</hi> of ſome ſo metaphyſical, and of otherſome ſo meerly <hi>carnal;</hi> their <hi>Reſults</hi> ſo wavering or contradictory; <hi>interferings</hi> ſo frequent, and their <hi>puzlings</hi> ſo many, to the dayly enereaſe of private and publick Grievances, with ſmall redreſs of any; and the people ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſcontented to ſee their burthens multiplyed, without any regard of making good their Securities and Engagements: that obſerving all this, and ſeeing ſix moneths conſumed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effecting any thing conſiderable, in a time threatning ſo many dangers, and neceſſitating their endeavour to preſerve the good affection of their old Servants: I was confident (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by my <hi>Epiſtle at Randome,</hi> publiſhed ſix weeks before their diſſolution) that another <hi>Change</hi> would ſhortly follow, if they did not ſpeedily better improve their time, and ſeaſon their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the Publick, with Juſtice and more works of private Mercy. And I feared a worſe thing would have happened, though, that which is come to paſs, will be bad enough, if <hi>GOD</hi> be not more merciful then we deſerve.</p>
            <p>And I am perſwaded, that a principal Cauſe of their late diſſolving, was their continual neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of mingling ſome Acts of private Juſtice and Mercy, with their endeavour for the Publick, according to their Engagements made to thoſe, by whom they had been preſerved in their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt need and danger; which duty they ſlunk from, under a pretended Zeal to ſettle thoſe Affairs which required ſpeedy proſecution: whereas, it was well enough perceived, that they could finde many days and opportunities, to take into Conſideration many Petitions, which concerned Themſelves, their Relations and Favourites, who were not deſtructively grieved, even when the Commonwealths Preſſures were moſt conſiderable; not caring how thoſe ſores which pained the meaneſt Members of the Body, whom they repreſented, might poſſibly <hi>Gangrene</hi> at laſt, to the deſtroying of the Vital parts thereof. For, the Commonwealth conſiſts of Individuals; which being neglected one by one, brings on by degrees an unheeded Conſumption, and diſmembring of the whole. <hi>A Body Politick</hi> having no affections, cannot have Cognizance of its own, or other mens wants and hazards, but by the <hi>natural Faculties and Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions</hi> of the <hi>ſingle Members</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And doubtleſs, when <hi>GOD,</hi> who hath care of every private mans Oppreſſions, obſerved, that (notwithſtanding his late exemplary Mercy to them vouchſafed) no ſad <hi>Remonſtrances</hi> of poor men, deſtructively grieved and wronged by them and others, though often exhibited, and proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with no leſs importunities, then thoſe which prevailed with that unrighteous Judge, who neither feared <hi>GOD,</hi> nor cared for men, could move them to more conſideration then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but, that as formerly, <hi>private Petitions</hi> were ſtill excluded from week to week, and from moneth to moneth many years together, till great numbers of oppreſſed Petitioners were dead and undone: this, ſo provoked Divine Wrath (aggravated by the many pre-caveats which they had) that, when they ſhewed more diligence and reſolution, to ſecure themſelves, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſts, then in ten times ſo many days formerly, <hi>GOD</hi> permitted what was then done, to be an occaſion of removing themſelves once again, out of the Throne; that, it may appear how invalid and unacceptable mens beſt endeavours are, when Juſtice and Mercy are groſly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118433:4"/>Their vain <hi>excuſe</hi> by ſome of them alleaged, of wanting <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Treaſure,</hi> to ſettle the <hi>Government,</hi> and ſupply the <hi>Commonwealths</hi> neceſſities, made them not excuſable: For, <hi>GOD,</hi> and I, and many other men, know, that much <hi>time,</hi> and great ſums of money were ſpent, which might have been better beſtowed, to preſerve ſome of them from ruine, to whom they had long owed it: And, they were put in minde, that the <hi>poor Widow,</hi> who made a Cake for the <hi>Prophet</hi> in his neceſſity, before ſhe provided one for her ſelf and her hungry Child (when there was ſcarce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough left to make another) had a miraculous ſupply of Oyl and Meal, for a reward: and ſo ſhould they have had, if their Faith and Charity had been but half ſo much as hers.</p>
            <p>Of what would be the Event upon thoſe <hi>Failings,</hi> I fore-warned ſome of them, both in <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,</hi> and <hi>publick,</hi> if not amended: which I now mention, rather to glorifie <hi>GOD</hi>'s <hi>Juſtice,</hi> then to aggravate their <hi>Shame.</hi> And I do not thus plainly expreſs what I know of their former acting, becauſe I think you will keep it private (for I am content you communicate this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to whom you pleaſe;) nor have I done it, becauſe <hi>I</hi> think their power is ſo annihilated that it will never be viſible again: For, I will not recant this, though they ſhould be reſtored; which (though unlikely) is not impoſſible: For, as well the <hi>Mercies</hi> as <hi>Judgements</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> are unſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable, and <hi>His Mind</hi> no leſs difficult to be found out in the one, then in the other. His <hi>ways</hi> are not as <hi>mans ways,</hi> nor his thoughts as ours. If, as I believe (and know in my own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar he hath done) He reſtores to <hi>Grace</hi> loſt, many <hi>ſingle perſons,</hi> ſeveral times, why may I not hope, He will be as merciful to the <hi>Repr ſentative</hi> of three whole Nations, in vouchſafing a third <hi>Probation?</hi> If he would have ſpared five wicked Cities for the ſakes of <hi>ten rightcous men,</hi> why may I not believe, that he will reſtore a <hi>Parliament</hi> for the ſakes of <hi>ten righteous perſons,</hi> or a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable</hi> number thereto, if there be but ſo many among all the <hi>Members</hi> of that <hi>parliament,</hi> or in the <hi>Counties, Cities</hi> and <hi>Towns</hi> whom they repreſented? And why ſhould not I have the ſame belief concerning the <hi>Army,</hi> though they have now prevaricated, and many times hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Verily I believe there are and were many <hi>righteous men</hi> Members of the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> and of this <hi>Army,</hi> who would have proſecuted the <hi>peoples Cauſe,</hi> in another manner, and to better effect, if the <hi>ſelf-mindedneſs</hi> of ſome other, had not obſtructed them; and I believe alſo, that the greateſt part of the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> whether that which they have lately done be altogether of <hi>GOD</hi> or not (or whether there be in it a Traiterous Deſigne againſt the Parliament contrived by ſome of their <hi>Chiefs</hi>) had a good intent;and as once many of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> being called by <hi>Abſolom,</hi> under colour of a Vow to <hi>GOD,</hi> when he rebelled againſt his Father, did joyn unto the reſt in ſimplicity of heart, not conſcious of ought miſ-intended: ſo perhaps did they. If it indeed be ſo, their <hi>Seducers</hi> will ſpeed like <hi>Abſolom;</hi> and they who were ſeduced, will return obedience to them, unto whom their obedience is due, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did to <hi>David;</hi> &amp; our great hazard thereby occaſioned, will become a means of our greater <hi>ſafety;</hi> that which hath been obſtructed, will be carried on with leſs interruption; our Governours will better heed, what GOD's purpoſe was in that which he hath done for theſe Nations, and how they ought to have proceeded heretofore: which I heartily beſeech his <hi>Almighty Majeſty</hi> they may timely perform, that further effuſion of blood in a hoſtile way, may be prevented, and that he would be ſo merciful to every <hi>Party</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, now diſagreeing and divided from each other, that we may be made happy in a timely Reconciliation to Him, and to each other.</p>
            <p>A main <hi>Cauſe</hi> of our <hi>Wandrings</hi> as it were in a Wilderneſs, (wherein we have been like ſo many Beaſts and Serpents to each other) and of GOD's bringing us as it were back again toward <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> when we were well onward in our way to the <hi>Land of Reſt,</hi> was the not underſtanding, or not regarding to obſerve and proſecute, what he intended; and our adhering to <hi>humane policy,</hi> rather then to <hi>Divine Indictions,</hi> like <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and <hi>Jehu,</hi> who when GOD gave unto them their Maſters <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> (with <hi>conditional promiſes,</hi> to ſettle them upon their <hi>poſterities</hi>) loſt them with diſhonour for their diſobedience and unthankfulneſs. And as thoſe two <hi>Kings</hi> truſted to their own Policy, ſo did our <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Protectors,</hi> though they were told upon what conditions the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of their <hi>Maſters</hi> were conferred upon them: and they have added this to the reſt of their ſins, that they have endeavoured to improve GOD's <hi>Donations,</hi> another <hi>way</hi> and to another <hi>end,</hi> then was providentially intended, by that <hi>Decree</hi> of GOD, which was written in <hi>Red Letters</hi> at a Trial in his <hi>Martial Court,</hi> with points of <hi>Swords.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118433:5"/>
            <p>For, when that great <hi>Controverſie,</hi> which had depended many Ages betwixt this <hi>people</hi> and their <hi>Kings,</hi> concerning the uſurped <hi>Prerogatives</hi> of the One, and the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal Freedoms</hi> of the Other, which (laſt mentioned) are <hi>Rights</hi> ſo due to the People by the Laws of <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> (though long uſurped) that none, there of make queſtion, but <hi>Tyrants</hi> and their <hi>Paraſites,</hi> or perſons of a bruitiſh, ſenſual and ſlaviſh Qualification: when (I ſay) thoſe <hi>Claims</hi> had been after ſeveral days of hearing (as it were) argued in the high places of the field, between the late <hi>King</hi> and that part of the People, who thought it more noble to be <hi>Free-men,</hi> then to have badges of their ſervility clapt upon them as <hi>Titles of Honour;</hi> when they had upon a joynt Appeal and a Trial by the Sword, according to the known <hi>Common Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the Law in force throughout all Nations, a <hi>Verdict</hi> at a <hi>Court</hi> from whence there is no further Appeal, (and when likewiſe, that <hi>Trial</hi> was paſt, and quiet poſſeſſion thereupon given to the <hi>Conquerors</hi>) Reaſon requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red proſecutions of another Nature then thoſe which were afterward begun and pretended, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſettle the people in a future enjoyment of their Liberties and ancient Rights: For, they ſhould immediately have repealed or altered all thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> which had relation to a Tyrannical Government, and laid a new <hi>Foundation</hi> proper to the Popular Intereſt; yea (as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> heretofore, in like <hi>Caſe,</hi> uſed to conſult with their <hi>Apollo</hi>) they ſhould have conſulted the <hi>Oracle</hi> of GOD, and ſearched after ſuch Directions as He commanded his people the <hi>Iſraeiites,</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, when he made them <hi>Conquerors</hi> of <hi>Canaan:</hi> which, would rightly have inſtructed them what courſe they ought to take. Among which <hi>Directions,</hi> thoſe that I remember as moſt conſiderable in our caſe, are to this effect: <hi>They were neither to ſerve their GODS, nor to obſerve their LAWS; nor make peace with thoſe among them, who ſhould adhere to their former Idolatries, and heatheniſh Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes; nor spare ſo many of them, (for politick ends, or through fooliſh pity) as might endanger their own ſafety; nor root them out all at once; nor permit any of their own Tribes to enjoy an inheritance there, who had not aſſiſted their Brethren in the Conqueſt;</hi> with ſuch like: which, if our <hi>Governours</hi> had heeded, and made uſe of ſo much of thoſe <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>Precepts</hi> as were pertinent to our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and practice, doubtleſs our troubles had been ended long ago; or, at leaſt we ſhould not have had ſo many thorns in our ſides, as at this day we have.</p>
            <p>Somewhat of this Nature, and to the like purpoſe, I offered to their conſideration, whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to take notice thereof, but with little or no regard; for, not remembring that but a while ſince, ſome of themſelves, then in power, were as inconſiderable perſons as I am, they were ſo elevated, that they thought it a diſparagement to take advice in ſuch matters, from ſo obſcure a perſon: yet, knowing my ſelf concerned in the <hi>Publick Welfare,</hi> I perſiſted in endeavouring what I thought pertinent thereto: And when <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> late Lord Protector had taken upon himſelf the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> (thereto providentially admitted both for his own Probation and our) I ſubmitted (according to my <hi>Principle</hi> grounded upon Divine Precepts) to that Power which was in <hi>being,</hi> and complyed with him in things tending to preſervation of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> in hope to inſinuate thereby, ſomewhat into his Conſideration, for Publick Advantage: And, becauſe, <hi>I</hi> had not ſuch a meaſure of the <hi>Spirit</hi> which reſted upon <hi>Elias,</hi> as might warrant me to ſay unto my <hi>Soveraign Prince,</hi> in plain terms, <hi>Thou art wicked,</hi> (when <hi>I</hi> ſaw him prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate from what he had profeſſed) yet I endeavoured, as <hi>Paul</hi> did to work upon King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> firſt, by publiſhing ſomewhat whereby I might preſerve and encreaſe a good opinion, without any ſor did flattery, (though ſome who miſunder ſtood my Poems, have conceived otherwiſe) and then I ſought by private Addreſſes, to ſcrew into him a ſerious Conſideration of his Duty, in many particulars relating to <hi>GOD,</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> and to <hi>Himſelf;</hi> declaring boldly and plainly (not a little to my perſonal diſadvantage) that the power conferred upon him was not vouchſafed for his own ſake; but, that he might thereby glorifie <hi>GOD,</hi> and ſettle upon his People thoſe Rights, which were ſo anciently and naturally their due, that no Preſcription could be a juſt bar to their Claim. And though perhaps he ſurreptitiouſly and unjuſtly haſtned to get poſſeſſion of that power which <hi>GOD</hi> had deſigned him, (as <hi>Hazael</hi> did, after the Prophet of GOD had foretold him he ſhould be King) yet I perceiving, by his honourable new <hi>Title,</hi> and by other Circumſtances, that <hi>GOD</hi> had permitted a more abſolute Arbitrary Power to be devolved upon him, then any of our Kings ever had, becauſe without ſuch a <hi>Power,</hi> it was impoſſible for him to bring us to a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118433:5"/>perfect <hi>Settlement,</hi> (being ſo unſettled and divided as we then were, and yet are) I preſumed both to declare unto him, to what intent that <hi>exorbitant Power</hi> was permitted; how long he was to enjoy it; in what manner he ſhould thereby proceed; and what would follow if he employed it to any other end.</p>
            <p>But, (before I had preſumed ſo far, or declared any thing, to the making ineffectual my good <hi>Intents,</hi> by ought which might be diſtaſtful) I then perceiving he took as little notice as the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> had done before their firſt <hi>Interruption,</hi> of that courſe which I tought pertinent to the introducing of a <hi>Righteous Government;</hi> and that he probably intended rather to eſtabliſh it for his own and his Poſterities advantage, then for the Peoples Accommodation, (or elſe, that he might trifle away the <hi>Opportunities</hi> then given, by proſecuting his own <hi>Deſignes</hi> until they were loſt.) I ſignified unto him in a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> prepared in form of a <hi>Declaration</hi> to theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> how he might ſettle a <hi>Righteous Government</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> believed) with ſafety and honour, if he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelf to the <hi>People,</hi> by publiſhing a <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> to that effect for their ſatisfaction. This Overture being made at a time wherein his fears and hazards were very great: Though that <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> was very large, he with much ſeeming Contentment, heard me read it over to the laſt word; and then proteſted, according to his uſual manner, that it anſwered to his heart, as the <hi>ſhadow of his face</hi> in the Glaſs (then hanging before him in the room) anſwered to his <hi>face;</hi> and pretended he would publiſh that <hi>Declaration,</hi> and act accordingly, aſſoon as he with one in whoſe diſcretion he much confided, had conſidered what alteration it might need, (or words to that effect) and then received it of me, promiſing to return it with his final reſolution, within a week.</p>
            <p>At the weeks end, or thereabout, he, or Mr. <hi>Thurloe</hi> then Secretary, (who ſeemed alſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thereof) delivered back unto me my <hi>Papers;</hi> and the <hi>Protectors</hi> Anſwer, which then was, That he himſelf, together with the ſaid <hi>Secretary</hi> and <hi>my Self,</hi> would within a few days, examine it over, to ſee what <hi>verbally,</hi> might require alteration, or what addition would be neceſſary; and that being done, he would then without fail, take order for Publication thereof. But, afterward he apoſtatiz'd from that <hi>Reſolution,</hi> to his own diſ-advantage, and to the occaſion of what hath ſince befallen to the <hi>Publick Detriment;</hi> yet, pretended many moneths together, a firm adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to what he had ſeemingly reſolved on, keeping me all that time in attendance; gave me the Key of his Cloſet at the end of the <hi>Sheild Gallery</hi> in <hi>White-hall,</hi> (wherein his Books and his Papers lay) to retite unto when I came thither; carried me often to his own Table; frequently diſcourſed with me concerning my <hi>Propoſal;</hi> and appointed many ſet days wherein to review the ſaid <hi>Papers,</hi> but failed always in performance; wherewith I being a little diſcontented, told him, I thought his mind was changed; and giving him back the Key of his <hi>Cloſet,</hi> purpoſed never to wait again upon him, in relation to that buſineſs. He then, with very reſpective words to me, excuſing his clays, aſſured me that at ſix of the Clock next morning, he would ſend for his <hi>Secretary,</hi> and diſpatch that which he intended, before he would admit any other perſon into his preſence. I came before the appointed hour, but was then alſo put off, until a little paſt three in the afternoon, at which time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>attended till paſt four; and then, hearing that <hi>He,</hi> and his <hi>Secretary,</hi> were gone forth in a Coach to take the Air, I purpoſed to depart, and looſe no more time on that occaſion: and as I was leaving the room, one informed me, that about the ſame hour, in which I was appointed to attend <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Secretary,</hi> their necks were both in hazard to be broken, by the <hi>Protectors</hi> uſurping the Office of his <hi>Coach-man;</hi> and that they were both brought in ſo hurt, that their lives were in danger. Of that imprudent, if not diſgraceful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt miſ-befeeming his perſon, I endeavored to prevent as much of the diſhonor, as I might, by a little <hi>Poem,</hi> as I thought it my duty, in regard he executed the <hi>Supreme Office</hi> at that time. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, he called on me again, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if his mind had not been wholly changed, and referred the ſaid Papers to his <hi>Privy-Council,</hi> who referred them to a <hi>Sub-Committee,</hi> of which Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering</hi> being one, gave it a high approbation, and was pleaſed to ſay he did not flatter me; but from that time forward, I heard no more of it. Another ſervice I did, which much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to <hi>His</hi> and the <hi>Publick Safety,</hi> whereto Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering</hi> is privy likewiſe; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in conſideration of the fore-mentioned ſervices, the ſaid <hi>Protector</hi> having, without my asking that, or any thing elſe, (oct
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118433:6"/>to be relieved according to Juſtice from my oppreſſions, which I could not obtain) gave me the <hi>Statute-Office,</hi> and afterward made it little worth unto me, becauſe (as I conceive) I expreſt my thankfulneſs for it, in declaring unto him thoſe <hi>Truths,</hi> which he was not willing to hear of. Pardon this digreſſion, for it is ſomewhat pertinent.</p>
            <p>Thus, both the ſaid <hi>Protector</hi> and the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> either through over-ſight, wilfulneſs, or miſunderſtanding the ſtate of the <hi>Peoples Cauſe,</hi> (or how far forth for the <hi>Commonwealths</hi> beſt advantage, they ought to have proſecuted the execution of that <hi>Sentence</hi> which GOD gave on her behalf) acted not onely repugnantly to the <hi>Welfare</hi> thereof, but alſo, by endeavouring a <hi>means</hi> impoſſible to be effected. For, to ſay the truth, they were nor, nor now are, nor ever can be, in a capacity to have an orderly proceeding toward a <hi>Peaceable Government,</hi> much leſs an <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment</hi> thereof, in a <hi>Parliameatary mode,</hi> according to the old conſtitution of <hi>Parliaments:</hi> yea, I will confidently affirm (though it will ſeem a great preſumption) that, as Affairs now ſtand, the <hi>People</hi> cannot by any ordinary means be reduced to ſuch a poſture, as may bring them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree upon, or admit of, any ſettled <hi>Government</hi> whatſoever agreeable to the Laws now extant, or otherwiſe, by reaſon of the irreconcileable <hi>differing Judgements, Factions, Diviſions</hi> and <hi>malignant Diſaffections,</hi> which are begot and fomented more and more among them, by the habit of <hi>licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> which they have now gotten. Nor will their turbulent Animoſities be ever calmed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til there ſhall be ſome <hi>Foundations</hi> firſt laid, by an <hi>unreſiſtable Arbitrary Power,</hi> depoſited for a while, in one or more perſons, whereby an orderly proceeding toward ſettling <hi>a juſt Government,</hi> may unreſiſtably take place. This conſtrained the <hi>Roman Senate</hi> to conſtitute otherwhile, in ſuch caſes, a <hi>Dictator,</hi> who had ſuch an <hi>abſolute Power,</hi> for a time. This is the natural <hi>Cauſe</hi> (if <hi>violent motions</hi> may properly be called natural) why the Determinations and Beginnings of moſt <hi>Governments, Monarchical</hi> and <hi>Popular,</hi> in all times and places, were derived from the <hi>Sword;</hi> which (how diſpleaſing ſoever it be to thoſe whom it may concern) is the remedy to which we, and all <hi>Nations</hi> in out condition, muſt ſubmit, before they can have a <hi>laſting Peace.</hi> The <hi>Sword of War</hi> is the onely <hi>Umpire</hi> in all ſuch extreams, and it muſt be endured until we are brought to ſuch a temper as will make us governable by the <hi>Civil Sword;</hi> and that it may preſerve us, in the mean time, from <hi>Dom ſtick Inſurrections,</hi> and <hi>Forraign Invaſions.</hi> And indeed, there is no ſuch cauſe to fear it, as we pretend; for, it is not the corruption, violence, and want of ſincerity, which is uſual in Armies, that endangers us half ſo much as our <hi>ſins</hi> in general: For, whilſt they are unrepented &amp; encreaſe, even the beſt <hi>Government,</hi> &amp; moſt <hi>Righteous Governours</hi> on earth, ſhall not ſecure us: and when we are as we ought to be, the worſt ſhall not be able to harm us. The LORD of HOSTS, who is our GOD, is <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of all the Armies in the World; nothing is acted for, or againſt any <hi>People,</hi> but by his command or permiſſion; and if we diſpleaſe Him, who ſhall protect us? If our Ways and Deſignes be ſuch as He approves, who can hurt us? He is our <hi>Supreme,</hi> yea, ſole <hi>Judge</hi> in all cauſes triable by <hi>Combate,</hi> and by the <hi>Sword of war,</hi> in a peculiar manner; and none who love <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> need be affraid of his <hi>doom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will be a ſweet comfortable <hi>Cordial,</hi> to thoſe innocent and honeſt men, who through hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmity, are frighted by the <hi>Diſtractions</hi> of theſe times, and dread what our <hi>Army</hi> may do; if their profeſſions ſhould be hypocritical; or if they, who are yet ſincere, ſhould fall from their uprightneſs: and this being well conſidered, will terrifie them, who truſt in an <hi>armed power,</hi> and hoped that would protect them in all their Falſhoods, Oppreſſions and Wicked Deſignes. This will alſo be unpleaſing to them, who would by their own power, their own way, and to their own ends, eſtabliſh a <hi>Government</hi> at this time among us; and no leſs diſguſt them, who aſcribe Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to <hi>Kings,</hi> or make Idols of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as many have done, and ſome yet do among us; and of which ſuperſtition, I my ſelf (being educated under a <hi>Tyranny,</hi> which kept me ignorant of what I was born to) have hitherto been guilty, as may appear by many ſtaggering and dubious <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,</hi> ſcattered here and there in my <hi>Writings,</hi> which I am content ſhould remain upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to teſtifie that I think not my ſelf infallible; and that I do not impoſe my <hi>Aſſertions</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially, with expectation that they ſhould be ſubſcribed unto, without due examination. Nevertheleſs, let not that which will 'bide the <hi>Test,</hi> be rejected.</p>
            <p>As there are many among us, who cry out for <hi>Kings</hi> again, thinking them to be more then of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118433:6"/>humane Extract or Inſtitution: becauſe they neither know that they were the <hi>Peoples Creatures,</hi> made originally but to be their <hi>principal Servants,</hi> to ſee thoſe Laws duly executed which they themſelves made; nor take notice, how by degrees, they have made them who were their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> to become their <hi>Slaves;</hi> nor do remember; how they have oppreſſed them; nor conſider how much more they intend to oppreſs them, nor how they will again oppreſs them, if they be re-admitted; nor that they were the cauſe of all thoſe Burthens, which at this time lye upon them, and for which they clamour againſt thoſe who would remove them: In like manner, many do as inconſiderately cry out for <hi>Parliaments;</hi> which if they be not well conſtitute, may be more deſtructive then their <hi>Kings.</hi> But, they would have <hi>Free Parliaments;</hi> and ſuch they call <hi>Free,</hi> as ſhould be formed of the wiſeſt and honeſteſt men among us, as near as is poſſible, made <hi>Members</hi> thereof, at the choyce of all perſons who have a conſiderable intereſt in the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> freely admitted to <hi>elect;</hi> which would be ſuch a <hi>Parliament</hi> as may poſſibly be hereafter, when a <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> whereon to fix it, and an orderly <hi>Medium</hi> for ſuch <hi>Elections</hi> is provided: but ſuch a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was never yet in being (if before my remembrance <hi>Knights, Citizens</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> were elected, as they have been in many places, within the time of my knowledge) and it is the great Mercy of GOD, conſidering how many were brought in by the <hi>Court-Faction</hi> for their ends, and how many ſcrew'd in themſelves for their own ends, that ſo much of our <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal Freedoms</hi> is yet left.</p>
            <p>That which is now interrupted, and againſt whoſe imperfection and unlawfulneſs, ſo many have lately clamoured, was as good and legal a <hi>Parliament,</hi> all things conſidered, (even when it was at worſt) as any heretofore, to all intents and purpoſes, whilſt it had <hi>being</hi> and <hi>power;</hi> and every Act thereof, till it be repealed by its own or by another <hi>abſolute Power,</hi> is as binding as the Acts of any other <hi>Partiaments:</hi> For, a <hi>powerful being</hi> in the Members thereof, gives it <hi>Eſſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> according to the nature of that <hi>being</hi> for which it was ordained, as truly as the <hi>reaſonable Soul</hi> in a <hi>Body of fleſh</hi> gives <hi>being</hi> to a <hi>man,</hi> who, whether he be lawfully or unlawfully begotten, or born with <hi>too many</hi> or with <hi>too few Members,</hi> or whether he be maimed by others or by his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, is nevertheleſs a <hi>Man</hi> whilſt the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> continue together. Whilſt, power (which is the <hi>Soul</hi> of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> or at leaſt, that by which a <hi>Soul</hi> is know to be in it) remained in that which was lately interrupted, if not totally deſtroyed, it might have performed what would have been neceſſary for the preſent, to ſupply thoſe defects, which may elſe deſtroy the <hi>Body</hi> whom they repreſent; and during the time vouchſafed by GOD for their <hi>ſecond Probation,</hi> it might (if not again interrupted) have been a help to prepare a more perfect <hi>Medium</hi> toward eſtabliſhing a <hi>Government,</hi> then yet we have any, and which might have given unto future <hi>Parliaments</hi> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution more likely to preſerve it, then ever they had heretofore: For, all our Parliaments for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly convened, were conſtituted by Tyrants, or Princes little better. They were their <hi>Creatures,</hi> and not the <hi>Peoples:</hi> They were <hi>called, prorogued</hi> and <hi>diſſolved</hi> at their pleaſure: were made up of ſuch <hi>Perſons,</hi> and of ſuch a <hi>Number</hi> as they liſted: were choſen by, and for ſuch places, and out of ſuch orders of men, as they priviledged to that purpoſe; and were originally ordained, for no other intent, but to preſerve the Peace of other men ſo long and ſo far forth onely, as it might uphold their <hi>Grandeur,</hi> and make the people <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to enſlave themſelves thereunto: though, through GOD's Mercy, the People have by degrees, acquired means in Parliaments to recover ſome part of their loſt Liberties, much againſt the wills of their Kings and Creators: But their Liberties will never perfectly be recovered, until a Foundation be laid by the Power of the Peoples own Sword, in the hands of faithful <hi>Truſtees,</hi> whereupon a juſt Government may be ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, with out-works to defend it from Innovators; and whereby Parliaments may be ſo regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, that the peoples Civil, Natural and Spiritual Proprieties and Freedoms, may be preſerved without violation, as much as poſſible.</p>
            <p>What would be the effects of giving Liberty at this preſent (as it is by the greateſt number de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired) for any man to chuſe, or to be choſen a Member of Parliament, but the deſtroying of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, Morality</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> together with all the juſt Liberties of the people, which they have ſo dearly paid for, and were likely to recover when almoſt quite loſt? For the worſt men are moſt numerous, and the greater part of them conſiſting of thoſe, who by conniving at, or complying
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118433:7"/>with Tyrants and Oppreſſours (under whom they ſhall enjoy moſt Licentiouſneſs) were the chief Cauſers and Continuers of our late and preſent Troubles; and theſe having, ſtill their hearts wholly inclined to renew them, how eaſie will it be, for them, by indirect means, to bring into a Parliament, Members like themſelves, more then enough; yea, doubly, to over-vote thoſe who are elected by that part of the People, who ought to have chief Benefit of that Conqueſt which GOD lately gave them? For do we purſue and apprehend <hi>Theeves</hi> and <hi>Murderers,</hi> who have robbed and ſlain honeſt men, to make them and their <hi>Abettors,</hi> ſharers in the goods they cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, when they are again recovered? Or, do we make them keepers, or diſpoſers of our perſons or eſtates? Did <hi>Gideon</hi> make them to be partakers of his Victory, when he overcame <hi>Zeba</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna,</hi> who, when he was in purſuit of them, derided him inſtead of relieving his fainting <hi>Army</hi> with bread? Verily, they ought to be rewarded like them, who have oppoſed the <hi>Common Cauſe,</hi> by their hands, tongues or pens; and even they alſo, who have not therein aſſiſted their brethren, rather then to be vouchſafed partnerſhip in their <hi>Freedoms:</hi> And it would not only manifeſt theſe <hi>Nations</hi> to be very imprudent, if without good aſſurance, of their being better affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to their juſt <hi>Cauſe</hi> then heretofore, they do admit them both to an equal enjoyment of that and all other Freedomes with themſelves, and to a capacity, upon their imprudent claim thereof, to be their <hi>Lawgivers,</hi> the <hi>Keepers of their Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſers</hi> of their Eſtates and Perſons; But, it would imply alſo, a high contempt of GOD's late Diſpenſations, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the benefit of them to his <hi>Oppoſers.</hi> The right of <hi>chuſing,</hi> and of being <hi>choſen Members of Parliament,</hi> is now in thoſe onely, who have gotten it by Conqueſt; the Law of Conqueſt is paramount to all their <hi>humane Laws;</hi> it is nor onely <hi>Municipal,</hi> but <hi>Catholick,</hi> and gives juſt Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the <hi>Conquering Party,</hi> to make new Laws as they pleaſe, and to continue, ſuſpend, abrogate, or reform all other <hi>humane Laws</hi> within their own Territories, as they conceive them to be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or a hinderance to their <hi>Common Welfare.</hi> It is that <hi>Law</hi> by which the LORD of HOSTS hath decided our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as I ſaid before: it is that by which all the moſt famous <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the world in all Ages, were firſt conſtituted and ſettled, before they could ſafely lay the <hi>Sword</hi> aſide, to be governed by other <hi>Laws;</hi> and they who are diſſatisfied with that ſettlement, are not to be regarded.</p>
            <p>That, therefore, which the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould have done, (in my judgement) when the power of the <hi>Sword</hi> was in their hands; and that which their late <hi>Succeſſours</hi> ought to have proſecuted, when for the <hi>Parliaments</hi> failings the ſame power was tranſlated to them, was not to employ their <hi>Authority,</hi> and the Revenues of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> thereby graſped, that they might advance <hi>themſelves;</hi> build up what GOD hath <hi>broken down,</hi> trifle away precious opportunities, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the publick Treaſure in making an <hi>Image</hi> of the BEAST formerly adored; or in patching up that which was uſeleſs, and not poſſibly repairable, and would more encreaſe then diminiſh the <hi>Peoples Grievances:</hi> They ought not under a pretended Zeal to the <hi>Common Welſare,</hi> inſtead of contriving a <hi>Government,</hi> whereby <hi>Juſtice</hi> might be indifferently and impartially adminiſtred to all, (and every man been thereby equally made capable of <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>profit,</hi> according to his merit, for an encouragement to Vertue) to have plotted how to model it ſo, as, that Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Dignities, whereby the <hi>publick Honour</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> may be moſt advanced or hazarded, ſhould be continued to themſelves, conferred on their neareſt <hi>Relations,</hi> and derived to their <hi>Poſterity:</hi> But, on the contrary, they ſhould have improved GOD's appearing for us, and the power thereby acquired, like magnanimous <hi>Conquerers,</hi> to ſettle in deſpight of oppoſition, ſuch a <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> as GOD would have given them a <hi>pattern</hi> of, had they ſought it; and, whereby <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> ſhould have been duly adminiſtred. They ſhould have exerciſed that <hi>power</hi> in making (as it were) <hi>a new Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>new Earth,</hi> by eſtabliſhing the <hi>Superior Orbs</hi> in motions tending to Pious and Righteous Diſpenſations; and by confining every part of their <hi>inferiour Globe,</hi> to ſuch Rules of obedience to their <hi>Governours,</hi> and to ſuch Agreements among themſelves, that good Influences might reciprocally deſcend and aſcend to preſerve the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>well-being</hi> of both; Which by prudent men, having courage, fearing GOD, and hating covetouſneſs, might have been effected by the <hi>power</hi> which they had once, yea, oftentimes, in their hands; and made up theſe three Nations into one well-tempered Body, though conſiſting of many thouſands
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118433:7"/>diſagreeing in <hi>Judgements, Manners,</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi> (ſome good, ſome evil, ſome indifferent) ſo that they might have peaceably been made ſerviceable to GOD, and to each other, as a skilful <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary</hi> makes a wholſome <hi>confection,</hi> by mixing many Simples of contrary qualities; even of <hi>Vipers, Serpents,</hi> and ſome <hi>Drugs poyſonous in their own nature,</hi> which in <hi>Compoſition,</hi> make the beſt <hi>Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients</hi> the more vertuous. To this end, was an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> put into their hands, by the <hi>Sword,</hi> which if they had known how they ſhould have uſed it, would have been a comfort to <hi>good men,</hi> and a terrour to the <hi>wicked</hi> partial ſelf-ſeekers onely, to whom it hath been hitherto moſt advantageous.</p>
            <p>We fought to preſerve our <hi>Freedoms</hi> which were left, and to recover thoſe we had loſt; yea, we fought for our <hi>Laws;</hi> but, not for thoſe which were impoſed upon us, by their prevailings, who had corrupted, or over-voted our <hi>Truſtees</hi> by a Party of their own, and eſtabliſhed <hi>wickedneſs for a Law;</hi> by which means our <hi>Laws</hi> that are magnified by ſome, as if it were more haynous then <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> to ſeek to have any of them reformed, are become (in their execution at leaſt) more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive then the <hi>Sword:</hi> For, I am confident, that the needleſs expences, thereby yearly occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, do amount to much more, then all that which is yearly charged to maintain the States <hi>Fleets</hi> and <hi>Armies;</hi> and that as many, if not more, are impoveriſhed thereby every year, as were in any one year by <hi>plundering,</hi> during the late <hi>War.</hi> It would fill a Volume to enumerate the Practiſes and Formalities, occaſioning the vaſt expence and intolerable Vexations, whereto, men plunged into that miſery, are liable, eſpecially ſuch as are compelled to travel above 200 miles, four or five times in a year from their habitations. Yea, even our Trials by <hi>Juries</hi> (which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded as one of theſe moſt <hi>equal ways</hi> of determining <hi>Controverſies</hi>) is no leſs injurious then any, by reaſon of the Ignorance and Corruption of <hi>Juries,</hi> packt by as corrupt <hi>Officers;</hi> as alſo, by the ſhortneſs of the time whereto a great number of <hi>Cauſes</hi> at times of trial, are limited, both at <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> as alſo, at the <hi>Aſſizes</hi> in the <hi>Counties;</hi> where, by the ſtraightneſs of the <hi>place</hi> otherwhile, and by other conſiderable defects, <hi>Trials</hi> are frequently, ſo ſuperficially and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily ſlubber'd over; <hi>Parties,</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> (on whoſe Teſtimony the whole Livelyhood of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Families depend) ſo thronged, interrupted, diſcountenanced, or negligently heard and examined, that a <hi>Caſt at Dice</hi> would have given a cheaper and a more righteous <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict,</hi> then is paſſed in ſome <hi>Cauſes.</hi> But this is beſide my Text, and not added out of any diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to our <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Lawyers;</hi> for I honour the Laws, and the Profeſſors thereof, who are unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveable.</p>
            <p>It may be for theſe, and other <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> of that kind, (whoſe removal ſome grand <hi>Gown-men</hi> are thought to obſtruct) GOD hath ſtirred up the <hi>Sword-men</hi> to take notice of that <hi>Grievance;</hi> and ſeeing it more likely to be enlarged then removed, or made leſs, one <hi>ſin</hi> ſhall be puniſhed by another. Or, the <hi>Officers of the Army,</hi> fearing perhaps that the <hi>disbanding</hi> or <hi>diſablement</hi> of their <hi>Brigades</hi> and <hi>Regiments,</hi> was intended by ſome in <hi>Parliament,</hi> for their better carrying on of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes</hi> advantageous to their own Perſons or Factions, to the <hi>publick detriment</hi> (in which practice it is thought ſome of them can hardly be over-gone) or peradventure, they perceive that timely proviſion to ſecure this <hi>Republick</hi> from <hi>the Common Enemy</hi> was neglected; and, that not onely their Eſtates, Families and Perſons might therewith be ruined, but that the diſhonour likewiſe, of all the evil <hi>Conſequences</hi> thereof, would at laſt be imputed to them, &amp; upon theſe, or on ſome other Conſiderations have reſolved to aſſume the management of the <hi>peoples Cauſe,</hi> into their <hi>own hands</hi> for the future, and ſo to proceed in the <hi>Courſe</hi> hitherto neglected, that they may clear their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported Reputations, by uſing the Military Sword to eſtabliſh the Civil (as others at firſt ſhould have done) and then to ſheath it up again, and lay it aſide; which I pray GOD may be the worſt part of their Deſigne; and that whatſoever be deſigned by them, he will be pleaſed graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to make uſe of it for the good of theſe Nations, and pardon what was well intended, though irregularly acted.</p>
            <p>For, I hope, whether their former proceedings have been juſtifiable or not, they are not perſons of ſo little Conſcience and Humanity, that they will perſevere in what is amiſs done, when they are convinced of their errour, and that the Power which the people by their Repreſentative, firſt gave them; which is yet maintained at their coſt; and which GOD hath, at this time, permitted to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118433:8"/>reſide in them onely, (and is no where elſe viſible) ſhall not be wilfully employed to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe who truſted them, though it be a while exerciſed contrary to order, and their good liking from whom they received it: For, ſuch an <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> will be anſwerably avenged, and they would thereby become the moſt infamous <hi>Army</hi> that ever was in the world; becauſe, they have pretended to more Piety and Juſtice, then ever any <hi>Army</hi> did heretofore. The <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Perfidiouſneſs</hi> of other <hi>Armies,</hi> was but the Falſhood and Perfidiouſneſs of <hi>Heathens, Turks,</hi> or de baunched <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and it made them infamous as meer carnal men onely: But, this being an <hi>Army</hi> conſiſting of perſons not onely profeſſing <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but, having the repute of <hi>Saints</hi> alſo, their <hi>perfidiouſneſs</hi> will render them as abominable as <hi>Devils;</hi> and even they who to their own advantage make uſe of their perſons, will hate them in their hearts; be always diſtruſtful of them; and not onely ſcatter them aſſoon as poſſibly they can, but expoſe them alſo to ſuch a <hi>condition,</hi> as may diſable them to be further miſchievous hereafter, and to be juſtly abhorred of all men whereſoever they live. But, as that experience afore-mentioned which I have of ſome in this <hi>Army,</hi> makes me preſume they will not wilfully deceive our <hi>hopes of them:</hi> So their <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the many <hi>occaſions</hi> which have been given to make Them and Others juſtly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the <hi>Common Safety,</hi> inclines me to think it poſſible, that what they have lately and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore done, contrary to order, may (as to ſome of them) deſerve more then an excuſe: <hi>For,</hi> when I conſider GOD's <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> of old, with ſuch undertakings as have been proſecuted, when his <hi>honour</hi> and the <hi>ſafety of his people</hi> required them; and how the one is blaſphemed, and the other endangered at this time, I conceive that it may proceed partly from a <hi>Divine Impulſe;</hi> whereof (though I cannot be ſo aſſured) they who have been <hi>Leading Actors</hi> therein, may be aſcertained by what Spirit they were moved.</p>
            <p>Whilſt I was writing this, I caſt mine eyes upon a Copy of thoſe <hi>Papers</hi> aforementioned, (then lying before me) which I preſented to the firſt <hi>Protector,</hi> and wherein are expreſſed thoſe <hi>Concomitant Circumſtances,</hi> which be requiſite to warrantize an <hi>irregular Act:</hi> Therefore, I will here inſert them, word for word, as they are there) becauſe, perhaps it may come to the knowledge of ſome who will now need thoſe <hi>Cautions,</hi> as much as the <hi>Protector</hi> did heretofore. They are theſe ten.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, there muſt be an unfeigned, and an apparent</hi> neceſſity <hi>of deviating from</hi> Rule <hi>and</hi> Order; <hi>at leaſt ſuch a</hi> neceſſity <hi>as is apparent to the</hi> Actor, <hi>and which may, or might have been apparent to others, who had like means to be informed thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, it muſt be for preſervation of a</hi> nobler Intereſt, Authority <hi>or</hi> Command, <hi>then that which is thereby</hi> violated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, it muſt be practiſed in</hi> Faith, <hi>without any</hi> ſelf-end <hi>or</hi> by-reſpect <hi>to private</hi> Intereſts, <hi>(ſuch onely excepted, as are ſo naturally therewith wrapt up, that they cannot be ſeparated.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, there muſt be warrantable</hi> Example <hi>in holy Scripture, of like practiſes in like caſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly, there muſt be an</hi> outward calling <hi>thereto, by the Office of the undertaker, either Spiritual, Civil or Military, or an</hi> extraordinary calling <hi>evidenced by ſome gift or qualification proper to that undertaking, or by an appearance of GOD's preſence with him, by ſome evident work of</hi> Providence <hi>not common.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly, there muſt be a</hi> viſible power <hi>in ſome meaſure, enabling the</hi> Proſecutor <hi>in probability, at leaſt, to begin, continue and finiſh his part of the enterprize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly, it muſt be done in</hi> Charity, <hi>without Envy, Hatred, Malice, or a Revengeful mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly, there muſt be an</hi> internal Energie <hi>of the</hi> Spirit of GOD, <hi>witneſſing to his Conſcience that he aims onely, or at leaſt chiefly, at His Glory; and ſtrengthning him, to ſuffer undauntedly, contentedly, and modeſtly, with ſubmiſſion to</hi> GOD's Will, <hi>if the</hi> Enterprize <hi>miſcarry; and not with that dejected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, impatience, or deſperateneſs, which is in</hi> Impoſtors <hi>and</hi> Malefactors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly, he muſt not willingly permit any other to</hi> bear the outward penalty <hi>due by the Law for his irregularity, but rather offer his own perſon to thoſe who are to preſerve</hi> order, <hi>and depend on GOD onely, for the reward of his</hi> undertaking; <hi>ſeeing, men cannot take notice of GOD's ſecret diſpenſations; for it is</hi> ſin <hi>againſt the outward</hi> Rule, <hi>to do</hi> evil <hi>that</hi> good <hi>may come thereof, as well-meaning men ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118433:8"/>do; though it be a</hi> greater ſin <hi>to do</hi> good, <hi>that</hi> evil purpoſes <hi>may take effect, as</hi> Hypocrites <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly, He that acts to the Breach of at Law by a</hi> Divine impulſe, <hi>will nevertheleſs finde in his heart, ſuch a reſpect to</hi> Order, <hi>that he will unfainedly be induſtrious to reduce all things to their</hi> priſtine orderly Courſe, <hi>aſſoon as the neceſſity which conſtrained his irregularity, is ſo evidently removed, that it may be ſafely done; except it ſhall ſo come to paſs, that</hi> Providence, <hi>from thenceforward, ſhall change the old</hi> Foundations, <hi>and order all things anew, as ſometimes it is pleaſed to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Without theſe afore-written</hi> Concomitants, <hi>the Proſecutors of</hi> irregular actings, (<hi>though their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions may poſſibly be good, and their attempts be permitted by</hi> Divine Juſtice, <hi>to prepare her way, to what ſhall afterward be executed according to GOD's purpoſe</hi>) <hi>are deluded by the Devil, or by their own Luſts and Paſſions, to be brought to condign puniſhment for ſome known or ſecret ſins formerly committed, rather then warrantably called: Yea, and when men are duly called to ſuch</hi> attempts, <hi>and the main work which GOD intended thereby, is outwardly accompliſhed for his glory and the publick welfare, yet if there be a defect of any ſuch</hi> Circumſtance <hi>or</hi> Qualification <hi>as is eſſential to the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification thereof, or at least, any falſhood or hypocriſie unrepented of, relating thereto, in the</hi> Actors, <hi>they will thereby loſe much of their honour and reward.</hi> Thus much is tranſcribed out of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Addreſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Now whether that which was acted enormouſly by the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> was accompanied with the fore-mentioned Circumſtances, or not, it will more concern them then us, to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of: We can have no certainty of it, becauſe it is a <hi>Tranſaction</hi> between GOD and their <hi>Conſciences</hi> onely; but of this we may be certain, to preſerve in us a charitable hope of them, that there may be ſometime <hi>extraordinary actings</hi> contrary to <hi>ordinary ſtanding Laws and Orders,</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>well-pleaſed Will of GOD,</hi> both internally and externally warranted: For <hi>Phineas</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſingle knowledge of a tranſgreſſion committed, executed <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon the <hi>Offenders</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an <hi>ordinary Commiſſion,</hi> yet he was highly honoured and rewarded for it; and <hi>Jehu</hi> ſlew the King his Maſter, which by <hi>Our</hi> Law made him guilty of a double Treaſon, and High Treaſon it was queſtionleſly accounted by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law; yet <hi>GOD</hi> recompenced it with a Kingdom; which his Poſterity ſhould have inherited for that ſervice, if he and they had but performed thoſe conditions whereupon it might have been confirmed. If it be alledged, He was <hi>viſibly anointed</hi> to that purpoſe by a Prophet; I may anſwer, That of little force his anointing had been, if there had not been alſo, a <hi>spiritual anointing,</hi> much more effectual, poured out in viſibly, upon him, and his Companions: for <hi>Jehu</hi> in himſelf, was conſiderable for nothing (that we know of) but his <hi>furious march:</hi> and his Companions (as their own words imply) judged the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet who anointed him, to be a <hi>mad fellow,</hi> by his deportment: and (for ought I perceive) the <hi>Jews,</hi> for the moſt part, in thoſe and future times, had no better opinion of their Prophets, then men have in theſe dayes of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and of ſome other among us, becauſe many of their actings, whereby they were made ſignes, to that Generation, appeared to them as ridiculous, as thoſe which are perhaps permitted at this time, to be ſignal to us. And what would then the viſible pouring forth of Oyl have effected, without a <hi>spiritual anointing,</hi> which like the <hi>white ſtone,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is onely known to him that hath it? This conſideration, with ſuch-like, makes me think fitter, to look to my own Actions, and Warranties for them, then to judge of other mens proceedings, whoſe Warrants I cannot know.</p>
            <p>This I well know, That we are in an exceeding deſperate condition; and like the <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Mice</hi> preparing to a Battel, which if not prevented, will expoſe us to the <hi>Kite;</hi> nay, we are in a far greater hazard, according to my apprehenſion of it: for, we appear to my <hi>Fancie,</hi> not unfit to be reſembled (in what may probably befal us) to a great number of <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>Lyons; Bears</hi> and <hi>Dogs; Men</hi> and <hi>Horſes; Tygers</hi> and <hi>Goats; Wolves</hi> and <hi>Sheep; Foxes</hi> and <hi>Lambs; Swine</hi> and <hi>Leopards; Women</hi> and <hi>Children; Innocents</hi> and <hi>Malefactors;</hi> armed and unarmed; Princes and Peaſants; Paſtors and their Flocks; Old and Young; Poor and Rich; thruſt and throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all together promiſcuouſly into the <hi>Cirque</hi> of a <hi>Theater,</hi> to be torn and to tear each other to pieces: whilſt our Neighbours, Foes and Friends, (if we have any) ſit Spectators on ſeats round
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118433:9"/>about, to behold that horrible Spectacle, till we being deſtroyed, or wearied with deſtroying each other, they may come down without danger to themſelves, and divide the ſpoil of that which is left, poſſeſs our Eſtates, and make ſlaves of our perſons: yet, that <hi>Herd of Beaſts,</hi> which we call the <hi>common People,</hi> is ſo ſtupid and inſenſible of what is likely to come upon them, that like natural Fools, they ſit grinning on each other, in thoſe meeting places, where they recreate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by hearing and repeating thoſe things, which are beginnings of their own deſtruction; run together with a brutiſh delight, to be Spectators of their own miſeries and maſſacres to enſue, if an over-ruling Providence prevent it not; and like <hi>mad-men,</hi> rejoyce when they think it begun. Of this I my ſelf have often took notice, and particularly upon that day whereon the Parliament was laſt interrupted. For, when by the Vollies of Shot, it was in <hi>London</hi> ſuppoſed that the Parliaments Guards, and the Armies Forces were engaged, the people who then flocked into the Temple, to look toward <hi>Veſtminſter,</hi> where they hoped that <hi>Engagament</hi> was begun, did in my ſight and hearing, expreſs their barbarous joy, with ſo much diſaffection to both Parties, and with ſuch unchriſtian Language, and unmanly Geſticulations, that being filled with grief, and tranſported with indignation, I could not withhold from openly reproving them. O GOD! <hi>By what ordinary courſe is ſuch a Frenzie curable? whoſe power can calm the rage of ſuch Waters, but thine onely,</hi> who commandeſt <hi>the ſtorming Winds,</hi> and art obeyed? and when thou ſayeſt to the Seas, <hi>Proceed no further?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Veſſel</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> now weather-beaten and torn, is in more danger then that, wherein <hi>jonas</hi> would have fled to <hi>Tarſus;</hi> for, though we have caſt forth a great part of our Goods to ſecure it, our danger ſtill continues, and increaſeth; and we are not ſo ſenſible of it, nor ſo much think upon GOD, or on our ſins, which are the cauſe of it, as the <hi>Heathen Mariners</hi> then did. Moreover, that Ship, had but one Delinquent which occaſioned the Storm; and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thrown into the Sea, brought immediate ſafety: They had many Skilful Sea-men to guide it; but all our Pilots are caſt over-board, and none left in appearance, but guilty Paſſengers: This, might make me deſpair; yet my Hope is greater then my Fear, by contemplating GOD's mercy to <hi>Jonas:</hi> For, though he were a Delinquent, who had knowingly offended, as it were in a contempt of GOD; though, he were caſt out into the Sea, far from Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, where was no hope of eſcaping; though it was when that Sea was ſo extraordinarily enraged by a Storm, that it made ſafety leſs hopeful; and though he was then ſwallowed by a Whale, which was as it were conveying of him down quick to Hell, (as he himſelf apprehended it) from whence there is no redemption; yet he was preferved by that which was naturally, irrecoverably of it ſelf, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; and vouchſafed alſo ſo much Grace, as to be imployed again in the ſervice of him, and by him, againſt whom he had been rebellious. <hi>Oh GOD! how infinite are thy Mercies!</hi> and how exceeding merciful are the ſevereſt of thy Judgements!</p>
            <p>Yet, becauſe GOD expects, that, in all emergencies and extremities, we ſhould uſe the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and grace that he hath given us, as the Mariners and Paſſengers then did, toward our preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and not as <hi>Jonas,</hi> retire into our private Cabins, nor into the Holds, and there ſleep out this Storm; I have kept my ſelf waking, whilſt other men ſlept; to look upward, inward, and round about me, every way from whence means of Salvation may come, (or, whereby, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of danger may be prevented) that I may ſtir up my ſelf and others to meet GOD, who is alway ready to provide it, and come along with it, if he be ſought for in time. I have conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what ſome might have done, but now cannot; what ſome, other may yet do, but will not: what many intend, and will do, if they can, to undo us; and what we ſhould and may do, if we loſe not opportunities yet offered, by pride, partiality, ſelf-ſeeking, and conſuming that ſtrength which is left, in oppoſing each other, and them who perhaps, by an irregularity providentially permitted, are brought into a ſtraight, for the preſent, that we might be thereby inlarged for ever after; and be better ſecured by a <hi>Storm</hi> and a <hi>Whale,</hi> then by the <hi>Ship</hi> in which we were ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a <hi>wrong courſe;</hi> yea, peradventure by this Breach (which makes our Enemies cry, <hi>Aha! ſo we would have it!</hi>) that ſhall be occaſioned, which will cement the Hearts of our Governours, of our Armies, and of the people, more ſtrongly, and more affectionately then ever heretofore. It is not now a ſeaſon wherein to purſue Vengeance: When <hi>Shimei</hi> curſed his King, and <hi>Joah</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118433:9"/>would have taken off his head for it; <hi>David</hi> thought it poſſible that <hi>GOD</hi> might commiſſion him to curſe; and whether it were ſo or not, he prudentially judged it unſeaſonable to avenge an injury done to him, and puniſh a fault in another, when he lay under a Chaſtiſement for his own, greater tranſgreſſions againſt a greater King then himſelf. <hi>GOD,</hi> hath winked at ſo many of our failings, and that ſo often, that we are obliged to wink at each others eſcapes. Our <hi>Princes, Parliaments, People</hi> and <hi>Armies,</hi> have complained of each other; but, the truth is, we are all become ſo guilty, and have ſo many ways given occaſions of provoking each other, as well as of diſpleaſing <hi>GOD;</hi> and of increaſing both our <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>puniſhments;</hi> that, if there be not a more <hi>Chriſtian Forbearance,</hi> more <hi>Unity, Love</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> among us, (then yet I ſee) and a ſpeedy endeavouring joyntly and ſingly toward an unfeigned agreement, in <hi>Civil Concernments;</hi> then, as firſt the <hi>Regal,</hi> and then the <hi>Parliamentary power</hi> was deſtroyed; ſo, ſhall firſt the <hi>Army,</hi> and then the <hi>People,</hi> be deprived of their <hi>Power;</hi> and this perhaps to let in another <hi>Party</hi> as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as themſelves, or worſe, to be plagued and rooted out among them, to make room for a more pious and <hi>Righteous Generation,</hi> if we be not in time warned by other mens examples.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Queſtion</hi> ſomewhat like one of thoſe which you propounded to me, was propoſed by <hi>David,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>When the Foundations are overthrown, what ſhall the righteous do?</hi> but he himſelf thereto implies an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> in the words next following; for there he ſheweth, what <hi>GOD</hi> will do, and what will at ſuch times be the <hi>portion</hi> both of thoſe who have righteouſly or unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acted: <hi>GOD</hi> give us Grace to conſider it. To prevent, what I feared, would come upon us, I have added my <hi>ſpoonfull of Water,</hi> from time to time (as occaſion was offered) toward quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the <hi>Flames</hi> which I ſaw kindling, and have ſent abroad many <hi>Remembrances</hi> and <hi>Cave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ats,</hi> which have been as ineffectual, as if I had written to the <hi>mad men in Bedlam</hi> to perſwade them to be ſober; and yet I am ſtill moved by ſomewhat, which will not let me be quiet (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my late reſolution to the contrary) to adventure my <hi>Notions</hi> toward their cure, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in private, as I do at this preſent to you: And, ſince the late <hi>Rupture,</hi> have looked ſeriouſly toward thoſe <hi>four Winds,</hi> kept by <hi>four Angels,</hi> who are commanded to let them breathe, or reſtrain them, as <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall permit them to be active, together or apart, either according to their own <hi>natural power,</hi> or as he ſhall pleaſe, by his extraordinary complyance, to make them a furtherance or an obſtruction to our <hi>Settlement.</hi> And, now, in regard many men depending much upon <hi>meer natural Cauſes,</hi> have raiſed expectations from them, according to their ſeveral hopes and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I will inform you, what upon inquiry into their <hi>ſelf-ſufficiency,</hi> may probably come or not come from them reſpectively, (leaving <hi>GOD's unrevealed determinations</hi> to his own good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) there are, I ſay, four <hi>Mountains,</hi> from whence mens Windy Hopes iſſue, and they are theſe: 1. <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and his Party: 2. The <hi>Parliamentary Authority,</hi> which was, and ſeems in a poſſibility of reviving again: 3. The <hi>Body of the People,</hi> whom they repreſented: And laſtly, the <hi>Armies</hi> now in being: of which <hi>Four,</hi> I will diſcourſe in order, and declare what I perceive probable to proceed from them, according to my underſtanding; and leave it to be conſidered, and cenſured, as you and they ſhall pleaſe, to whoſe view it ſhall come.</p>
            <p>The coming in of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> is much deſired and wiſhed for, by thoſe who aim at their preſent, quiet and perſonal, or worldly advantages onely, becauſe they neither underſtand nor care for that which will be moſt for <hi>GOD</hi>'s Glory, or the publick Welfare hereafter, ſo they may have a ſpeedy Settlement upon any terms, which will put quickeſt end to our preſent Troubles. But, his coming with ſuch a conſequence as they dream of, will neither be ſo ſpeedy, nor the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel ſo ſatisfactory as they imagine; for though the late <hi>Breach</hi> ſhould make the way eaſier then it was; Yet if he come by <hi>force,</hi> he will find a rugged <hi>paſſage,</hi> and long and dangerous <hi>marches</hi> before he arrive at <hi>White-hall;</hi> and may be ſtaid a while alſo, to ſee ſome playing at <hi>Duck</hi> and <hi>Drake,</hi> upon the great waters in his way hitherward, and what Wagers will be tride about <hi>diving</hi> and <hi>ſwimming</hi> before he comes on ſhore. The <hi>Pond</hi> over which he muſt paſs, is ſo great, that he will hardly finde means to waft himſelf and all the <hi>Beggers</hi> and <hi>Baggages</hi> that muſt be brought along with him, unleſs our good <hi>Friends</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> help him; who, we hope, will either be more honeſt, or at leaſt ſo politick, as to conſider, that if <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> (as the report goes) will aſſiſt him, upon a deſigne to propagate their <hi>Religion,</hi> and uphold <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as well their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118433:10"/>and <hi>Religion,</hi> will be in danger, as ours; and that if they of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> or either of them, prevail to ſettle an obliged Friend to their Cauſe on this ſide of them, to hold the <hi>Dutch</hi> play upon the Water, they will hew out a paſſage well enough on the other ſide by Land, to the <hi>Spaniſh Kings</hi> old Inheritance, to which no <hi>Preſcription</hi> is a bar, by a <hi>Royal Maxime:</hi> But, though <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Dutch, Dane,</hi> and <hi>Devil</hi> to boot, ſhould aſſiſt him, yet he may come ſhort; and I believe, moſt of thoſe who long for his coming, will looſe much of their preſent enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of their faireſt future hopes alſo, before <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> arriveth here in peace; and perhaps ſpeed worſe then ſo, before he be ſettled: For, they, who have paid dearly for what they conquered from his Father, will ſell it at a rate much dearer, before they forgo their intereſt: And it is infallibly evident to every man of underſtanding, that if he comes in by force, it cannot be without their Forraign Ayd, which over and above thoſe many thouſands of diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, debauched and beggerly <hi>Scots, Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> (which wait for ſuch a time) will ſpue out after them into theſe <hi>Iſlands,</hi> all the Bandetti, Thieves, Rogues, needy Perſons, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſeful Souldiers which over-burthen their Countries already; ſo that this place will then be an Epitomy of Hell, where all ſhall be tormented by thoſe Furies and Devils incarnate, which will be brought in thereby: For, it will be impoſſible then, to make diſtinction between Friends and Foes to the Commonwealth, who have not Swords in their hands; neither will it be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if they have any thing to looſe; and if he prevail at laſt by a Forraign Ayd, the beſt that can be expected by the greateſt part of the Natives, is to be enſlaved under all manner of Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, both Spiritual and Temporal; the apprehenſion of which, will make all thoſe who have either Religion, Honeſty, or Love to their Country, or to Themſelves, fight it out to the laſt man: and theſe things conſidered, there will be no probability of a happy or ſpeedy Settlement, if <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> come in by force.</p>
            <p>But, it is hoped by ſome few, that he will come in by compact and conſent, upon ſuch terms as will render his coming acceptable. Well, admit this, and alſo grant that his Afflictions had prepared his heart, to offer or accept of ſuch conditions as may preſerve the Temporal and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Freedoms, due to the people by the Laws of <hi>GOD</hi> and Nature; and that he would covenant to ſecure us in a future enjoyment of our Eſtates and Conſciences under a Righteous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in ſuch manner, that he and we by <hi>GOD</hi>'s Bleſſing, may be happy in each other. Grant alſo, there were a willingneſs and a reciprocal Condeſcention on both ſides, without Fraud, to all reaſonable Propoſitions; and that his Party now in exile, would be contented with ſuch a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable allowance, as might not be over-burthenſome to the Commonwealth, whereto the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of ſome, and the generoſity of others, may poſſibly incline them to accord: Yet how ſhould ſuch an Agreement be begun, proſecuted or ſecured? I know no ſafe <hi>Medium</hi> whereby this may be made feiſible. Stones and Sand will never make a Building without Lime, or ſome other gluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous matter. If the Dutch ſhould interpoſe, they might perhaps mediate more for their own advantage then for his or ours: ſo probably would the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> alſo, whoſe Deſignes would be more advanced, by our continuing diſagreements, then by our reconciliation: and we ſhall find a pad of miſchief in the ſtraw, if they have any hand in it; and receive, it may be, a <hi>Snake</hi> into our boſome, if he ſhould be admitted by their mediation: for it may rationally be ſuſpected, that they will not appear for him either in an <hi>amicable or hoſtile manner,</hi> without hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome concealed Engagement of his to them, or to one of them, which may be hereafter diſadvantageous to our Spiritual or Temporal Freedoms, or both: and if he ſhould be ſecretly reconciled to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> during his abode, among them, by thoſe opportunities which they have had to work upon him, and then come over, ſeaſoned with this Principle of theirs, <hi>That no Faith or Contract, is to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> (and we then appear to be ſuch in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem) what ſecurity ſhall we have, whereupon we can ſafely depend?</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is conſiderable, that to make an honourable and laſting reconciliation, he muſt not onely come in with the love and aſſent of that part of the people who will inſiſt upon the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their juſt Freedoms claimed; but he muſt alſo firſt renounce that pretended Right which he claims as due from his <hi>Progenitors:</hi> for, if he ſtill think that to be a right inherent in himſelf, as many abſurdly do, (becauſe they neither underſtand right <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Law</hi>) and if the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118433:10"/>people ſhall receive him without abjuration of that Claim, they do thereby make voyd the <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> which <hi>GOD</hi> hath given on their part, at the <hi>Trial</hi> by <hi>Combat;</hi> &amp; give away for ever, that which they recovered by <hi>Conqueſt:</hi> and ſo, by our <hi>Atonement,</hi> we ſhall but prorogue our Troubles at beſt, till <hi>he</hi> or his <hi>poſterity</hi> have acquired power to renew the old quarrel upon this falſe Maxime, <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Tempus occurrit Regi;</hi> thoug the truth is, <hi>Nullum Tempus occurrit populo,</hi> no time or <hi>Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> is a juſt bar to the <hi>Peoples Right;</hi> for whoſe ſake, <hi>Kings</hi> (being but their ſervants) were at firſt ordained. Though I have ſhewed it before, yet I will here again briefly touch upon the ſtate of our Cauſe, becauſe it is not well enough heeded.</p>
            <p>This people lately claimed their natural Freedoms, which the <hi>King</hi> had uſurped: the <hi>King</hi> claimed, likewiſe, his long <hi>uſurped Prerogatives:</hi> after a tedious conteſt on both ſides, they at length joyntly appealed to <hi>GOD,</hi> to give ſentence according to Juſtice, upon a Tryal by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, as it is manifeſted by the Words, for Diſtinction, given out by both Parties, when they joyned <hi>Battel: GOD,</hi> by making the Peoples Champions Conquerers, gave Judgment on their behalf: Thereupon the King and his Party quitted the three Kingdoms, and left the Conquerors in quiet and abſolute poſſeſſion; and all the Kings and Commonwealths of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> taking notice both of the <hi>proceſs</hi> and <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> witneſſed that Reſtauration of their juſt Rights, by making Addreſſes to them as the <hi>Soveraign Power:</hi> all which undeniably demonſtrate, a <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> whereby all the pretended right of <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> and his heirs, was as peremptorily cut off, as ever the like Claim was heretofore from any <hi>Family</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> at the tranſlation of any Government from one perſon or Family to another, in any <hi>Kingdome</hi> or <hi>Empire,</hi> ſince the World began. And, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can be alleaged to the contrary, or, whoſoever murmurs againſt this Verdict, or ſhall aſſiſt him (if he be of this <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) to poſſeſs his pretended Claim to theſe <hi>Iſlands,</hi> is a Traytor to his <hi>Country,</hi> and a Reſiſter of <hi>GOD</hi>'s <hi>doom;</hi> and none but preſumptuous, ignorant, debauched or ſlaviſh-minded perſons, will perſevere after all this evidence, and finall Decree in <hi>GOD's Court-Martial,</hi> (from whence (as I ſaid) there is no appeal) to oppoſe the <hi>Conquerors Title,</hi> or reproach them as <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors,</hi> as yet ſome impudently do. This is briefly, the true ſtate of that Cauſe, which is in deciſion termed by our Adverſaries, (and ſcornfully by ſome <hi>Cox-combs</hi>) who are Enemies to themſelves) <hi>The Good Old Cauſe:</hi> and this being duly conſidered, <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> hath, in my underſtanding, no more Legal Right to theſe Iſlands, then I have to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He cannot juſtly be admitted hither, but on ſuch terms as may preſerve the <hi>Peoples Interest,</hi> unleſs <hi>GOD</hi> in wrath admit him, for a puniſhment of our ſins, and to be a plague to thoſe who deſire it in contempt of his diſpenſations; which otherwiſe, neither our preſent diviſions, or the power of all his Confederates beyond the Seas, would be able to effect, notwithſtanding the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative ſottiſhneſs of ſome among us, who ſeem fit to be governed by none but a <hi>Tyrant;</hi> and by whom <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> himſelf would be ſufficiently plagued, whether he be tyrannically incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or not, if the Government of them ſhould be on him impoſed: For, though ſome deſire his coming, it is not in love for his own ſake; but, in hope to enjoy under him, a licentious Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and upon the leaſt failing of their expectations in that hope, they would cry <hi>Crucifie him,</hi> the next day after they cryed <hi>Hoſanna;</hi> and wiſh for thoſe again, whom they now revile: For, many of them, are the ſame perſons who oppoſed, reviled, and purſued his Father even to his death; and againſt him, who ſhould rule over them piouſly and righteouſly, they would be much more exaſperated. This is not a raſh cenſure, founded upon paſſion or conjectures; but, a probable concluſion, on that long experience which I have had of the giddineſs, malice, and bruitiſh condition of that inconſiderate <hi>Rabble,</hi> which makes the loudeſt Clamours, and who are tranſported with the greateſt <hi>madneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No private intereſt makes me a verſe to <hi>Charles Stuarts</hi> admittance, neither have I any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection to his perſon; for, I never received in jury by him: But my averſeneſs, is meerly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to my Country, which, in my underſtanding, cannot enjoy a happy Peace, together with his perſon, as affairs now ſtand, in relation to <hi>Him,</hi> to his <hi>Confederates,</hi> and to this <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> I deſire nothing, by endeavouring to bar him, or any other, from that which he, or they ought in Juſtice to poſſeſs; and, though I may ſuſpect that my Actings againſt him for preſervation of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118433:11"/>the <hi>Common Liberties,</hi> will render me liable to his fury, and to the rage of his <hi>Party,</hi> I ſhall be no more afraid of him, though re-admitted to morrow, then he is now of me, though he ſhould come, both with an unreſtrained Power, and a revengeful Mind; becauſe, I have diſcharged a good Conſcience, even in doing that which may moſt offend him. Nay, upon Conſiderations of another nature, I ſhall have no cauſe to fear him, or to think I ſhall be more cruelly dealt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al by him, then I have been by thoſe in power, among whom I now live, though he ſhould take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my <hi>Life:</hi> For, though I have ſerved the late <hi>Powers</hi> faithfully, with my <hi>Eſtate, Perſon</hi> and <hi>Credit;</hi> yet, by their long neglect of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> in ſome things, and by their actual Injuſtice, in ſome other things, they have ſo expoſed me to contempt, and ſo nigh ruined me, both in my <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> without which <hi>Life</hi> is little worth; that, <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> cannot be ſo unmerciful to me as they have been, except, when I am quite deprived of my <hi>Livelyhood</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> he ſhould ſuffer me to live, until I ſaw likewiſe, the deſtruction of my <hi>Family</hi> and the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> whoſe welfare is to me more precious then <hi>Life;</hi> though, for all my Contributions and Services, (to the endangering of my Life, Eſtate and Credit) I could not obtain ſo much favor, toward the relief of my <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> as to have one <hi>Petition</hi> read in her <hi>Grand Aſſemblies</hi> during above nine years continual Sollicitations. In brief; as in relation to my ſelf, I have no reaſon to reſpect any one of the former <hi>Powers</hi> more then the other; for, as the Porter ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever were King, he ſhould be but a Porter;</hi> ſo, I may ſay, if they who ſhall come hereafter, be not more righteous then they who ruled heretofore, I am ſure to have but little <hi>Favour,</hi> and much <hi>Miſchief:</hi> and as for <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> in particular, if he comes hither by that <hi>paſſage,</hi> which we are likely to make for him at this time, and ſhall walk in <hi>ways</hi> no better then his <hi>Progenitors,</hi> and our late <hi>Governours</hi> have trod, I cannot have ſo much cauſe to dread him, as he will have to be afraid of <hi>himſelf;</hi> and I ſhall do him better ſervice, perhaps, (if I live to ſee him here in power) then any one of them, who moſt deſire his coming: For, as I did to his <hi>Father,</hi> and his <hi>Succeſſours,</hi> I will make bold (though with as little thanks or belief) to tell him plainly and truly, what will befal him and his Poſterity; and then, I think, my work will be at an end, and I ſhall leave the Stage.</p>
            <p>Now, I have done with <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> unleſs <hi>GOD's</hi> indignation ſends him thither; and then I muſt endure the <hi>Storm,</hi> (as well as GOD ſhall enable me) which will iſſue from that <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> (and I verily believe, that will be well enough, becauſe (though I affect them not) I am uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſafeſt in <hi>Storms;</hi> and thrive beſt, by GOD's mercy, when my greateſt Enemies, think they ſhall irrecoverably undo me.) I perceive, that neither ſuch <hi>peaceable Gales,</hi> as many expect, are likely to proceed thence, nor ſuch dreadful <hi>Tempeſts</hi> as are by ſome feared, if we make them not great by our own defaults: and therefore, I will turn toward the next <hi>Mountain</hi> (the late diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Parliament</hi>) if I know where to finde it; which will he a very hard matter; for, the <hi>Father</hi> of it is dead; the <hi>Mother</hi> upon which it was begotten, knows not whither it is departed; and in the place where it was born, lived and acted, I find here and there a <hi>Limb;</hi> but, of ſo many uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as may make them a <hi>Parliament,</hi> I cannot hear any news; no nor ſo much as a Paper from any one <hi>Member,</hi> laying claim to their <hi>loſt power.</hi> All I hear, of it, is but <hi>Ecchoes,</hi> which ſignifie little; or, ſome <hi>raging ſounds,</hi> implying that wrathful indignation, which will never accompliſh the will of <hi>GOD;</hi> or, elſe ſcurrilous Invectives, ſcattered by we know not whom, without <hi>names;</hi> and raiſed perhaps from private Suppoſitions, conducing onely to an inlargement of the late <hi>Breach,</hi> as if deſigned by the <hi>Common Adverſary</hi> to that end; and by ſuch as are acceſſary to that endeavour <hi>GOD,</hi> who raiſed up <hi>Lazarus,</hi> when he was dead, buried, &amp; ſtunk, may (if he pleaſe) once again reſtore it; and what he will do, no man knows; but, in common Reaſon, we can have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hope of it, or, of having any <hi>Deliverance</hi> from our hazards, by that, whereto we can make no <hi>Addreſs,</hi> and which had not power enough to ſave it ſelf, when it had a <hi>viſible Authority.</hi> The Horſes, which drew their Chariot, like thoſe in the Fable of <hi>Hippolitus,</hi> being frighted, hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown it, daſht it into pieces; and ſo ſcattered their <hi>Members,</hi> that ſhould <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> undertake the cure, he could not ſet them together again. When they were in <hi>being,</hi> and had <hi>Authority de Facto,</hi> (though ſome think not <hi>de jure</hi>) we were obliged to be obedient whilſt that <hi>Being</hi> laſted, becauſe there was no other <hi>viſible power,</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Comon Peace.</hi> We had then ſome hope
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118433:11"/>they might (though made lawful by neceſſity onely, have been a means of conſtituting a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Parliament,</hi> then they themſelves were: but, what can we now hope for from them? Or what ſubjection owe we to that, which if it had ſome <hi>being,</hi> can give us no protection in our obedience? Or unto whoſe uſe ought thoſe <hi>Fragments</hi> and <hi>Fractions</hi> of the <hi>Power,</hi> which was delegated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by them into particular hands, be now imployed, but, to their uſe, and for their ſafety, by whom that <hi>now-inviſible Repreſentative,</hi> was intruſted? Let us not then, deceive our ſelves with <hi>Shadows,</hi> and run after <hi>Voyces in the dark,</hi> which come we neither know <hi>whence,</hi> or from <hi>whence,</hi> leſt we fall into a <hi>bottomleſs Pit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Mountain</hi> is now quite breathleſs; there breathes no <hi>Wind</hi> from it, nor can, unleſs <hi>GOD</hi> extraordinarily breathe again into it; and therefore we are to addreſs our ſelves to that <hi>viſible Power,</hi> which <hi>GOD</hi> hath permitted to riſe up in the ſtead thereof, by what means ſoever it was advanced: for, though perhaps it was treaſonably acquired, <hi>that which ought not to have been done, being done, is of force;</hi> and it was juſtly permitted of <hi>GOD,</hi> though unjuſtly acted by men; and the Act was of <hi>GOD,</hi> though the obliquity of the Act, was their who perpetrated the ſame; as the rending of <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> from the houſe of <hi>Solomon,</hi> was of <hi>GOD,</hi> though it was treaſonably proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Jeroboam:</hi> and they who armed themſelves to reduce them to their former ſubjection, (as perhaps we now intend to do) were ſo told, and thereupon deſiſted from their purpoſe. This conſidered, they who at this preſent, exerciſe the <hi>ſupreme power</hi> over theſe Nations; and they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who received heretofore power by Commiſſions from the late <hi>Repreſentative</hi> whilſt it was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, muſt (as well for the ſafety of the whole <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> as for their own ſecurity) preſerve that <hi>Power,</hi> as intire as they can, for their ſafe-guard, whoſe ſafety was thereby primarily inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and ought not to ſacrifice it, either to <hi>Revenge,</hi> or to the <hi>Ghoſt</hi> of that Body, whereto they have now no Obligation; and eſſentially violate their <hi>Truſt</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> under colour of preſerving fidelity to the ſhadow of their <hi>Inviſible Repreſentative,</hi> leſt they finde at laſt, they were deluded by their own Corruption, or by a <hi>deceitful Spirit:</hi> And they in particular, who have aſſumed the <hi>Soveraign Power,</hi> inſtead of that which is aboliſhed, or ſuſpended, ought not to deal ſeverely with ſuch as not out of <hi>wilfulneſs,</hi> but rather in Conſcience, and through want of due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, ſhall not comply therewith, until they have means to be fully informed, what in <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> they are obliged unto, in ſo extraordinary an <hi>Emergency.</hi> In the whole, I could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover no likelyhood of help, in our preſent neceſſities, from that <hi>Mountain;</hi> and, perhaps, <hi>GOD</hi> hath buried it, as he did the Body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> no man knows where, leſt they who truſted over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much in it, might commit <hi>Idolatry</hi> again therewith, and think he could no way elſe deliver them from their Oppreſſours, but by that <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third <hi>Mountain,</hi> which with the <hi>Wind</hi> from thence blowing, will be next conſiderable, is the <hi>Grand Body of the people,</hi> whom they repreſented, whoſe Limbs, are now ſcattered. From this <hi>Mountain,</hi> I hear as it were the ſound of a <hi>mighty Wind,</hi> but can perceive no product likely to be anſwerable to the noiſe it makes, nor any birth at preſent more conſiderable then a <hi>Mouſe.</hi> It is expected perhaps, that the people will be avenged upon thoſe who have deſtroyed their <hi>Image,</hi> and offered violence to their late <hi>Repreſentative;</hi> but <hi>Cui bono,</hi> to what purpoſe, if it were of <hi>GOD?</hi> They will raiſe up a <hi>Power,</hi> ſome think, to proſecute alſo their <hi>Cauſe.</hi> That's a dream, (if not an impoſſibility) likely to produce ſuch an event, as the rage of the men of <hi>Ophra</hi> had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Gideon,</hi> when he brake down the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Baal;</hi> and we may as well endeavour to gather all the drops of a <hi>Showre</hi> into one Bucker, &amp; aſſoon imbody therewith the ſparklings of <hi>Char-coa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and the <hi>ſprinklings of Dew</hi> lying upon the graſs tops, into an <hi>Electuary:</hi> For, the <hi>Members</hi> of that <hi>Body,</hi> are ſo many, ſo ſcattered, and ſo divided into <hi>Factions,</hi> by their differing Judgments, Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Intereſts, that, without an <hi>over-ruling Power,</hi> they will never be brought to agree upon any <hi>Medium</hi> to preſerve themſelves; much leſs to vindicate that <hi>Parliament,</hi> which the greateſt part of them, would not acknowledge to be their lawful <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> whilſt it continued in <hi>Power:</hi> For, many of them ſought the ruine thereof, when it was in being; rejoyced when it was deſtroyed, (as they think it to be) and were ſorry for nothing, ſo much, as that the <hi>Army</hi> was not alſo therewith annihilated. Yea, not a few of thoſe who faithfully ſerved that <hi>Parliament,</hi> and conſcientiouſly did their beſt endeavour to preſerve it, were ſo diſſatisfied with their partial and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118433:12"/>unjuſt proceeding in ſome things; with their neglect in other matters, and with the dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of their <hi>Authority,</hi> that they adhered thereto, for no reſpect ſo much, as becauſe they had thereto engaged themſelves, and knew no other viſible means under <hi>GOD,</hi> ſo likely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a general and <hi>destructive Confuſion;</hi> or, elſe, for that they thought them impowered at firſt by <hi>GOD</hi>'s <hi>permiſſion,</hi> and graciouſly reſtored after their long <hi>Interruption,</hi> (for that purpoſe which they themſelves have pretended) until this people ſhould be prepared (by thoſe <hi>Changes</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he will further prove them) for ſuch a <hi>Government,</hi> as will be moſt for His Glory, and their good. In expectation of this Mercy, they, who were their <hi>Friends,</hi> now wait upon <hi>GOD,</hi> and think themſelves not obliged to endeavour an avengement upon thoſe, who have done <hi>GOD</hi>'s <hi>Work,</hi> for ought they know to the contrary; and, moſt of that part of the <hi>People</hi> who diſaffected the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> will not engage againſt the <hi>Infringers</hi> of it, in hope to ſee their own malitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne againſt the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> to take place by the removal thereof, by the diſtractions, or miſcarriages, of the <hi>Army.</hi> Upon theſe, and ſuch like Conſiderations, I concluded, that, from this <hi>Mountain,</hi> (until it were put into a better capacity) nothing could be expected anſwerable to a rational Expectation; but, ſome mad Combinations, in ſeveral parts of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> for and againſt reviving the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is doubtleſs deſigned, and will be fomented by the <hi>Common Adverſary,</hi> to make him an <hi>Inlet,</hi> and bring at laſt to his ſide, one part of their diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Forces.</p>
            <p>Then, I lifted mine eyes toward that other <hi>Hill,</hi> from whence many men look for help: to wit, the <hi>Army;</hi> for, though I expect ſalvation from that <hi>Hill</hi> onely, which over-tops all <hi>Mountains,</hi> I conſidered that alſo; and, at the firſt fixing of mine eyes upon it, I ſaw many doubtful and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible <hi>Appearances,</hi> which did a little affright me. It reſembled, me thought, <hi>a Hill with three tops, ſeemingly divided,</hi> with ſome ſlaſhes of fire, and ſmoakes breathing and iſſuing out from between them, which portended ſuch miſchiefs as many feared would enſue their diſſolving of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> For, this is the <hi>Hill</hi> which juſtled aſide that <hi>Mountain,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> was jealous it might rather prove to be <hi>Mount Ebal,</hi> whence <hi>Curſes</hi> were pronounced, then <hi>Mount Gerazim,</hi> from whence <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> could be expected; and it may poſſibly be unto us as <hi>GADS-HILL,</hi> which hath been a <hi>Hill of Robbors,</hi> as well as <hi>GODS-HILL,</hi> notwithſtanding any thing, that <hi>I</hi> can abſolutely warrant to the contrary. But, <hi>I</hi> hope better: for, as the ſins of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> made <hi>GOD</hi> incline <hi>Davids</hi> heart to diſcover the pride which was in it, by <hi>numbring the people;</hi> and then for a puniſhment of that offence, brought him into ſuch a ſtreight, that he himſelf was to chuſe whether his <hi>Penance</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Sword, Peſtilence</hi> or <hi>Famine;</hi> and upon his reſigning himſelf with penitence, to <hi>GOD</hi>'s good pleaſure, had a <hi>Correction,</hi> vouchſated in mercy, which gave occaſion of purchaſing that piece of ground, whereon the <hi>Temple</hi> was afterward erected: <hi>So,</hi> perhaps the <hi>Army,</hi> or the <hi>Officers</hi> thereof, having in ſome ſpecial manner ſinned againſt <hi>GOD;</hi> and, they, and theſe <hi>Nations</hi> being mutually occaſions of tranſgreſſions in each other, which have provoked <hi>GOD</hi> againſt both, we are brought into the like <hi>streights;</hi> which, if they produce true <hi>Repentance,</hi> with an unfeigned <hi>Reſignation</hi> of our ſelves to <hi>GOD,</hi> he will not onely correct us in mercy, but, make this <hi>Breach</hi> likewiſe, an occaſion of erecting ſuch a <hi>Government,</hi> as will together with advance of our Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, make ſome preparation for that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which will glorifie him throughout all <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe, and ſuch muſings, that <hi>Mountain,</hi> which before appeared to me as contemptible as a <hi>Mole-hill,</hi> and to ſend forth diſcomfortable blaſts, ſeemed to have a more venerable Aſpect: yea, to have much <hi>Holy Ground</hi> in it, and to breathe forth <hi>refreſhing Gales.</hi> It then appeared to me, like that <hi>Mountain,</hi> in ſome reſpects, on which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> beheld <hi>Clouds, Flames</hi> and <hi>Smoke;</hi> from which they heard a <hi>Trumpet</hi> and <hi>Thunders,</hi> and which the People were enjoyned not to touch, on penalty of being ſtoned. Methought alſo, <hi>I</hi> ſaw appearances of <hi>GOD</hi> upon it, and the <hi>Popular Mountain</hi> laſt mentioned, to move <hi>gradatim</hi> toward the ſame, &amp; therewith incorporating into one <hi>ſtrong Hill,</hi> which if our ſins hinder not, will be joyntly active and paſſive, according to my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, in the profecution of that <hi>Expedient</hi> which is moſt heroick, and which will produce many future <hi>Experiments,</hi> teaching us better to know <hi>GOD</hi>'s, our own, and other mens intentions, and the way to both our ſettlement, &amp; to that <hi>Kingdom</hi> which hath no end This <hi>Courſe,</hi> if the <hi>Army,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118433:12"/>they who have pretended to GOD's glory, and the common welfare, have reſolution and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enough to purſue as they yet may; they ſhall thereby wipe off, all former and preſent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſions, with everlaſting honour: the upbraidings and reproaches of their Malignant Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Oppreſſors, ſhall effect no more againſt them, then the barkings and bawlings of Dogs againſt the Moon: their former failings, will be means of prevailings hereafter: every Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhall ſet them two ſteps forwarder: though they were more diſabled then yet they are, the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited powers, of all their mighty Adverſaries abroad and at home, ſhall be to them, but as a Field of ſtubble before a Flame; and their over-powering them with multitudes, ſhall be but like hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping up ſtraw and dry brambles, to cover a <hi>ſtrong Fire:</hi> For, <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall return into their <hi>Camps</hi> with <hi>invincible Auxiliacies,</hi> lodge in their <hi>Head-quarters,</hi> and rejoyce in protecting and enabling them as heretofore, to the producing of miraculous effects, and to the reterting on their <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries</hi> (who are puffed up with vain hopes by their Diviſions) that ſcorn and confuſion which they expected ſhould befall theſe <hi>Iſlands</hi> are long: and I have here averred no more then <hi>GOD</hi> will perform on his part, if the <hi>Armies,</hi> and they who pretend for the <hi>common Intereſt,</hi> ſhall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatize from what is to be performed on their parts.</p>
            <p>Let them take heed to this: for, it is the effect of thoſe promiſes, which are made conditionally to all men throughout all Generations, and recorded to be transferred and applyed particularly and univerſally as occaſion is offered: and, that which is contrary to what is here averred, will befal them, who falſifie their truſt, or engagements for <hi>GOD</hi>'s or their <hi>Countries Cauſe,</hi> even to their own inexpreſſible ſhame and deſtruction. For, as when the <hi>ways</hi> of men pleaſe <hi>GOD,</hi> he makes troubles to be their advantage, and their greateſt <hi>Enemies</hi> to be their <hi>Friends:</hi> ſo, when they wilfully diſpleaſe him, he makes their <hi>beſt Friends</hi> to be their <hi>Enemies,</hi> their <hi>ſtrength</hi> to weaken them; their <hi>wiſdome,</hi> to befool them; their <hi>prevailings</hi> to overthrow them; and that, wherein they take moſt delight, to be their greateſt vexation: yea, if they perſevere in their wickedneſs, he will make them at laſt, to be their own <hi>deſtroyers,</hi> as were the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe deſtruction, <hi>GOD</hi> ſaid, <hi>Was of themſelves.</hi> So, is our deſolation likely to be: for, we are as like them, in all things, as if we had been patterned out by them; yea, as well in other particulars as in our <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> as appears by what follows.</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>diſtinct being</hi> among us, reſembling that of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and we are both ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and mixt, as they were, in relation to <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Concernments:</hi> our <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Enemies</hi> round about us, were in every reſpect typified, by their <hi>Friends, Adverſaries</hi> and <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates:</hi> we are as obſtinate as they, in proſecuting our <hi>carnal Deſignes:</hi> we dote as much upon our own <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Traditions,</hi> as ever they did: like them, we deride and proſecute, thoſe who are ſtirred up by GOD, to declare his Will, to reprove our ſins, and to forewarn us of his <hi>Judgments:</hi> like them, we prefer our preſent profit, and a <hi>temporal Kingdom,</hi> before a <hi>Spiritual:</hi> as many <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> we have among us, as they had, a little before, and at the time wherein <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and if Chriſt were in the fleſh among us, as he was with them, we are as likely to prefer a Murderer before him, and to crucifie him. VVe deſerve therefore to be rejected as they were; nay, far greater Judgements then fell upon them, becauſe, what they did, and what thereon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, is recorded for our inſtruction and forewarnings. But, no <hi>Examples,</hi> of ancient times, nor thoſe which we have ſeen in our days, will work upon us, or move us to any conſiderable amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; rather, on the contrary, we delight in lies, and take pleaſure in deriding the moſt ſacred things, yea, in abuſing each other, and in hearing each other abuſed, by ſcurrilous Invectives: and methinks I ſee, with what ridiculous Geſticulations, and vain rejoycings, our Adverſaries beyond the Seas, peruſe our ſcurrilities. Theſe, we can finde time enough to read or hear: but what may tend to <hi>edification, reconciliation</hi> or <hi>performance</hi> of our duties, we have neither money to buy, nor leaſure to peruſe, nor will to take notice of, though it be put <hi>gratis,</hi> into our hands: but, we keep them in our pockets, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did that Letter, which might have prevented his death, till the miſchief whereof we are forewarned, comes upon us. OH LORD! <hi>Deliver us from all our Enemies in this time of our hazard; eſpecially deliver us from our ſelves, without whoſe prevarications, no other enemies could hurt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing, comes now ſuddenly to mind, not impertinent, which I will here inſert, leſt it be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118433:13"/>forgotten; and it will concern you, (whom I believe to be one of GOD's Elect in this City of <hi>London</hi>) to put other men in mind to be be heedful thereof: I have obſerved ſo many <hi>wicked Spirits,</hi> to be lately conjur'd up, and let looſe among you, and now poſſeſſing the greateſt number, as well of the richer ſort, as of poor Artificers Tradeſmen, Apprentices, Clerks, and other debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deſpicable, and giddy-headed perſons, whoſe hearts are filled with malice, and their mouths overflow with helliſh Curſes, direful Imprecations, and ſcandalous Language againſt their <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors,</hi> and thoſe things which they underſtand not, manifeſting in them, a proneneſs to deſperate <hi>Mutinies</hi> and <hi>Inſurrections,</hi> when occaſion ſhall be offered, that it is <hi>GOD's</hi> great mercy, this <hi>great City</hi> hath not been in a Flame long ſince: and, I am perſwaded that a great Judgement hangs over it, which had ere now deſcended, if a conſiderable number of <hi>righteous men,</hi> had not ſtood in the <hi>Gap</hi> to divert it; and for whoſe ſakes, GOD, hath hitherto ſpared it. There ſeemed to me, a <hi>Forewarning Symptome</hi> thereof exhibited on or about the 23 day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, at which time a <hi>Prodigious Meteor</hi> (the like not heard of by me heretofore) was ſeen by the effect, which ought to have been more heeded then it was. <hi>A Flame</hi> deſcending in a <hi>Whirle-wind,</hi> about two Furlongs Weſt-ward from the Suburbs of your <hi>City,</hi> conſumed to the roots, the ſtumps of the Sun-ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Graſs on the ground, many poles every way (which I ſaw, and have mentioned in another occaſional Diſcourſe) not without obſerving GOD's mercy to the <hi>City,</hi> in reſtraining it from paſſing a little further Eaſt-ward, where was combuſtible matter enough, which by feeding it, might, as the Wind then ſate, have made it a more dreadful, and a more obſervable <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, that which laſt precedeth, hath brought another <hi>Mountain</hi> to my conſideration, from whence there may poſſibly, iſſue ſuch <hi>Winds,</hi> as will be of more conſequence, toward the ſettling or unſettling the <hi>Common peace,</hi> then from any one of the <hi>four</hi> afore-mentioned, conſidering the poſture we are in. It lies neither <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North</hi> or <hi>Southward;</hi> but, is that <hi>Hill,</hi> even that great <hi>City,</hi> wherein you are. I dare not expreſs, what I either hope or fear, as in relation thereunto, leſt it may be more offenſive then profitable: and therefore, ſmothering my thoughts, I will onely pray to <hi>GOD,</hi> ſo to qualifie their ſpirits, who are diſtempered, and ſo to direct them, who are peaceably minded among you; that, in the great <hi>Tryal</hi> of their prudence, which is now at hand, they may proſecute what will be moſt expedient for their own and the publick ſafety, ſeaſonably, faithfully, and with courage: for, the turning of the Balance to the wrong or right ſide, will now (next under GOD) be in their Power; and the greateſt future <hi>honour</hi> or <hi>ſhame,</hi> will accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly be their portion.</p>
            <p>From that, which I have here haſtily ſcribled, out of thoſe many <hi>Notions</hi> which lay confuſedly in my heart; (and which like an <hi>Olla podredae,</hi> will afford ſome <hi>Refection,</hi> though the whole diſh be not for every mans diet) you may pick out thus much at leaſt, that, <hi>I</hi> hope GOD, who makes <hi>light</hi> ſpring out of <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and produceth good effects from evil, will be pleaſed ſo to diſpoſe of what ſhall iſſue from theſe Mountains, or from that which ſome of the <hi>Army</hi> have irregularly done, (whatſoever they intended) that it ſhall advantage us at the laſt; and that he will in the mean time reſtrain both the City and Commonwealths Forces from that Engagement againſt each other (which our <hi>Friends</hi> fear, and our <hi>Enemies</hi> hope for) by making them conſider what ſad effects may elſe follow, to the ruine of their <hi>Country,</hi> and to their own ſhame and diſtraction; that he will give them grace, to preſerve that <hi>Power</hi> intire, which was at firſt put into their hands, for the ſafe-guard of the <hi>People</hi> and their <hi>Rep eſontative,</hi> (and ſince they have aſſumed a <hi>Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> inſtead of what was intended to be ſubordinate) to make that uſe of it, whereto they are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Gratitude, Conſcience and Juſtice, even to preſerve the <hi>Common Peace,</hi> and to ſtrengthen their hands, whom GOD ſhall ſtir up, and endow with ſuch a portion of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> as may enable them, to ſettle a <hi>Righteous Government,</hi> by reducing thoſe things into <hi>order,</hi> with <hi>a ſtrong hand,</hi> which are not otherwiſe reducible by humane wiſdom; and then reſigne again the <hi>Military Sword,</hi> to be returned into the Scabberd, and continue in quiet ſubjection to the <hi>Civil Sword,</hi> as in times paſt, when the <hi>Peoples Repreſentative</hi> had it at command.</p>
            <p>If this you think to be my <hi>hope,</hi> as indeed it is, you may then ask me, how it ſhall be effected: if you do, all I can tell you, is onely of another branch of that <hi>hope,</hi> which, is, that the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118433:13"/>Armies,</hi> who have now the <hi>viſible Power</hi> in their hands, will become of one minde, and being lovingly and firmly united, will either ſpeedily reſtore, (if it be needful and poſſible) thoſe whom they have ſcattered, or, reſigne it cordially to ſuch as GOD ſhall providentially call together, and fitly qualifie for ſo great a work; and from whom the ſaid <hi>Armies</hi> (having ſo delivered up that <hi>ſupreme Power</hi>) may receive back a <hi>ſubordinate Authority,</hi> to be faithfully and obediently aſſiſtant according to their commands in their ſeveral places of truſt for the future: for, though it may ſeem abſurd or improper for them, who once had the greateſt power, to make others greater then themſelves, and then to receive back a leſs power; yet, that, is but ſuch a denial of themſelves as is juſt; and no new, or ſtrange thing, ſeeing the <hi>People</hi> in whom is vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually the <hi>Soveraign Power,</hi> do conſtitute their <hi>Repreſentative</hi> to be the <hi>ſupreme active power,</hi> of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> and then are again in ſeveral <hi>Parties,</hi> and <hi>diſtinct Capacities,</hi> re-impowered thereby, as their various occaſions and ſervices require it.</p>
            <p>You may then ask me, likewiſe, whether ſome of the <hi>chief Officers</hi> of the <hi>Armies,</hi> may not have a ſecret intention of advancing themſelves to the publick wrong, and by having an influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>common Souldiery,</hi> render them to be more ſerviceable to themſelves, and their purpoſes, then to the <hi>Republick,</hi> as it hath happened otherwhile heretofore. I hereto anſwer, that, GOD, hath a more prevailing influence upon <hi>Armies,</hi> then their <hi>Officers</hi> can have; and he being the LORD of HOSTS, can turn the hearts of their <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> (if any be depraved) or make the <hi>Souldiery,</hi> by their <hi>Officers</hi> late example, to caſt off their obedience to them, as they did caſt off their obedience to the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> and perhaps with as good or a better Conſcience, then ſome of them have ſo done, though they were thereto really neceſſitated: For, if the <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery</hi> ſhall be jealous of any <hi>ſelf-ends,</hi> in their <hi>Officers</hi> from whence the late <hi>Innovation</hi> might ſpring; or are not convinced in their Conſciences, that the late defection was warranted by GOD, and by an unqueſtionable neceſſity apparent to them; and ſhall withal, perceive that it will plunge them into a <hi>Bloody Engagemem</hi> againſt each other, both to the deſtroying of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to the endangering of their Country, as probably it will: I hope, they will conſider, by whom they are paid their Wages; for whoſe defence and ſervice, they are imbodied; that, they are a part of the ſame <hi>Body</hi> which is to be ſecured, &amp; which is expoſed at this time to hazard; and that they are not obliged to obey thoſe who abuſe their truſt, contrary to that end for which they had it conferred upon them; and that then they will deliver up their <hi>Delinquent Officers,</hi> and not make themſelves guilty of other mens crimes, leſt they hazard the whole <hi>Army,</hi> as the <hi>Benjamites</hi> did their whole <hi>Tribe,</hi> by not delivering up the Delinquents of <hi>Gibea,</hi> who did abuſe to death, the <hi>Levites</hi> Concubine.</p>
            <p>But, if the <hi>Parliament</hi> cannot be reſtored; or if (though they may) the ſaid <hi>Parliament</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confide in the <hi>Army;</hi> or, if the <hi>Army</hi> being reconciled, ſhall be perſwaded in Conſcience, that the late <hi>Parliament</hi> was not capable of making a <hi>firm Settlement;</hi> and that their <hi>Officers,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with good warrant, done that which they did, and knowingly intend ſuch a courſe, as will more conduce to an Eſtabliſhment of the Peoples juſt Liberties, and ſafety, then that which the <hi>Parliament</hi> proſecuted; and that it will be alſo more ſpeedy and more honourable both to theſe Nations and to them: what muſt we then do? Doubtleſs, we muſt then ſubmit to the preſent neceſſity, and to that expedient which they will proſecute; and thoſe men of underſtanding, courage, honeſty and piety, who believe it to be ſo, and rake notice what a hazardous and deſperate condition this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is viſibly and unqueſtionably in, at this time, (being called together, and impowered by thoſe on whom the <hi>ſupreme Power</hi> is now devolved) muſt act for our preſervation ſo far forth as they are able, notwithſtanding any Law heretofore made to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them; and leave the event to GOD: for, no man that acts for <hi>common ſafety,</hi> when the <hi>Sword</hi> hath abſolute power, and ſhall alſo command it, can juſtly be queſtioned afterward, for acting contrary to any former Law, which could be binding no longer then during that time wherein the <hi>Civil Sword</hi> had Soveraignty. Indeed, if during that time he acts contrary to ſuch Laws as were made for a Legal <hi>Government,</hi> and to the deſtroying thereof; or, ſhall not conform again to thoſe Laws, when a <hi>Military Juriſdiction</hi> is to be laid aſide: he is a Traytor, is lyable to condign puniſhment, and not for acting that which neceſſity required, when the Sword ſuperſeded the Law formerly in force.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118433:14"/>
            <p>But, who hath Authority to <hi>levy money,</hi> for payment of the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and to defray other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent expences, that a proceed may be made toward ſettling a <hi>Government;</hi> and that <hi>Plunder, Free quarter,</hi> and <hi>the common Enemies attempts</hi> may be prevented the mean while? I will imply an Anſwer to theſe <hi>Queſtions,</hi> by asking who is not authorized to do it in ſuch a caſe as we are in, or may be in, if he be actually in Arms, and ſufficiently ſtrengthned ſo to do? eſpecially if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by thoſe who have the moſt viſible <hi>ſupreme Authority,</hi> to ſecure the <hi>Publike Intereſt?</hi> Or, who, though not commiſſioned by any, is not warranted, if he be enabled, (and ſhall do it ſincerely) to endeavour preſervation of the <hi>Common ſafety</hi> and <hi>intereſt,</hi> by an <hi>Arbitrary Proceeding,</hi> in a time of univerſal danger, and when it cannot be done in a legal manner? May any man come without blame, and with thanks, to help ſave a <hi>ſingle City,</hi> endangered by a raging Fire, and take Inſtruments uſeful thereto out of any mans poſſeſſion? Yea, enter into his houſe, and pull it down if need be; or, burn the Suburbs of a City, whereby an Enemy may be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged in laying a Siege thereunto, and the ſaid City be loſt? And, ſhall it not be allowable for any man to do as much for preſervation of the <hi>whole Commonwealth,</hi> conſiſting of many <hi>Cities, Counties, Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> yea, of three populous <hi>Nations,</hi> when they are in danger to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, or (which is worſe) to be inſlaved? Are not all the <hi>Goods,</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi> yea, and the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> alſo, within a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> her Goods and Lands, and Perſons; whoſe ſoever they are, or in whoſe occupation, propriety or poſſeſſion ſoever they be? This cannot be denyed: and may ſhe not then take her own to ſecure her ſelf, whereſoever ſhe findes it? Verily it may lawfully be taken by the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> which is the <hi>Supreme Law</hi> whereto all other <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws</hi> are ſubſervient: and curſed is he, above all other Tranſgreſſors of humane <hi>Laws,</hi> who either abuſeth this Law by neglecting to put it in execution, ſo far as he is able, when need requires it; or who ſhall pretend to a neceſſity, when there is none; or make it ſeem greater then it is, to advantage his <hi>private Deſignes</hi> to the oppreſsing of other men: and wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt is that <hi>Commonwealth</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ciyt,</hi> which, when the danger is paſt, doth not contribute out of the <hi>Common Purſe</hi> a reaſonable repair of their particular damages, whoſe goods were ſeized or ſpoiled to prevent a general detriment, by an Arbitrary or irregular Act.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Objection</hi> more may be yet made, which is implyed in this Verſe of the Poet:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nulla fides, pietaſve viris, qui caſtra ſequuntur.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Faith, or Piety, is in their words,</l>
                     <l>Who, have no living, but their <hi>Swords.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Armies,</hi> are as dangerous and unſtable, as the Seas; ebbing, flowing, calmed, inraged, turning and returning, as Windes and Tydes move them. They are but an <hi>Arm of Fleſh,</hi> you will ſay, and we can have no aſſurance of their conſtancy, whereby we may be confident thereof; and, our <hi>Army,</hi> may ſet up, one of their own <hi>Officers,</hi> or call in <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> or make ſome other uſe of their power at laſt, for their own advantage, to the deſtroying of the <hi>Peoples intereſt;</hi> and, what ſhall we then do? Truly, we muſt then do as, I hope, you and I do now, and ever ſhall do, in proſperity, and adverſity. We muſt do as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did when they were oppreſſed. It is recorded, that, when for their ſins, they were (as we now are) at ſuch and ſuch a time, ſo, and ſo oppreſſed, they cryed unto GOD, and obtained deliverance. They cryed, and were delivered; and ſinned again, and cryed again, and were again and again delivered; as we have often been. Yea, though their hearts were not right, and their cries proceeded more form a ſenſe of their <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,</hi> then of their <hi>ſins;</hi> yea, though they cryed and prayed, but as <hi>Ahab</hi> once did, and as (I fear) moſt of us have often done; yet, they had temporary deliverances; and they returning to their ſins, the puniſhments again returned, increaſing from ſeven years bondage, to ſeventy years captivity: and, we ſtarting aſide as they did like a warped Bow, are in danger of the like Chaſtiſements: For, our verbal profeſſion of truſting in GOD; our loud vocal Prayers, and ſometimes a days abſtinence from food, prevails very little, except there comes therewith, a <hi>ſtill
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118433:14"/>voyce</hi> from the heart, which cries for <hi>mercy,</hi> as <hi>Abels</hi> blood cryed out of the earth for <hi>vengeance.</hi> To tell the greateſt part of men, that they muſt <hi>truſt in God,</hi> is in their apprehenſion (though they ſeemingly receive it as good counſel) as if they were plainly told that there is no hope of their deliverance: For, they feel their hearts cannot truſt in him, except we ſhew them ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing left wherein they might truſt, if GOD ſhould fail their expectation, as they fear he will, when he looks into their hearts, and ſees that they truſt him no longer, then thoſe outward things continue whereon they placed their confidence. If we cannot truſt GOD with our <hi>Army,</hi> who is the LORD of Armies, except we may be aſſured our <hi>Armies</hi> will prove truſty, or, unleſs we ſee ſome other <hi>earthly reſerve</hi> to rely upon if that ſhould be falſe; we muſt then ſuffer for our unfaithfulneſs, without remedy; and may be likened to a fooliſh man, who having an excellent ſtout Horſe able to bear him to the <hi>Lands end,</hi> is afraid he may miſcarry in a Journey of ten miles, unleſs he hath alſo, a <hi>wooden Hobby-horſe</hi> to be a <hi>Reſerve.</hi> He, that could caſt down the VValls of a ſtrong City, with the ſound of <hi>Rams-horns,</hi> can ſave us without an <hi>Army,</hi> and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of the moſt puiſſant Armies in the world; and, he hath deſerved better of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> then to be diſtruſted by them.</p>
            <p>For, what People under Heaven, hath had more Experiments of GOD's timely aſſiſtance in all extremities, then hath been vouchſafed by him unto us both in times paſt, and within our remembrance? Nay, what Hiſtories record a Mercy vouchſafed to any <hi>Nation</hi> ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, like that which we enjoy at this preſent amidſt our <hi>Confuſions?</hi> We are a living active <hi>Body</hi> without a <hi>Head:</hi> A <hi>burning Buſh</hi> that is not conſumed: A <hi>People without a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> yet not embrewed with each others blood; which I believe (though few of us heed that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) is a wonderment to all our <hi>Neighbours</hi> round about us; and is a token undubitable that GOD is yet in the <hi>Buſh,</hi> and will gather us together as Chickens under a Hen, to be brooded by him, if we were not wilful: for, if I ſhould enumerate (beſide our three late ſignal Changes without Bloodſhed) thoſe other late mercies, which but I my ſelf have taken heed of in my time, have been ſo extraordinarily linked to each other, that we had been utterly deſtroyed, if any one of thoſe Links had been broken off, it would amount to a large Volumn; or, if I ſhould commemorate, how many of thoſe <hi>outward truſts</hi> have failed us, whereon we relyed, it would appear, that all other Dependencies are empty vanities. I will particularize a few of them, that we may be more mindful how we have been deceived by thoſe other <hi>helps</hi> wherein we truſted, and learn henceforward, to think GOD's Protection is all-ſufficient.</p>
            <p>We had a <hi>King</hi> of whom we had great hopes, as appeared by our mourning, for his long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in <hi>Spain,</hi> when he was <hi>Prince;</hi> and by our extravagant rejoycings at his return; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had an extraordinary confidence in him when he firſt aſſumed the <hi>Regal Authority:</hi> yet, he became our <hi>Oppreſſour</hi> ſoon after; and much was deſigned, which might have more oppreſt us. We had afterward a <hi>Parliament,</hi> on which we ſo much depended, that we made an <hi>Idol</hi> of it, and were no leſs oppreſſed thereby. We had many <hi>eminent Perſons</hi> among us, whom we thought ſuch true <hi>Patriots,</hi> that we almoſt deifi'd them; and ſuppoſed they ſhould have been our <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers,</hi> from the ſervitude which we groaned under; but, many of them, apoſtatized from <hi>our Cauſe,</hi> and other ſome were taken away by death, whom we thought moſt ſincere; and both failed in our greateſt need. We had a <hi>Protector,</hi> whom ſome did compare unto (nay, prefer before) <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua;</hi> and he made ſuch fair ſhews of <hi>Piety,</hi> that we much truſted in him, and thought it impoſſible he ſhould deceive us; yet, in him alſe, there was no truſt. Then the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> being reſtored, we again repoſed our confidence therein, and were again deceived: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have truſted in <hi>themſelves,</hi> in their <hi>power,</hi> in their <hi>eſtates,</hi> in their own <hi>piety,</hi> in their <hi>policy;</hi> and all thoſe things vaniſh away alſo like Smoke: ſome other at this preſent truſt in our <hi>Armies,</hi> in the ſtrength of <hi>men and horſes,</hi> in <hi>Forts and Fleets,</hi> with ſuch like; and now begin to diſtruſt them, feeling not onely our late <hi>hopes</hi> of them to be ſhaken, but our <hi>Fears</hi> likewiſe to be by them in creaſed: and what ſhould all this teach us, but to relic on him onely, who is immutable? He hath <hi>Wiſdome</hi> enough to know what is beſt for us; <hi>Power</hi> enough, to effect it for us; <hi>Love</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to vouchſafe it; <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> enough, to perform his promiſes; and <hi>Ubiquity</hi> and <hi>Eternity,</hi> to be preſent with us at all <hi>times,</hi> in all <hi>places,</hi> and in all <hi>extremities:</hi> yea, he hath freely engaged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118433:15"/>by his Word and Promiſes, to do all this for us, if we have but <hi>Faith</hi> enough to believe him; and will alſo give us that <hi>Faith,</hi> if we heartily ask it. If we think not this a ſufficient <hi>Reſerve</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us, though our <hi>Armies,</hi> and all things elſe in the world, ſhould be falſe and helpleſs, we are worthy to be deſerted; and can have no ſecurity, until we ſearch out the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of our diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and then endeavour to remove it: which <hi>Cauſe,</hi> is our many great unrepented ſins; and in ſpecial, our <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> our groſs <hi>partiality,</hi> our <hi>ſelf-ſeekings,</hi> and remiſſneſs in doing <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and in mercifully relieving the oppreſſed, the Widows, the Fatherleſs and the Friendleſs; which ſins, were the principal cauſes of the Deſolation of all <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>Republicks,</hi> heretofore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, in former Ages.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Sins,</hi> have been the <hi>ſole Cauſe,</hi> that our <hi>Kings,</hi> our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> our <hi>Protectors,</hi> our <hi>Armies,</hi> our <hi>Navies,</hi> our <hi>Counſels,</hi> our <hi>Coſt,</hi> our <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> and that <hi>we our ſelves,</hi> have been deſtructive to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> to <hi>each other,</hi> and to a <hi>happy progreſſion</hi> toward the ſettlement which we have long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected: Therefore, until theſe ſins are more truly repented, all the <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>power</hi> upon earth, ſhall not avail us; but every day will encreaſe our troubles, until there be a final extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of all that which now hinders GOD's <hi>work:</hi> For, if our <hi>Armies</hi> reconcile to each other, an <hi>unarmed power,</hi> ſhall break them in pieces: If, by their Union with the <hi>People,</hi> who are well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to their own <hi>Cauſe,</hi> we could ſecure theſe <hi>Iſlands</hi> from <hi>Forreign Invaſions,</hi> and <hi>Domeſtick Inſurrections,</hi> until our <hi>own wiſdom</hi> had contrived and ſettled ſuch a <hi>Government</hi> as we moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; yet, if our ſins remain unrepented, GOD, may make us miſerable by <hi>Famine,</hi> which would conſume us with a lingring death. If our <hi>Induſtry,</hi> were able to prevent or mitigate a <hi>Famine;</hi> he hath <hi>Peſtilences</hi> and other <hi>Sickneſſes</hi> at command, to make a quicker diſpatch; and if we had cures for theſe, he can rain down <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sulpher</hi> from Heaven, as he did on <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rha.</hi> GOD, is a ſure <hi>Refuge</hi> againſt all theſe, and againſt evils more to be feared then all theſe; and if we reconcile our ſelves to him in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> we ſhall not need to ſeek for ſafety in the <hi>Reeds of Aegypt,</hi> or, by climing <hi>Rocks,</hi> or creeping into <hi>Dens;</hi> or by fawning upon <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, Dogs, Devils,</hi> and <hi>despicable Deliverers, who</hi> cannot ſave themſelves. We ſhall then, neither fear <hi>ill News,</hi> or <hi>Mid-day,</hi> or <hi>Mid-night-miſchieſs;</hi> not the roaring of <hi>Lyons,</hi> nor the hiſſing of <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi> nor the <hi>murmurings of the People,</hi> nor their <hi>Fury,</hi> how horribly ſoever they rage; nor the failing of our <hi>Corn</hi> or <hi>wine,</hi> nor the increaſe of our <hi>Troubles,</hi> or of our <hi>Enemies,</hi> though they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe us with <hi>Armies;</hi> nor ſuſpect our own <hi>Armies,</hi> nor dread the malice of the <hi>Devil,</hi> nor our own <hi>Sins,</hi> which are more dangerous then all the reſt aforementioned: For, nothing ſhall then harm us; but, even thoſe things which are moſt miſchievous in their own nature, ſhall be made our advantage and ſecurity. Moreover, when we do not truſt in any outward means of ſafety, but value them onely as tokens of GOD's love for the Givers ſake, and make uſe of them as Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries from him, he will multiply and continue even thoſe outward Accommodations which our frailty deſireth; that, they may help ſupport our fleſhly part, when Faith muſt employ the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of our minds and bodies in working out with him, both our Temporal and Spiritual Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak this experimentally: for, I being ſubject to ſuch infirmities as all other men are, when I am buffered by Satan for my ſins paſt, by GOD's permiſſion, (or to prevent ſins where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into I had elſe fallen) do, oftentimes, (like men in danger of drowning, catching hold of a Ruſh) entertain ſuch vain hopes, as may keep my fleſh quiet, and the leſs burthenſome to my <hi>Spirit;</hi> that, thereby pleaſing her ſelf a while, till ſhe be a little enured to the <hi>Affliction</hi> which lies upon us, it may be the more tolerable: and I am thankful to GOD, even for ſuch <hi>vain hopes,</hi> as come to nothing; and for that eaſe which I had by them, whilſt they laſted: But, I placed no truſt in them; for, GOD is my onely <hi>truſt,</hi> whom I ſo well know by thoſe manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he hath made of himſelf, that I cannot deſpair (though I tremble) when I contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the ſevereſt of his Judgements; and am ſo aſſured he is merciful, that I cannot but truſt in his <hi>mercies,</hi> how long ſoever delayed, or, how far off ſoever they ſeem removed: And, when in ſuch diſtractions, troubles, and doubtful conſequences, as thoſe wherewithal I am now exerciſed, (and which theſe <hi>Changes</hi> threaten to make greater) I feel my heart diſtempered; then, <hi>I</hi> make uſe of ſuch <hi>Cordials</hi> as <hi>David</hi> hath left in his Book of <hi>approved Experiments;</hi> and, I thus expoſtulate with my heart in his words: <hi>Why art thou ſo dejected, Oh my Soul? Why art thou
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118433:15"/>ſo diſquieted within me? Hope thou in GOD; for, I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and my GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If, we get but this <hi>Reſerve,</hi> we are ſafe enough, though the <hi>Army</hi> ſhould fail us, and though neither that, nor any other earthly hope, took effect: we ſhould not then, deſtroy the comforts of the day preſent, ſo often as we do, by an impertinent vexatious caring for to <hi>morrow.</hi> GOD, ſhould then keep our <hi>Armies</hi> truſty, and ſo far forth fortifie and ſtrengthen them, that they would reſtrain their old <hi>diſtempers,</hi> and be a terrour to thoſe onely, who wickedly or fooliſhly ſeek to hinder the ſettlement both of our <hi>Peace,</hi> and of their own. He would then prepare the hearts of all the <hi>People,</hi> to be deſirous of, and conformable to, what muſt be done for their <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being:</hi> He would qualifie and impower perſons to proſecute it for his glory, &amp; for the conſolation of thoſe who are faithful and peaceable in our <hi>Iſrael;</hi> yea, he would then ſo clear the eye of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and of <hi>Faith,</hi> which ſin hath clouded, that many thouſands of thoſe, who can yet ſee no poſſibility of modelling any ſafe, juſt, or laſting <hi>Government,</hi> ſave according to the <hi>old mode,</hi> and by re-admitting all that hath been exploded and rejected, ſhall perceive that to be feiſible which they deſpaired; cheerfully ſubmit thereto, when it is compleated; and contribute wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, to the means of compleating it: and, I am perſwaded that in the <hi>Mountain of Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> I have had a little <hi>glimpſe</hi> of that <hi>compleat model</hi> which will take place, when the date of that <hi>Mole</hi> or <hi>Moon-Calf,</hi> is expired, which is mentioned in my <hi>Britains Genius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot expreſs what I ſaw; but, I do believe (by the little <hi>glimpſe</hi> aforeſaid, which I had of it) that to make a <hi>Government</hi> perfect and durable, there are ſome <hi>Foundations</hi> to be laid, which muſt be <hi>everlaſting,</hi> (as in reſpect to that <hi>everlaſtingneſs,</hi> which belongs to things of that nature) and that thoſe <hi>Foundations</hi> muſt be guarded with <hi>Pedeſtals</hi> deeply laid, and barred about, that none may undermine, deface or ſhake, much leſs remove them, in any length of time, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering of the whole <hi>Edifice.</hi> That, alſo, the contriving of thoſe <hi>Foundations,</hi> and of ſome of the firſt <hi>Superſtructures,</hi> muſt proceed from righteous <hi>unbyaſſed perſons,</hi> who are in unity in <hi>Spirit;</hi> or elſe it muſt be begotten by one and the <hi>ſame Father;</hi> that there may be a <hi>natural</hi> ſympathy in the whole <hi>Structure;</hi> that, all the parts thereof may be made homogeneous and adequate one to the other, to prevent oppugnancie; and that ſuch <hi>additions</hi> as muſt be raiſed and pulled down in future time, and perhaps raiſed and pulled down again as occaſions will require, may neither deform or weaken the principal Members of the <hi>Fabrick.</hi> They, likewiſe, who ſhall be intruſted to modellize our <hi>Government,</hi> to make it ſuch as it ought to be, muſt ſo frame it, that it may correſpond with, and be ſubſervient unto the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by conſidering what is <hi>morally, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally,</hi> or <hi>Evangelically</hi> pertinent to all <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Ages;</hi> and what is but <hi>Ceremonial</hi> or Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and belonging peculiarly to the <hi>Jews</hi> onely in their own <hi>Country,</hi> and during the time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their <hi>Law</hi> was in force; leſt, they form a <hi>Jewiſh Commonwealth</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Chriſtian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and bring us back again by degrees to a <hi>Legal Bondage,</hi> inſtead of an <hi>Evangelical Freedom.</hi> I, contemplatively apprehended alſo, that theſe following <hi>Particulars,</hi> with ſome other of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, were to be <hi>unchangeable Conſtitutions</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Government.</hi> 1. That all perſons whoſoever, pretending right to a <hi>Supremacy</hi> over theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> were to be for ever excluded. 2. That no other <hi>ſingle perſon,</hi> or number of men, great or ſmall, ſhould have a <hi>Perpetual Soveraignly,</hi> but be ſometimes reducible to a condition of <hi>Subjection.</hi> 3. That none ſhould govern <hi>Arbitrarily,</hi> but by <hi>poſitive Laws,</hi> except in extraordinary emergent <hi>neceſſities,</hi> ſo long time onely as the <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> ſhould require it, by their Judgement and Aſſent who are competent Judges of that <hi>neceſſity.</hi> 4. That no mans <hi>Propriety</hi> ſhould be infringed, but in the like <hi>neceſſity;</hi> and that, <hi>recompence</hi> ſhould be made out of the <hi>Publick Purſe,</hi> as ſoon as may be after the <hi>neceſſity</hi> is removed, to every one then damnified thereby. 5. That the <hi>Peoples Truſtees,</hi> may have election of all <hi>Publick Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> and GOD have his choyce by lot, out of thoſe Elections. 6. That GOD<hi>'s Throne</hi> in the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of men, may be uſurped by no <hi>humane Power;</hi> and that no man or men impowered, under pretence of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or otherwiſe, may enjoy any <hi>Liberty</hi> or <hi>Priviledge,</hi> contrary to the Moral Laws of GOD; or the Law of Nature; or deſtructive to <hi>humane ſociety;</hi> or to the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any <hi>Forraign Power,</hi> or Perſon, a Juriſdiction, within this <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> or to the obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of <hi>Common Right</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi> 7. That whoſoever, will not ſubmit and ſubſcribe to thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118433:16"/>Fundamentals (when it is required) ſhall be as an excommunicated perſon, having no benefit of the <hi>Laws,</hi> or <hi>Protection</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Government;</hi> and ſuffer as a Traytor, if by act or word he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully infringe them.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Contemplations</hi> as theſe relating to our future <hi>Government,</hi> I long ſince had, and here and there hinted them in <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Private</hi> expreſſions, to ſome in <hi>Authority;</hi> and though they were then little regarded, I hear that ſome of them are lately taken into Conſideration: and I might have added more perhaps, as conſiderable as thoſe, if I had not perceived that my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures had been ſleighted by them, who ſaw they obſtructed what was deſigned for their <hi>private advantages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, why this <hi>Generation</hi> (which pretendeth much to the gifts of the <hi>Spirit</hi> that ſhall be vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to his Children in the laſt Ages of the world) ſhould be ſo averſe from thoſe <hi>Cautions, Forewarnings, Tenders</hi> and <hi>Expedients</hi> by me exhibited, I conceive not, unleſs it be out of <hi>Self-wil,</hi> and <hi>Pride of Heart.</hi> Why may not GOD, if he ſo pleaſe, ſave this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> by a poor mans <hi>Expedient,</hi> that is not very wiſe, as well, as he did heretofore ſave a <hi>City</hi> by a <hi>poor wiſe man</hi> that was as little regarded? Some indeed have been pleaſed to ask my <hi>Advice,</hi> with ſeeming ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, as if they thought it might be pertinent to their <hi>well-being,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> did ſome of their approved Prophets, pretending Conformity therein; but, when they perceived it was not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with their own <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſignes</hi> and <hi>Self-ends,</hi> they wholly waved it, as thoſe did. If to have <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi> of my being rightly informed, by a meaſure of <hi>Divine Grace,</hi> and by what hath ſucceeded on my <hi>Pre-conjectures;</hi> there have been ſome ſuch evidences on my part. If <hi>Education</hi> may be a means of informing me, I was educated in our <hi>Univerſities,</hi> and <hi>Inns of Court.</hi> If to be a <hi>Souldier</hi> may ought qualifie me, I was a <hi>Commander</hi> in our firſt <hi>Army,</hi> ſo conformable to the <hi>Precept</hi> given to <hi>Souldiers</hi> by <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> in reſting content with my <hi>pay,</hi> that I have not been malevolently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented though nigh 1700 <hi>l.</hi> made due to me by an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> hath been kept from me almoſt 17 years, without receiving either the Principal or Intereſt, though 700 <hi>l.</hi> thereof was <hi>money lent,</hi> and for which I have paid intereſt ever ſince; and though I may poſſibly be kept without it 17 years longer, longer. If Manifeſtations of my <hi>good Affection</hi> to the <hi>Common Safety</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> may make my offers conſiderable, I have contributed without compulſion, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing of my <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> If my <hi>Religion,</hi> be of any concernment, I am a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> If my <hi>Converſation</hi> be pertinent; who can object ought againſt it, or lay any thing to my charge? If a competency of Eſtate be requiſite to gain eſteem, I wanted not that, until I was deprived thereof, by <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and by the want of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> in other men. If to have converſed with <hi>Books,</hi> and to have obſerved long time the manners of men, and to have heeded the Conſtitution of our preſent times and Affairs, may be any thing helpful to inform me what may be now <hi>expedient;</hi> I have had thoſe helps alſo. Nay, if to be poor, ignorant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, meanly gifted, and of a low and obſcure condition, are ſuch qualifications, as make men in theſe days moſt capable of <hi>illumination,</hi> and of that knowledge whereby they may beſt ſerve their <hi>Country</hi> in giving good advice; I am in all theſe reſpects as likely to be that way ſerviceable, as any of thoſe <hi>Huntſmen, Falconers, Taylors, Tinkers, Coblers, Plow-men, Brewers</hi> or <hi>Dray men,</hi> which are now, or have been heretofore, <hi>Officers of the Army, Members of Parliament,</hi> of <hi>Committees of Safety,</hi> or <hi>Counſellors of State.</hi> And if I had the volubility of <hi>tongue,</hi> which is in ſome; <hi>Ignorance</hi> enough to make me confidently ſpeak <hi>Non-ſence,</hi> and many words to little purpoſe; the <hi>ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſneſs</hi> of a <hi>Whore;</hi> the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of an <hi>Hypocrite;</hi> and the valour of an <hi>Engliſh Maſtiff,</hi> to flye upon any dangerous attempt without fear or wit; and but that advantage which two or three <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> have at this preſent: I ſhould not think it a hard matter, if GOD (as one of the <hi>Royal Party</hi> once ſaid, ſtood neuter, and as our <hi>Affairs</hi> now ſtand) to make my ſelf a <hi>King,</hi> or a <hi>Protector,</hi> or ſomething equivalent, either before next <hi>March,</hi> or elſe before <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> had complemented themſelves into a firm and laſting <hi>Reconcilement,</hi> as near to a concluſion as they now think it to be.</p>
            <p>Though I have hitherto publickly contributed my endeavours in vain, yet I will privately, as I do now, employ my <hi>Talent</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Common Peace,</hi> in hope to bring in (by a more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable hand) thoſe things which I conceive pertinent to conſideration; and which will be a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118433:16"/>means to ſtir abler Inſtruments, to become active toward eſtabliſhing ſuch a <hi>Righteous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as is yet poſſible; or at leaſt to prevent ſome of thoſe miſchiefs which <hi>Anarchy</hi> threatens: For, if all the Premiſes were duly conſidered by thoſe whom they concern, and what <hi>Reſults</hi> may rationally be deduced from them, they would diſcover an Expedient, (and the onely Expedient now loft) if they be capable of any wherein they themſelves may be active; by which, theſe Nations, <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> our Governours that are or may be, and all the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> may be happy; make all their Subjects and Neighbours partakers of the ſame happineſs; and eſcape that <hi>Doom,</hi> which they are in danger to undergo with that <hi>Scarlet Whore,</hi> by whoſe <hi>Cup of Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> they have been made drunk. I will declare without reſpect of perſons, what that <hi>Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ont</hi> is; though I know it will be derided, if communicated in publick. But, he, who pretends to aſſiſt men that are in an intricate <hi>Labyrinth</hi> under ground in the dark, where are many crooked turnings and returnings, and gives him directions in a Paper only, leaving them no <hi>light</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they may accuſtome their eyes a while, nor whereby they may ſee how to read what is given, (or, what Paſſages they muſt avoid or take) may juſtly be thought to mock them: Therefore, before I ſhew my <hi>Expedient,</hi> I will endeavour to remove ſome Prejudicacies, relating to my ſelf, and other men, by declaring what it is, which will hinder every Party afore-mentioned, from putting it into practiſe; and that is included in this brief ſentence, <hi>Non videmus id manticae quod in tergo eſt;</hi> which applying to my ſelf in the firſt place, I thus Engliſh in the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber:
<q>
                  <l>I partly ſee what's in my Neighbours Pack;</l>
                  <l>Not that part of the Wallet at my back.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, I feel it very heavy, and do more then gueſs what is in it: Some of my Neighbors, who know not ſo well as I, what I carry, take upon them, as if they knew thoſe things to be therein, which my Conſcience aſſures me are not. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f they think otherwiſe, let them ſearch it, and diſcover what they finde offenſive to GOD, to them, or to my ſelf, ſo it be with as much Charity, and to as good purpoſe, as I have told ſome of them, what is in their Budgets; and I will take them to be my Friends, and thank them. It is too true, that by humane frailty I have in my beſt endeavours more inclined to ſelf-ends, then I ought; and by ſeeking to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my Eſtate and Credit in the world, neglected ſometimes to perform my duty ſo as I ſhould have done to GOD and to my Country; and that alſo, I ſhould not have ſo far forth diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, as I have imperfectly done, if I had not been purſu'd with Storms heretofore, and caſt as it were into a <hi>Whales</hi> Belly as now I am: however, GOD's grace is ſufficient for me; and therefore, though I have many failings of mine own (hoping they ſhall not make my endeavors altogether ineffectual) <hi>I</hi> will proceed to declare what the chief cauſe of obſtruction is, which muſt be taken away, before my <hi>Expedient</hi> can be put in practiſe, by thoſe Parties whom it will concern: and that is, the not duely examining the true ſtate of thoſe Cauſes which they proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute; and their looking ſo much after each others failings, that they heed not their own Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rications. They are very ſenſible of wrongs done unto themſelves, but not ſenſible in the leaſt degree of thoſe injuries which they themſelves do to other men: and I having been an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant <hi>by-ſtander,</hi> above threeſcore years, without any prejudice or partial reſpect to any Party, think it my duty, to declare in part, what I have obſerved in relation to them, and their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Cauſes now in controverſie, ſince my remembrance; and by what means I became infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thoſe Quarrels and Proceedings on both ſides, which occaſioned the ſad Conſequences that have enſued.</p>
            <p>I having (as is before intimated) no cauſe to prejudice either of thoſe Parties, out of hope any way to advantage my ſelf thereby, or for any ſiniſter reſpect to either of them, (but loving and wiſhing them well, joyntly and apart) took ſuch ſpecial notice, (as is aforeſaid) both in the times of King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles,</hi> how the Peoples Liberties were encroached upon, and what farther Slaveries were likely to enſue, that I am well aſſured, the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty,</hi> which is by many magnified as effects of their good <hi>Government,</hi> was acquired by GOD's bleſſing upon the <hi>Peoples Induſtry</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raign, and during the time wherein thoſe forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118433:17"/>
               <hi>Kings,</hi> made uſe of thoſe bleſſings to get ſettlement of power upon themſelves, rather then by their juſt and prudent <hi>Government:</hi> For, I ſaw them waſt and conſume in vanities, ſo much of the <hi>Publick Lands</hi> and <hi>Treaſures,</hi> to accompliſh their ends, and fulfil their luſts, as might (if em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as it ought) have made this one of the moſt happy and renowned <hi>Empires</hi> in the world. I obſerved how they conferred their Titles of honour, and part of the Publick Revenues, with vaſt ſums extorted out of private mens Eſtates (by Monopolies, unlawful and baſe Projects) upon perſons of <hi>ignoble extract,</hi> and debauched manners, to make them inſtrumental in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes; and perhaps it might be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e probable (if not evident) that if a ſtop had not been put to their <hi>proceedings,</hi> here might have been ere this, as horrible a <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as was in <hi>Ireland. I</hi> perceived, (as miſcrable as we are now made) that, things were plotted, and in part executed, which in likelyhood would have brought us to a more miſerable condition in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, then we are now in; and into which we are plunged by their occaſioning that which we were lately enforced unto, for prevention of their increaſing <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> and <hi>Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> and, though our <hi>preſent ſufferings</hi> have cauſed moſt of them, who lived before the <hi>late Wars,</hi> to forget what was then impoſed, attempted and purpoſed; <hi>I,</hi> and many other have not forgotten it. Though likewiſe, King <hi>Charles</hi> deceaſed, is both by his own <hi>Party,</hi> and by thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, who are depraved (or, elſe were born too late to know what he was) impudently mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified as a <hi>Martyr for Religion,</hi> and an <hi>Aſſertor</hi> of the <hi>Peoples Freedoms;</hi> yet, they, and I, to whom the ſeries of his tranſactions and endeavours, is well known, cannot be deluded, by <hi>Fictions</hi> and <hi>Impoſtures,</hi> as many now are, and as more may perhaps be hereafter, by thoſe <hi>Books of Devotion</hi> compiled by his <hi>flattering Clergie,</hi> and fathered upon him: though other of the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> compile Volumns to deceive after-Ages, ſtuft with Vanities; and ſcatter ſeditious <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> and ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Invectives (which, coming abroad without names, no wiſe man regards) thereby to render thoſe odious, who have moſt faithfully endeavoured to vindicate the <hi>Peoples Rights,</hi> and to make ignorant perſons eſteem them Rebels, Traitors, Barbarous Murthere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of their <hi>King,</hi> and wilful O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowers of <hi>Government</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth:</hi> which imputations, many are apt to believe, in regard of ill ſucceſſes, occaſioned both by the <hi>Common Enemies</hi> default, and by thoſe among our ſelves, who were under-hand their <hi>Abettors;</hi> yet, <hi>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yaſſed men,</hi> do plainly enough ſee their falſifications, &amp; whereto they tend: Moreover, though the <hi>Adverſaries of Common Welfare,</hi> do ſcandalize the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as perfidious Breakers of their Promiſes, Proteſtations and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and particularly for taking away his Life, whom they pretended to make a <hi>glorious King,</hi> and in changing the <hi>Government;</hi> Nevertheleſs, I conceive (though ſome individual perſons among them may be premeditately guilty of all this) that the <hi>Parliament</hi> is not juſtly lyable to theſe miſ-imputations: For, upon good grounds, I do verily believe, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly intended what they profeſſed in that kind, and would accordingly have performed their Engagements, if the <hi>King</hi> would have accepted of thoſe terms whereby he might have been a <hi>King</hi> and not a <hi>Tyrant;</hi> and would have raigned in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as by the Laws of GOD and Nature, he was obliged to do: For, it cannot be reaſonably imagined, but that thoſe were the implicite conditions of all their <hi>Proteſtations</hi> and <hi>Engagements.</hi> But, he ſo obſtinately perſevered in his wilfulneſs, even when there was a <hi>Treaty for Reconcilement,</hi> that he diſobliged them from all their promiſes, and compelled the proſecution of that which afterward enſued, and was not at firſt intended: And, I do here to the Glory of GOD aver (though I know it may be to my perſonal diſadvantage) that GOD's doom was juſtly executed upon him for his own ſins, and the ſins of his <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> with what intent ſoever, and with what <hi>juglings</hi> ſoever it was proſecuted by men; and, that, the <hi>Peoples Cauſe,</hi> was, and is a <hi>Righteous Cauſe,</hi> though it was not ſo prudently and righteouſly managed, as it might and ought to have been: and I believe it is too evident, that ſome of both <hi>Parties,</hi> by ſeeking to ſcrew in perſonal advantages to themſelves, at the <hi>Treaty,</hi> and at other times, were the <hi>Cauſers</hi> of all that miſ-befel both to the <hi>King</hi> and to the <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may rationally believe this, becauſe I had opportunities to diſcover much of their ſiniſter actings on both ſides, tending to the trapanning of each other, (if <hi>I</hi> am not miſ-informed) which juſtly provoked GOD, and occaſioned Confuſions, to the inſnaring of many well-meaning men,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118433:17"/>to the involving them in guiltineſs, troubles and hazards, from which they will not eaſily be delivered. I many times adventured (not without danger to my ſelf) to inform the King what I had obſerved; and when he was Priſoner in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> ſignified by what means he might then unqueſtionably have made his peace both with <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> (as I have done without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his <hi>Succeſſours</hi>) but, he adhered ſtill to his <hi>evil Counſellours;</hi> or rather, to his own <hi>wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (which was enough to have depraved them, if they had been good) and inſtead of complying with his <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſo endeavoured even when he was their <hi>Priſoner,</hi> by corrupting the <hi>Scots,</hi> and a great number of the <hi>Parliaments Members,</hi> with large Promiſes, that he was likely, by <hi>plowing with their Oxen,</hi> either to have cheated them, of all the Peoples <hi>Freedoms,</hi> or to have plunged the three <hi>Nations,</hi> into a new War: and this cauſed the <hi>Armies</hi> firſt extraordinary at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, at which the <hi>Royal Party</hi> and their Confederates have ſo much railed, as a high breach of the <hi>Parliaments Priviledges,</hi> and of the <hi>Peoples Freedoms;</hi> whereas, they could not at that time have been any other way preſerved in humane underſtanding: And therefore, then, and not before, that <hi>part of the Parliament,</hi> which was true to the truſt repoſed in them by the <hi>People,</hi> did with the Aſſiſtance of their <hi>Army,</hi> ſeeing (as I conceive) no way elſe but removing him out of the world, to prevent the treacheries of their <hi>corrupt Members,</hi> and the Kings <hi>Destructive Deſignes,</hi> carried on by their complyance; they out-witted him at his own game; and (<hi>Stratagems</hi> being as lawful againſt an Enemy, as <hi>Force</hi>) got poſſeſſion of his perſon; brought him to a <hi>Legal Tryal,</hi> and condemned him to death <hi>A Legal Tryal</hi> was it? (you will ſay perhaps) by what <hi>Law,</hi> or by what <hi>Authority?</hi> Truly, I was heartily ſorry for him, when he was condemned; and ſo far from having any hand therein, or aſſenting thereto, that I drew a <hi>Petition</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> to forbear from executing the ſentence of the <hi>Court,</hi> by reaſon the <hi>rarity</hi> of ſuch an Act, made me then abhor it: but no <hi>Member</hi> daring to preſent it; and I having thereby opportunity to conſider better of my intention, was ſatisfied in my Conſcience, that he was Legally condemned by that <hi>Law,</hi> which makes it Treaſon for a <hi>Servant</hi> to ſeek the deſtruction of his <hi>Maſter</hi> who had truſted him; that he was no more but a <hi>principal Servant</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> juſtly queſtionable for breach of his <hi>Truſt;</hi> and that by the ſame <hi>Authority,</hi> whereby the <hi>People</hi> might raiſe any one from among themſelves, to be their <hi>Supreme Officer,</hi> they might for his ingratitude, and violation of the truſt repoſed in him, judge, depoſe or condemn him to death, as his Crime, and the neceſſity of preſerving the <hi>Common Peace</hi> or <hi>Safety,</hi> ſhould require: and the Son of him whoſe Predeceſſours had for many Generations been <hi>Steward</hi> of a <hi>Princes Family,</hi> and who was executed for his Treaſon thereto, may as juſtly claim, that he and his Poſterity ſhould be ſtill <hi>Stewards</hi> thereof, becauſe his ſaid Predeceſſours had been injurious and falſe unto it, for many Ages together, as <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> may claim to be King by inheritance over theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe Conſiderations, it ſeemeth to me, and may appear to others, that the <hi>Peoples Cauſe</hi> hath been unjuſtly ſcandalized; and that a falſe opinion derived unto the late <hi>King</hi> from his <hi>Progenitors,</hi> ſettled in him by long Uſurpation, and confirmed by the Flatteries of his <hi>Courtiers, Chaplains,</hi> and other <hi>Paraſites,</hi> made him believe that GOD had given him a right to all that which he claimed: though it were contrary to the <hi>poſitive Law,</hi> whereby he had commanded <hi>Kings</hi> to be regulated; and repugnant alſo to that <hi>Law</hi> which was written in his heart, until he had blotted it out: For, none but they, who are more worthy to be made <hi>Beasts</hi> then <hi>Men,</hi> can imagine that our ever-wiſe, juſt, and moſt merciful GOD (except by permiſſion, when a <hi>Nation</hi> depraved by their own vanity, fooliſhneſs and ſlaviſh mind, deſires it) would have conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch a <hi>deſtructive Monſter</hi> as an <hi>unlimited Governour,</hi> and advance a few men in every Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (yea, and ſometimes the vileſt out of the vileſt among them) to ſubject all the reſt to his luſt and ambition upon a juſt <hi>Title;</hi> as if all the reſidue of <hi>man-kind</hi> had been created for the ſake of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> Doubtleſs, no reaſonable Creature can imagine this; or think it impoſſible (as in appearance many do) that, they cannot be well governed without ſuch a <hi>gay Bable,</hi> as they uſually make of it; or that it is diſpleaſing to GOD, that, when he hath given them power and opportunity ſo to do, a <hi>People</hi> ſhould endeavour to ſhake off their Fetters, and eſtabliſh ſuch a <hi>Government,</hi> as may preſerve their Temporal <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Freedoms,</hi> without admitting ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of <hi>humane ſociety,</hi> for the time to come. Theſe, and ſuch things as theſe, muſt be well
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118433:18"/>conſidered by <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> to prepare his heart, before my <hi>Expedient</hi> will be pertinent and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto him.</p>
            <p>As, I had means to be rightly informed of the <hi>Kings Cauſe,</hi> ſo I had of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> alſo, by being thereby called to a <hi>Military Command</hi> in their firſt <hi>Army;</hi> to the execution of <hi>Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy</hi> in the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and by being inforced to attend almoſt 18 years at the latter end of my life, in hope to obtain Juſtice from them or their Interruptors: For, by theſe means I knew the greateſt part of them ſo far forth as Trees are known by their Fruits, which may acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally be made better or worſe: Thoſe three <hi>Employments,</hi> gave me opportunity to obſerve how our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> our <hi>Protectors,</hi> our <hi>Councils,</hi> our <hi>Armies,</hi> our <hi>Committees,</hi> our <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> behaved themſelves toward GOD and each other in the management of their <hi>Cauſe.</hi> And to ſpeak truth, without lying for them, or againſt them; if I had been a ſtranger to their Cauſe and the Kings, and muſt have judged whether had been moſt righteous, by the manners and actings of the men, I ſhould have given judgement againſt the Peoples Cauſe: For, the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Party, whom we call Cavaliers, proſecuted their Evil Cauſe like men, and like ſuch men as they made ſhew to be: But the Parliament Party, (ſome few excepted, whoſe burthens and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations were the greater, and makes them worthy to be the more pitied and honoured) managed their Good Cauſe like—like—like—(to tell you truly) like I know not what; for I can deviſe nothing under heaven, and above ground, whereto I may liken them: and it is no wonder that ſo many thouſands fall off dayly from them, and that our Enemies judge of our Cauſe, and of Us, as I hear they do. I ſhould not have thought it poſſible, that men profeſſing and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much good, ſhould have been ſo evil, if GOD had permitted me to have lived ſo obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a Country Village, as I much deſired, where I ſhould have known no more of the one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or of the other, then common Fame had informed, to whoſe rumours I give little credit. And knowing me ſo well as many of thoſe men do, if they had not been infatuated, they would have done me Juſtice (though not for Juſtice ſake) to have ſent me thither, (being reſolved to do as they have done) where I ſhould not have had means to be a witneſs againſt them for that inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and partiality which I have obſerved. I engaged for the Parliament out of conſcience, elſe I might have had as good means to know experimentally, the manners of the Kings Party, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am informed, but by report onely: For, being by ſome of them, thought more conſiderable, then I am by thoſe to whom I voluntarily adhered, I was invited to that ſide by two Letters from the Lord <hi>Butler</hi> (which I think are yet among my papers) who thereby engaged to ſettle imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon me half his Eſtate, and that it ſhould be but an earneſt of a far greater gratitude in future from the King, if I would come unto him then at <hi>Oxford:</hi> yet I conſtantly adhered to the Parliament, and do not repent it in this day of our confuſion, though in requital of my faithfulneſs in adventuring my Life, Credit, and all my Eſtate for it, they have expoſed me and my Family to ſcorn and poverty, as well by other injuries done, as by neglect of Juſtice, and by not making good their Securities, and Engagements, which occaſioned my Engagements to other men.</p>
            <p>I mention theſe things, that being ſome way brought to their Conſideration, it may prepare them to be capable of another extraordinary Mercy, in this their greateſt need; and not out of revenge: For, I know Vengeance belongs to GOD, and that I ſhall but burn my own Fingers, by endeavouring to pull down hot Coals upon the heads of mine Oppreſſours: Therefore, my ſmitings are but friendly blows, and my corroding Expreſſions applyed but to eat out the dead fleſh which may hinder the operation of a healing Balſame: and, it is very needful: for by all thoſe Parties afore particularized, and even by us who pretend to the beſt Cauſe, many things have been acted or connived at, which were ſo imprudent, ſo unjuſt, ſo unmerciful, and indeed ſo barbarous, that we are a plague to each other, and a laughing-ſtock to all our Neighbours round about us: and, inſtead of repenting, and endeavouring to amend what is amiſs, in a rational and poſſible way, we behave our ſelves like Whores in a City-Alley: They firſt fall to ſcolding, railing, belying, impeaching and abuſing each other by all opprobrious words; then, to tear and ſcratch, and at laſt to grow ſo mad, that they ſet each others houſes on fire, to the undoing of themſelves and their neighbours. We, and our Enemies, inſtead of looking to our own ways,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118433:18"/>and proſecuting that which might deliver us out of thoſe confuſions and ſtreights, whereinto our ſins and follies have brought us, do ſpend much of our time in ſowing ſeeds of diſcord, and in ſcandalous Imputations, as if that juſtified our ſeveral Cauſes. It is written, that <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel when he contended with the Devil, (as bad as the Devil was) durſt not bring a rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Accuſation againſt him; but ſaid onely, <hi>The LORD rebuke thee.</hi> Such Accuſations, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, were even theſe of mine, as were not allowable, if they were untrue; and no better, though they be true, if I intended them maliciouſly to bring any one to deſtruction or ſhame, and not in true Charity to ſave men from ſhame and deſtruction by repentance. We on both ſides cannot be contented to object matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> ſo far as we know or believe it to be true, in juſtification of our <hi>Cauſes,</hi> but endeavour alſo to make it ſeem good by doing that which is evil, and affirming that which is untrue, or ſo doubtful that it ought not to be peremptorily averred: yea, we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make bold to intrude into GOD's <hi>ſecret Judgements</hi> to diſparage our Adverſaries Cauſe, or to juſtifie our own thereby; and often-abuſively miſ-apply GOD's Word to our own wicked purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> think to juſtifie their Cauſe by an Argument drawn from our unſtableneſs, boaſting that they have not been ſo fickle and diſobedient to their <hi>Governour</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> as we have been to ours; but that, they have in all his, and in their own dangers and troubles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued conſtant both to their <hi>first Principles</hi> and to their <hi>King:</hi> which is partly true, to our <hi>ſhame,</hi> but not much to their <hi>honour,</hi> and no whit to the juſtifying of their <hi>Cauſe:</hi> For, mans corruption makes him to adhere more firmly to that which is <hi>evil,</hi> then to that which is <hi>good.</hi> And, it is not ſo much their <hi>vertue,</hi> as their <hi>neceſſity,</hi> perhaps, which keeps them conſtant. They, have no other means of ſafety and ſubſiſtence for the moſt part, elſe (as many of them have done, who had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Reſuge</hi>) they, it may be, who brag of their <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> would have deſerted him alſo, ere this day: Moreover, many of them are the perſons whoſe evil Counſels was the undoing of their <hi>King</hi> and of his <hi>Father,</hi> and of themſelves. They had gotten thereby great <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Titles of honour,</hi> which they could not elſe have obtained; and which being now loſt, cannot be re-poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but by adherence unto him, until his condition grows deſperate, or until they can be better provided for: ſo their faithfulneſs and perſeverance doth probably proceed rather from ſelf-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, then from love to their King, or from the juſtneſs of his Cauſe. But, indeed, the greateſt ſtumbling-block, and ſtone of offence, which will obſtruct my <hi>Expedient</hi> in taking good effect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Common People,</hi> are thoſe <hi>Events</hi> which have enſued upon miſ-underſtanding our Cauſe, and upon our miſ-proceeding therein; and thoſe obſtructive Objections, are caſt in, and raiſed partly by the <hi>Royalists,</hi> and partly by ſome ignorant and malevolent perſons among our ſelves, who perceive not from whence thoſe Events do more naturally proceed.</p>
            <p>To make the <hi>Peoples Cauſe</hi> appear unjuſt, and therefore their proſecutions thereof unpleaſing to GOD, and to make the vulgar ſort think the <hi>Kings claim</hi> to be righteous, they object that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can ſettle upon no <hi>Government</hi> without him, and that we have no good and lawful <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> to build upon; and that therefore, GOD blaſteth all our endeavours from time to time: whereas that iſſues not from the evilneſs of our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> but from the imprudence or ſelf-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Proſecutors.</hi> To fright ignorant perſons into a belief or ſuſpition of the goodneſs or lawfulneſs of our <hi>Claim,</hi> they tell them of one <hi>Parliament-man</hi> that hanged himſelf; how theſe and theſe, came to ſuch and ſuch Tragical ends, and what befel to ſome other eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who were Patrons thereof; as if that proved the Cauſe which they owned, to be unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably evil; all which are but <hi>Childiſh Bug-bears,</hi> and Fanatick Hob-Goblins, which are eaſily charmed into nothing. What a ridiculous Argument is it to prove the unjuſtneſs of a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to alledge that one of the Proſecutors thereof hanged himſelf! There were but twelve <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and one of them hanged himſelf; doth that any whit diſparage the <hi>Apoſtolick Faith?</hi> perhaps as theſe do, the malitious <hi>Jews</hi> made uſe of it to the like <hi>purpoſe,</hi> though by his own confeſſion, they knew that Judgement fell upon <hi>Judas,</hi> not becauſe he was one of <hi>Chriſts Followers,</hi> but for that he was a <hi>Traitor</hi> to his <hi>Maſter,</hi> and had betrayed an Innocent into their hands. There were above 400 <hi>Parliament-men,</hi> of which but one made away himſelf; and we knowing not upon what ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>Motive,</hi> what can be thereupon inferred? Indeed, if all the 400, or ſo many of them as <hi>owned</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118433:19"/>the <hi>peoples Cauſe,</hi> had banged themſelves, except one, we might have concluded as our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries do. The Conjurers up of thoſe deluſive <hi>Apparations,</hi> do not remember, that thoſe 18 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon whom the Tower fell, and they whoſe <hi>blood-Pilat</hi> mingled with their Sacrifices, were no greater ſinners then other men; and that they who conceived hardly of them, ſhould alſo periſh unleſs they repented: nor do they take notice, that the like ends have happened to as many, or to more of their own <hi>party;</hi> and that it would be as valid an <hi>Argument</hi> againſt their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as againſt ours. Nor, do they know, (or elſe will not know) as we do, who have obſerved their actings &amp; deportments, that moſt, if not all of them, on our ſide, who have been particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed as men purſued by <hi>Divine Vengeance,</hi> ſuffered not by the hand of <hi>Common Juſtice,</hi> or by a <hi>ſecret Judgment,</hi> in outward probability, for their deſerting the <hi>Kings Cauſe,</hi> or for being inſtrumental in removing him; but, for that they were Traytors to them by whom they were truſted, and falſe to the <hi>peoples Cauſe,</hi> which they ſeemingly owned; and either betrayed it, or would have betrayed it, if they had not been timely cut off. And, whereas the many <hi>extravagancies</hi> relating both to <hi>Religion</hi> and the depravation of Manners in theſe times are objected, as effects of our <hi>evil Cauſe;</hi> it is to be conſidered, that thoſe are the uſual products in times of War, of that licentiouſneſs which is in men of corrupt minds and principles, who then diſcover that pravity which lay hid in them formerly; and not from the Cauſe in Controverſie.</p>
            <p>For my part, I am not a whit out of heart, by the preſent diſtractions; by the ſcandalizing of our <hi>Cauſe;</hi> by the Obſtructions it hath met withal; by the hazards it is now in; by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of powerful Adverſaries; or, by the failings of thoſe that manage it: Nor do I judge the goodneſs of any mans <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to be more or leſs by <hi>Events,</hi> whether proſperous, or unproſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, at the firſt, leſt as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, I may condemn the Generation of the Righteous, or juſtifie the Wicked: nor do I judge of any thing, by the <hi>outward pomp,</hi> or <hi>baſe aſpect,</hi> which it hath in the eye of the world; nor by the continuance which it can plead by <hi>Preſcription:</hi> For, <hi>Tyranny,</hi> hath been ever ſince <hi>Nimrods</hi> raign. The <hi>Mahumetans Impoſtures,</hi> (which is an uſurped <hi>Antichriſtian power</hi> without the Pale of the Church) hath tyrannized almoſt a thouſand years. The <hi>Roman Hierarchy,</hi> which is the <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> in the viſible <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> hath perſecuted above ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years: our <hi>Norman bondage</hi> hath continued above five hundred. The Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they were brought out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where they had been enſlaved above three hundred years, and then advanced in hope to be made Poſſeſſors of a Country inhabited by <hi>powerful Nations,</hi> were doubtleſs as much derided for that <hi>Attempt,</hi> as we are by our Neighbours, and by ſome among our ſelves, who in deriſion and ſcorn call our, <hi>The Good Old Cauſe.</hi> They, had as many longings and lookings back toward <hi>Aegypt,</hi> as the greateſt part of this people hath at this day to return to their old <hi>Task-maſters,</hi> to their Garlick, Onyons, Fleſh-pots, and ſuch other Carnal Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as thoſe which we prefer before our <hi>Birth-rights,</hi> and value leſs then a Meſs of Porrage. They tempted GOD, and provoked him by their Idolatries, Fornications, Murmurings, Rebellions, Avarice, Backſlidings, and Self-ſeekings, as we do: So, they mutined againſt their <hi>Superiors;</hi> ſo, they diſcouraged each other, by miſ-reporting that <hi>Good Land,</hi> to which GOD was carrying them; by repreſenting formidably the ſtrength of the high-walled Cities, and the mighty Giants who were therein; and thoſe diſcouragements proceeded from ſome of the moſt eminent perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, even from no leſs then <hi>ſix</hi> to <hi>one</hi> of thoſe who were choſen to ſpy out the Land: ſo, alſo, were they for their unfaithfulneſs, and other ſins, waſted and delayed as we have been, even forty years in the <hi>Deſarts,</hi> as we have been almoſt twenty years already, as it were in <hi>a Wilderneſs of Confuſions,</hi> for our prevarications and miſ-belief: and our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> is at this preſent exerciſed with many Fears, Doubts, Wants, Troubles, and Powerful Adverſaries in the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage toward the recovery of our long-loſt <hi>Freedoms;</hi> and yet (as theirs was) our <hi>Cauſe</hi> is never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs that <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> of which we ſhould neither be aſhamed or diſtruſtful.</p>
            <p>If we may cenſure the Righteouſneſs of a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> by the mean beginning, by the outward deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cableneſs, by the tedious and difficult progreſſions, by the contemptibleneſs of the Proſecutors, or by the unproſperous ſucceſſes during many years; no Cauſe in the world, might be ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lyable to miſ cenſure, as our <hi>Chriſtian profeſſion,</hi> which for many Ages together, was the ſcorn not of the <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>fooliſh,</hi> but alſo of the <hi>nobleſt</hi> and <hi>wiſeſt perſons</hi> in the Worlds eſteem. The <hi>Profeſſors of it,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118433:19"/>were no better thought of then as Fanatick Dreamers, at beſt, and as Vagabonds, hunted through all Nations and Countries, by ten ſignal bloody Perſecutions, many hundreds of years, diſpoiled every where, of Livelyhood, Liberty and Life, And, our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> being in the principal ſcope thereof to be proſecuted for a <hi>Preparatory</hi> toward eſtabliſhing that Kingdome of CHRIST, for which the <hi>Saints</hi> have now waited in patience above ſix hundred fifty and eight years, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived (as I believe) within forty years of compleating that ſix hundred ſixty and ſix years, which numbers out the time limiting the Kingdom of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> it is no wonder that it meets with ſo much delay, hardſhip and oppreſſion, whilſt the <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the LAMB are but raw, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſciplined, not fully trained, liſted, ſealed, or formed into ſuch a well-ordered Body, as muſt fight his <hi>Battels.</hi> But, though our ſufferings, and the time of our warfare ſeems long, it is very ſhort, conſidering the perp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuity of the Kingdome which we ſhall at laſt conquer, and wherein, we ſhall individually reign with the <hi>Supreme Soveraign</hi> thereof: For, whereas all the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of the world have not laſted ſix thouſand years; that Kingdom is everlaſting without end, and communicated not to a few, (making the reſt Slaves) but to every follower of the LAMB in that <hi>Expedition;</hi> who will make them that <hi>overcome,</hi> Pillars in his houſe, never to be removed; yea, they ſhall be <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to GOD, ſitting with him upon his Throne, ſubjecting the <hi>Nations,</hi> and raigning with him for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Since I have mentioned that Kingdom whereto our Cauſe relates, and of which I hope our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Government</hi> ſhall be an appurtenant, I would gladly, without offence, though it ſeem a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, hint ſomewhat in this place, ſince it now comes into my mind, as not impertinent, to thoſe who call themſelves (or are called by others) <hi>Fifth Monarchy Men,</hi> who I think call that Kingdom the <hi>Fiſth Monarchy,</hi> leſt in ſome things they may be deſtructive thereunto, in proſecuting the ſettlement of our Government. For, though I believe there are many of thoſe, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther congregated Churches, who are truly zealous of advancing the Kingdom of CHRIST, and that a Government ſhould be modelized that might be ſubſervient thereunto; and whereby car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men might be reduced to order as well under a Spiritual, as under a Natural Government: yet, (if I have not been miſ-informed concerning the Judgments and Opinions of ſome among them) there are not a few who having a Zeal without Knowledge, do fancy ſuch a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> as neither conſiſts with the <hi>Divinity</hi> of CHRIST, nor with the <hi>Humanity of men;</hi> and that poſſibly ſome other (as in all Diſpenſations it hath happened) who are ſtirred up by the Devil, or by their own ſelf-mindedneſs, to hinder the coming of this Kingdom, by pretending in their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de to advance it; and who, to exerciſe the Faith and Patience of the Saints a little longer, will be making <hi>Linſie Wolſie,</hi> and plowing with Oxen and Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s together, in hope thereby to reduce us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to a meer earthly Foundation, or to build Caſtles in the Air, as they would do, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not that the <hi>Dimenſions, Materials,</hi> and other <hi>Appurtenances</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> myſtically deſcribed in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> are Evangelically, and not Literally to be underſtood. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in particular: <hi>The pavement ſhall be pure Gold, transparent as Glaſs;</hi> whereby, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, the Citizens of that City, ſhall be free from Covetouſneſs, treading more precious Gold under their feet, then that whereof a varitious Tyrants make their richeſt Ornaments for their heads; and that their walkings, will be evidently pure to all beholders.</p>
            <p>By what warrant they term the Kingdome of CHRIST the <hi>Fifth Monarchy,</hi> I know not. It may be called the <hi>Fifth,</hi> in relation to thoſe four <hi>Monarchies</hi> which are mentioned as preceding it in the Prophecy of <hi>Daniel,</hi> if you reckon the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> which ſprung from it but for one; <hi>Alexander</hi> and his four Captains, two <hi>Monarchies;</hi> and begin to reckon after the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarchy was tranſlated to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi> But, to ſay truth, whether we may call the Kingdom of CHRIST upon Earth the Fifth, Sixth or Seventh <hi>Monarchy,</hi> it is to me doubtful, when I conſult with <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophecies: For, by <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image, which conſiſted of five parts, Gold, Silver, Braſs, Iron, and Iron mixed with Clay, which laſt is the Kingdome of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> wherein were ten Kingdoms there typified by the ten toes, and by ten horns in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation;</hi> it ſeemeth to be the ſixth grand Monarchy in the world. If the Kingdom of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and that of the Roman Empire, be to be accounted but one, and the <hi>Grecian Monarch</hi> and his four <hi>Captains</hi> two Monarchies, then it will be the Fifth Monarchy, after <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſion of the four
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118433:20"/>Beaſts, leaving out the <hi>Babylonian Monarchy,</hi> which was paſt at the time of the <hi>Viſion,</hi> and but the fourth <hi>Monarchy</hi> from that time, if <hi>Alexander</hi> and his Captains be reckoned but one <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> as indeed they were no more, in regard that of the <hi>Captains</hi> was a <hi>Tetrarchy,</hi> not a Monarchy, and but the ſame Monarchy branched into four. But, if you make (as ſeveral Expoſitors do) that of the <hi>Babylonians</hi> one, the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Alexander</hi> a third, his four Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a fourth, the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Empire a fifth <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and the <hi>Clay and Iron Kingdom,</hi> which branched out of it, to be a ſixth; then the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of CHRIST muſt be the ſeventh <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Therefore, to give it the moſt proper Attribute, it is the Alpha and Omega, the firſt and laſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarchy, that was, is, or ſhall be, though <hi>Tyrants</hi> have had for many thouſands of years the moſt viſible power upon Earth: For GOD, and CHRIST in him, (though not manifeſted to the world) have inviſibly governed during their uſurpations, and concurred in governing du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Paternal Monarchies of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> until <hi>Nimrods</hi> intruſions, and afterward; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, in governing the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by his Vice-gerents, <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> and the Judges, until the people rejecting his Government, deſired a King like other Nations: for which folly and ſin, they were under a Tyrannical Government, even when it was at beſt, until CHRIST came in the Fleſh; and ſo ſhall we alſo, if we admit of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> or of any other <hi>Governours</hi> upon the old Terms and Conſtitutions, (after GOD upon tryal hath declared us free) until CHRIST comes to Judgement; whoſe Government, if we embrace in the mean time, we may be happy and free indeed; for his Yoke is eaſie, his Scepter a righteous Scepter, and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment whilſt we are in the Fleſh, will be ſuch a Government as Fleſh and Blood (whoſe frailty he knows) may ſuſtain, and be regulated by: For his raign upon earth, will not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Laws agreeable to the humane Nature, nor without Magiſtrates impowered to govern un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him; but, a Government reſembling in ſome reſpects, (but in an Evangelical and more excellent manner) that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> governing his people, and by ſuch humane Laws of their own as are not repugnant thereto, as the Jews were governed by their Judges, and by their Ceremonial and Judicial Laws, together with that Moral Law, which was univerſally obliging. And as GOD and the <hi>People,</hi> had then a concurrence in the Election of their Magiſtrates; ſo it will be, when the Kingdom of CHRIST, is ſettled among us. LORD, <hi>Haſten the coming of it; and let not the many ſtruglings of thy people in theſe Nations, at this time, to make way for it, be altogether in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt pardon my Immethodical Ramblings, to remove ſuch Obſtructions as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive may hinder my <hi>Expedient;</hi> and bear with my ſuddain ſtepping aſide otherwhile from the matter in hand, to do that which I think pertinent to my purpoſe, whilſt it is in my remembrance: for the diſorders of theſe times do not afford me leaſure to order my own muſings; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving expreſſed as much as I can at preſent think on by way of Preparative, <hi>I</hi> will now apply my <hi>Expedient</hi> to thoſe whom it may concern. <hi>I</hi> am grieved to perceive how witty moſt men are to raiſe Arguments againſt Truth and their own Peace; and ſhould be glad that our greateſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies might be reducible to that happineſs which they have loſt; and that they who are expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to many Temptations by dwelling in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and ſojourning in the Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> might have a more comfortable habitation: For, I believe ſome among them, who oppoſed our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> acted in their underſtanding upon a principle of Juſtice or Honour, which they thought obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them unto what they did; which makes me much pity their misfortune. <hi>I</hi> never heard any diſhonourable mention of the two Brothers of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> or that they acted againſt this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</hi> maliciouſly; but were active onely ſo far forth as they thought themſelves in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Alleageance, and Natural Affection obliged to their Brother; and <hi>I</hi> wiſh they might enjoy the Conveniences whereof they are deprived, with our ſafety: and though their Brother hath acted upon his own accompt, and yet proſecuteth ſuch things as are deſtructive to our Peace; and, though by that which we are informed of his inclination, we have cauſe to be ſuſpitious that thoſe prejudices and affections which are ſettled in him, will never be ſo clearly removed, as to make him capable of any <hi>Expedient</hi> which may bring him hither in Peace, and to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of theſe Nations: yet, not knowing, how that GOD, who hath all mens hearts in his hand, may pleaſe to ſanctifie his <hi>afflictions,</hi> and thereby prepare him to what ſeems elſe impoſſible;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118433:20"/>and conſidering that all the other <hi>Parties</hi> aforementioned, are as unable as he to perform of themſelves the conditions of my <hi>Expedients,</hi> without ſpecial grace, they ſhall have a Latitude as well to comprehend him reſpectively, as any other whom they may concern, that he or they who ſhall firſt conform thereto, may firſt have benefit thereby, without reſpect of perſons. I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, what Prejudicacies muſt be removed before they can be effectually entertained; and therefore now I come to the <hi>Expedients</hi> themſelves, which I communicate to you in <hi>private,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by <hi>Publication;</hi> becauſe what <hi>I</hi> have heretofore offered of that nature, hath been little regarded; and becauſe <hi>I</hi> know that if any of the <hi>Parties</hi> aforementioned ſhall be capable of them, GOD will either by you, or by ſome other hand, cauſe them to be ſeaſonably brought to their Cognizance, or direct them thereunto by his immediate grace.</p>
            <p>All thoſe <hi>Parties</hi> in general, muſt reſolve in the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt place, to deny themſelves, and act more for GOD's Glory, and for the Publick Welfare, according to his revealed Will, &amp; to the Dictates of a rectified Conſcience; ſo, muſt Patriots in particular more faithfully then they have done for the moſt part heretofore: among which, I have leſs hope of them, who by their deportment, words and actions, ſeem to call out as <hi>Jehu</hi> did to <hi>Jehonadab, Come &amp; ſee my zeal for the LORD,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Governours,</hi> by what Title ſoever they are called, who deſire to be at peace with their <hi>Neighbours</hi> and their <hi>Subjects</hi> over whom they reign, or to recover that Dignity and Authority which they have loſt, (or to be made happy and contented without it) muſt conſider, that GOD, the LORD of HOSTS, who is <hi>Soveraign Paramount</hi> over all <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Republicks</hi> in the world, beholds all their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous <hi>Deſignes</hi> proceeding from <hi>Ambition,</hi> Luſt or Avarice; that notwithſtanding all their hypocritical Pretendings to Religion and Juſtice, he knows when they regard it no further then it may advance their corrupt intereſts; that he heeds their bruitſh buſtlings, and diſſembled complementings one with another; their barbarous and inhumane devaſtations of their own and other Countries, to ſatiate their revenge, or to uphold their pomp by Fire, Sword and Rapine, to the deſtroying of <hi>Humane Society,</hi> and to the making millions of men miſerable, who might have lived comfortably, if they who were advanced for their Weal, had not made themſelves a plague to <hi>Man-kind</hi> by tyrannizing no leſs over their Conſciences, then their Eſtates and Perſons, under pretence of being <hi>GOD's Vice-gerents,</hi> whereas they do rather make true the <hi>Devils</hi> vaunt, who boaſted that all <hi>the Kingdoms of this world</hi> were at his diſpoſe: which implies, that they are then his <hi>Vice-roys</hi> and <hi>Deputies.</hi> They muſt alſo conſider, that GOD's Long-ſuffering permits their extravagancies, not as prerogatives juſtly due unto them, but, that every thing ſhould for a time onely manifeſt it ſelf in its own nature, to be purged in its own fire; that evil men, may be <hi>mutual Corrections</hi> for their own ſins, that by inter-wrangling <hi>Judgements</hi> and <hi>Mercies,</hi> he may bring them, if poſſible, to timely repentance and amendment: and that if they bring not forth fruits at laſt anſwerable to his expectation, he may be glorified in executing Juſtice; call them to a ſtrict account, and with his <hi>Iron Mace</hi> break them in pieces like a Potters Veſſel, which can never be ſet together again; as lately and often heretofore he hath done to other <hi>Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſours.</hi> Having duly conſidered theſe things, with ſuch like, they muſt then reſigne to GOD, his <hi>Throne</hi> in mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and permit his <hi>People</hi> to enjoy the <hi>Liberties</hi> due to them by the Laws of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> ruling for the future in <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> By practiſing this <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> and continuing conſtant therein, they ſhall be eſtabliſhed in <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> both at home and abroad, as <hi>Vice-roys</hi> and <hi>Vice-gerents</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>lords,</hi> with more honor then a <hi>Tyrant</hi> can acquire by an <hi>Univerſal Monarchy,</hi> and unlimited Prerogatives: yea, if they can but get hearts willing to embrace this <hi>Expedient,</hi> after they are irrecoverably caſt out of their <hi>Governments</hi> or <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> they ſhall be as happy and as well contented, as if they were again reſtored.</p>
            <p>This is my <hi>Expedient</hi> for all Governours in general, and it will be pertinent to <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> in particular: But, there may ſomewhat more be added, which will ſpecially belong to him; and <hi>I</hi> could wiſh it might be to him ſo ſeaſonably, and reſpectively communicated, that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entertained as a jeering of him in his affliction, (which baſeneſs my Soul abhors) he might at leaſt make ſome good uſe of it to fit him for a <hi>Coeleſtial Kingdome,</hi> if it cannot make way for his recovery of thoſe which he hath loſt in this world. His beſt <hi>Expedient</hi> will be, ſincerely to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118433:21"/>himſelf to GOD (who to that end hath outwardly humbled him) for his <hi>own ſins,</hi> and the ſins of his <hi>Fathers Houſe,</hi> and for which his <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>He,</hi> were caſt out of theſe <hi>Kingdoms.</hi> He muſt bewail them heartily and voluntarily, not by compulſion and feignedly, as perhaps he did in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was thereupon actually thrown out of that poſſeſſion which he then had. He muſt ſeriouſly conſider what Freedoms do naturally and reaſonably belong to <hi>Man kind,</hi> and to every man as a man, that he may do as he would be done unto, being a private perſon. He muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how vain the promiſings, pretended friendſhips, and help of Princes, and of all degrees of men are; how little hope there will be for him by the aſſiſtance of all his <hi>Allies</hi> and moſt powerful <hi>Confederates,</hi> to poſſeſs what he claims, if upon the repentance of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> GOD be ſtill on their ſide; and how great a plague (if they continue as they are) he and they would be to each other, if he ſhould obtain the Soveraignty over them; eſpecially, if reſtored by a <hi>Forraign Aid,</hi> whereby unſpeakable calamities would enſue both to him and them. He muſt take notice, that the two main <hi>Cauſes</hi> of the <hi>Quarrel</hi> betwixt his <hi>Father</hi> and theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> being for his uſurping a <hi>Negative Voyce</hi> upon thoſe Laws which the people ſhould chuſe; and his denying the <hi>Militia</hi> to belong to them in chief, was injuriouſly given by his <hi>Fathers</hi> default, in regard the chuſing what Laws they pleaſed (not repugnant to the Law of GOD) is not onely rationally and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally due unto them, but alſo by the <hi>common-Law</hi> of <hi>England</hi> long before the Intruſion of <hi>Duke William</hi> of <hi>Normandy;</hi> and that they had alſo a right, by continued <hi>Claim,</hi> and Practiſe, to chuſe the <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> who had <hi>Poſſe Comitatus,</hi> which is the <hi>Militia,</hi> in every <hi>County;</hi> and therewith he ſhall do well to conſider, that ſuch a <hi>Kingdom</hi> as his <hi>Predeceſſours</hi> had, and as he deſires to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs, is one of the <hi>Horns</hi> of that <hi>Beaſt</hi> which muſt ſhortly be deſtroyed; and, but one of the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> which the <hi>Devil</hi> claims to be in his Gift; and uſually beſtoweth upon them, who will fall down and worſhip him, apoſtatizing from GOD, to be his <hi>Vaſſals;</hi> that it is but ſuch a <hi>Kingdom</hi> as <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>wicked men,</hi> may as well poſſeſs as <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>good men;</hi> and that it neither makes the one wiſer, or the other better, but oftentimes makes a wiſe man a <hi>fool,</hi> and good men to be <hi>evil:</hi> that he, who had three ſuch <hi>Kingdoms</hi> yeſterday, may not have the next day three foot of earth in them to reſt upon: That, it brings more trouble and danger, then peace and ſafety: That, it ſets a man upon a <hi>Throne</hi> in the morning, and brings him down to a <hi>Dungeon</hi> ere night; and that the people who lye proſtrare before him, adoring him as a god, this moment, may ſoon after trample on him, and cut off his head with diſhonour. All theſe things being well conſidered, will make him a greater <hi>Conqueror</hi> by conquering himſelf, and ſubduing his paſſions and inordinate deſires, then if he had ſubdued theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> make him a more <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious King</hi> then any of his Predeceſſours; and conſtitute a better and a more abſolute <hi>Empire</hi> in his little <hi>Iſle of Man,</hi> then he could have enjoyed by the recovery of all that he hath loſt. His <hi>Courtiers,</hi> and perhaps he himſelf alſo, will deride this <hi>Expedient;</hi> but, all their policy, cannot contrive him a better: For, if he will make proof of it, and with patience under GOD's viſitation, make uſe of the charity of his Friends abroad, and live a peaceable private life, in performing as a <hi>Probationer</hi> all Moral and Pious Duties, till <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall provide better for him, as he did for <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim</hi> King of <hi>Judah</hi> (even by thoſe who had caſt him out of his <hi>Kingdome) GOD,</hi> to whom nothing is impoſſible, whatſoever bars are ſet againſt him, may bring him hither in mercy, both to him and to theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> yea, and will, if he ſhall be humbled and qualified according to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation; and then the ſooner he comes, the better welcome: nay, though he be not ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſhall come both to our deſtruction, and his own, <hi>GOD,</hi> may probably bring him; for, we are at this time, preparing him a ſmoothe way, paved in <hi>Checker-wiſe,</hi> with our <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>follies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much I have contemplated on the behalf of <hi>Charles Stuart;</hi> for whom, whatſoever he ſhall think of it, if it comes to his hands, I have contrived no worſe an <hi>Expedient,</hi> then I my ſelf would practiſe if I were in his caſe, and knew the world ſo well as I do. Now I will offer an <hi>Expedient</hi> to the <hi>Nations</hi> in general, who are enſlaved by Tyrants, and left without all probable means to infranchiſe themſelves; which is briefly this: Let them wait patiently upon <hi>GOD</hi> for Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, until he providentially makes way for it; and then thankfully take the opportunities of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and conſtantly proſecute them: Let them conſider, that their <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118433:21"/>juſtly come upon them for thier ſins, &amp; that they can have do deliverance but by GOD, nor any perfect deliverance by him, unleſs being reconciled to him, they break off from their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> fruitful in good works, and make him their onely <hi>Reſuge.</hi> This if they do, or but heartily endeavourit, their loſt Freedoms, for recovery whereof, they have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in vain waſted their <hi>Treaſure,</hi> endured many <hi>Frights, Troubles</hi> and <hi>Hardſhips;</hi> undergone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Changes;</hi> ſpont their <hi>Blood;</hi> fought, prayed and faſted alſo, without <hi>Succeſs,</hi> ſhall be obtained by <hi>Prayers</hi> onely; and then, they ſhall better ſee GOD's <hi>merciful intentions,</hi> and their own former <hi>miſ-underſtandings</hi> and <hi>failings;</hi> then their <hi>Governours</hi> ſhall be as <hi>Fathers:</hi> then their <hi>Armies,</hi> if they need any, ſhall be faithful; and then they ſhall enjoy their <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> fully and ſo peaceably, that they may ſerve GOD comfortably, in <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>righteoufneſs.</hi> all the days of their lives.</p>
            <p>Moreover, as for the <hi>Governours</hi> and people of theſe <hi>Nations</hi> in particular, it will be their beſt <hi>Expedient,</hi> joyntly and apart, to reconcile themſelves as aforeſaid, to GOD and to each other, by the like hearty repentance of their ſins, and by laying aſide their <hi>Animoſities,</hi> whereby they dayly infeſt and exaſperate each other; remembring who hath ſaid, that <hi>a kingdome divid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d cannot ſtand:</hi> that being united, they may in true Charity, be active in ſuch a Cauſe as may rationally effect a perfect <hi>Settlement:</hi> And, if GOD ſhall again reſtore the <hi>Parliameat,</hi> or impower other men permiſſively to endeavour it, let them who ſhall be authorized be <hi>merciful</hi> as he is <hi>merciful,</hi> and once more oblige them by forgiveneſs of their former Delinquencies, who ſhall acknowledge their faults, and ſubmit, with <hi>Engagements</hi> given, for the future, to be obedient and conformable to thoſe <hi>Constitutions</hi> which the <hi>viſible power</hi> then in being, ſhall reſolve upon, with the aſſent of <hi>that part of the people,</hi> who heretofore adventured their lives and eſtates to preſerve and continue their <hi>natural Freedoms.</hi> This <hi>mercy,</hi> (which the Covetouſneſs of ſome will perhaps obſtruct) being with prudence diſpenſed to ſuch as may be capable thereof, will doubtleſs prevail much both with <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> toward an Eſtabliſhment of peace; and the <hi>Provocations,</hi> which peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſome have had to miſ-lead them, will require in juſtice, that this mercy ſhould be vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to ſome among them. In order hereunto, I would intimate thus much by way of <hi>Caution,</hi> (if I had opportunity to make both Parties of our now divided <hi>Army,</hi> to take the ſame into Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration) even this; That, if they who think they were obliged in Conſcience, for advance of <hi>GOD's</hi> Glory, and the <hi>common Safety,</hi> to diſſolve the <hi>Parliament,</hi> engage againſt the reſt of the <hi>Army</hi> and their <hi>Brethren,</hi> who conceive themſelves as much obliged in Conſcience, to continue true to that <hi>Truſt</hi> which was repoſed in them by the late <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> (as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied with the warrantableneſs of that <hi>Fact</hi>) both <hi>Parties</hi> may then if they contend to blood, be guilty of <hi>murder,</hi> according to the Laws, yet vertually in force, as to the <hi>outward man;</hi> and that, they muſt depend upon that <hi>Indepnity</hi> onely which <hi>GOD</hi> will be pleaſed to vouchſafe to the <hi>inward man,</hi> according as they have conſcientiouſly acted or ſuffered; and, it will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them to heed, that, this (with ſome other <hi>conſequences</hi> that may follow) will require that there be a ſtrict <hi>ſelf-examination</hi> with what mind and ſecret intentions they were tranſpotted; and alſo to what <hi>Expedients</hi> they ought in prudence and juſtice, to ſubmit on both ſides for preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a good Conſcience, and of publick ſafety for the future, leſt they violate both. Yea, it is with ſeriouſneſs to be conſidered, whether they may not ſuſpect the integrity of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (at leaſt on one ſide) when they ſearch narrowly what <hi>ſelf-ends</hi> may lye at the bottom of that which was pretended for a publick advantage; and that they will not be clear from guilt therein, if they ſhall not be willing to ſubmit to the mercy of the preſent Power, or elſe to ſuffer for what they have done irregularly, rather then the three <hi>Nations</hi> ſhould be involved again in blood, to the hazard of the whole <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> For, as it is better, <hi>that one man, or a few men, ſhould ſuffer, then that all the people ſhould periſh;</hi> ſo, it is juſt that every one ſhould ſubmit to ſuffer for his <hi>Country,</hi> who hath occaſioned the endangering of it, though he were <hi>innocent:</hi> and, indeed, not onely <hi>Innocence,</hi> but <hi>repented guiltineſs</hi> alſo, ſhall in ſuch Caſes, have a recompence, more then equivalent, for all that it can ſuffer. Moreover, it is conſiderable by both the ſaid <hi>Parties,</hi> whether there may not be a <hi>Wolf</hi> or a <hi>Fox</hi> in a <hi>Lambs skin,</hi> active in the late <hi>Deſigne,</hi> to inſnare the <hi>Rams,</hi> and to bring the whole <hi>Flock</hi> within the Paws of the <hi>Lyon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118433:22"/>
            <p>The <hi>Governours,</hi> likewiſe, who ſhall hereafter, be therewith intruſted, muſt not as heretofore, endeavour ſo to contrive a future <hi>Government,</hi> that, they may hedge in peculiar advantages to themſelves, diſadvantagious to the <hi>Peoples</hi> intereſt; or inconſiſtent with a <hi>righteous-Government;</hi> and, the <hi>People,</hi> without murmuring at them, or withholding, or withdrawing <hi>neceſſary Supplies,</hi> muſt act obediently, and with integrity, endeavour to further an Eſtabliſhment to be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> juſtly conſtituted, rather then by patching up that, which when they have done all they can, will be an <hi>imperfect and qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtionable Authority</hi> in ſome reſpects, diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory to many. This, they may now do, (if they looſe not the opportunity given) and make a more abſolute and <hi>Free Parliament</hi> by the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> which they lately made, then ever they had heretofore. If any ſhall ask in deriſion (as probably they will) By what <hi>Conquest? by a Conqueſt of themſelves?</hi> I thereto anſwer, Yes; even by a <hi>Conqueſt of themſelves,</hi> which is the moſt noble Conqueſt that can be made: for, to ſubdue the diſtempers of our own <hi>Perſons, Paſſions</hi> and <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Parties,</hi> requires all the <hi>Vertues</hi> of <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> and more <hi>Stratagems,</hi> and more manly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, then any other <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> This <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> by <hi>GOD</hi>'s aſſiſtance, hath been made, by that part of the <hi>People,</hi> which was not infatuated by their own Corruptions, or ſeduced and bewitched by the Tyrannies and Incantations of their former <hi>Oppreſſive Governours,</hi> and their Inſtruments; yea, they have conquered both thoſe <hi>Uſurpers,</hi> and that <hi>Giddy Party</hi> among themſelves, which have been Traytors to their <hi>Brethren</hi> and to <hi>Themſelves;</hi> and thoſe who were at beſt, ignorant Obſtructers of their own <hi>Freedoms</hi> and <hi>Rights,</hi> by a ſortiſh <hi>Neutrality:</hi> ſo that theſe Nations, if it be not their own fault, may be governed by <hi>Laws</hi> of their own chuſing, as men were after the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Government</hi> ceaſed, by the death of <hi>Noah;</hi> and, before the Tyrannies of <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his Succeſſours began.</p>
            <p>That, which will be moſt expedient for the <hi>Army,</hi> is to abide contented with their <hi>pay;</hi> to do no <hi>unlawful violence;</hi> to be unanimous; to avoid mutinous ſuggeſtions, and attempting inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>impoſings</hi> upon their <hi>Superiours;</hi> to be valiant, and faithfully ſubſervient to them, who are, or ſhall be called to make up the preſent <hi>Breaches;</hi> and to truſt in <hi>GOD</hi> onely to be their defender, and the finiſher of the work deſired: and it will concern us all in the mean time, that ſpecial care be taken, by every one in power, who intends or pretends <hi>Common Safety;</hi> that, timely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion be made to pay the <hi>Souldiery,</hi> both of the <hi>ſtanding Armies,</hi> and <hi>Auxiliary County-Troops,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>Mariners</hi> (as alſo, thoſe in extream want, who heretofore adventured their Lives and Eſtates, when the <hi>Common Intereſt,</hi> was in greateſt hazard) that, they may not be expoſed at this time to ſuch temptations through poverty, as will make it eaſie for the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their neceſſities. And it will be expedient, (leſt their wants make them dangerouſly tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous) that ſome competent proviſion be madè alſo for thoſe poor indigent people, (eſpecially about this City) who by the failing of Trade, or otherwiſe, are likely to be without means of ſubſiſtence during the preſent troubles. Theſe works of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> will make our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours beneficial to our ſelves, and ſo acceptable to <hi>GOD,</hi> that, though I have long been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-burthened, I had rather confine my ſelf to live on bread and water, until this <hi>Storm</hi> were paſt, then that ſuch proviſions ſhould be neglected. Theſe, are thoſe <hi>Expedients,</hi> which I think fit to be now practiſed: and, though I know many will deride them, I hope ſome will make uſe of them, either toward a publick, or for their private ſettlements. <hi>OH GOD of my Salvation, if this Eſtabliſhment ſhall not be in my days, remember me in mercy, who deſire more to have the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to ſhine upon me, then that my corn, wine, or oyl ſhould be increaſed; or then all the enjoyments which a temporal peace can afford: and if it may pleaſe thee (to whoſe good pleaſure I ſubmit) let me before ſuch a dreadful viſitation cometh, as we are likely to deſerve, (if thy grace prevent it not) be laid aſleep in my grave, dying in a firm belief that I ſhall be vouchſafed a glorious Reſurrection, at the ſecond coming of my Redeemer: and, let my deareſt relation, and all they who ſhall ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing from us, to the end of the world, (and who may perhaps be left behind me in this froward Generation) meet me with joy at his Tribunal. To which place, bring them purified with his blood, through whatſoever proſperities or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, length or ſhortneſs of time in this life, ſhall be moſt for thy glory and their ſafety: and let this Prayer, be everlaſtingly in remembrance before thee, when either I ſhall forget to pray it, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not be able to pray any more for them. I believe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall be granted; and that makes me not to fear, what the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118433:22"/>of this age, or of any other, ſhall produce.</hi> Excuſe my digreſſion in this <hi>Ejaculation:</hi> for they who are near and dear to me, coming ſuddainly into my thought, I could not forbear it.</p>
            <p>I muſt ſtand or fall, according as I diſcharge my Conſcience; and therefore, do now (as u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually heretofore) expreſs what I think; and as one <hi>muſing</hi> draws on another, without fear of <hi>King, Parliament, Armies</hi> or <hi>People;</hi> or of any diſadvàntage to my <hi>particular intereſts;</hi> or for any other partial reſpect: and, you may hereby know as well as I, what may be probably conjectured of our <hi>pablick Affairs.</hi> What our <hi>Armies,</hi> and their <hi>Aſſociates</hi> intend, I yet hear not: for, they have not declared it; and I have not of late been in ſo much eſteem either among thoſe who have a <hi>Military</hi> or <hi>Civil Power,</hi> as to be made acquainted with their intentions, or to be thought uſeful in their <hi>Publick Tranſactions,</hi> as heretofore, becauſe <hi>I</hi> am not able to ſerve them any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at my own charge. And, perhaps by being onely a <hi>By-ſtander,</hi> I do the better ſee how they play their <hi>Games;</hi> and ſhall not be ſo great a looſer, as I have been, becauſe I could not ſhuffle, cut and deal, as many did; and when I played and ſtaked my own money for them, who turned it more to my detriment, then all they have done againſt whom I played. But, let that paſs: for this, and ſuch digreſſions, ſlip in before I am aware. Whatſoever our <hi>Parliament,</hi> or any of their Adherers have done amiſs, I pray <hi>GOD</hi> forgive them, and reſtore it once more, if it may be for his <hi>Glory</hi> and the <hi>Common Welfare:</hi> for the worſt <hi>I</hi> wiſh them, is this, that the worſt men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, may be better then the beſt have heretofore been. Whatſoever the <hi>Armies,</hi> or their <hi>Confederates</hi> have intended, or ſhall proſecute, I pray in like manner for them; and think it will moſt concern us to look to our own actings and intentions; to beſeech <hi>GOD,</hi> to ſet and keep them and us in a <hi>Righteous Courſe;</hi> and to reſtrain both <hi>Parties</hi> now diſſenting, from <hi>blood-ſhed:</hi> For, if a <hi>Vein</hi> be opened, conſidering what <hi>Planets</hi> are in <hi>Conjunction,</hi> what malevolent Aſpects al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſome other <hi>Stars</hi> have, and in what an evil <hi>Signe</hi> the Moon is at this preſent, it will be very hazardous both to thoſe Members of it, and to the whole <hi>Body of this Republick.</hi> That which you, and I, &amp; other <hi>private men</hi> of our quality, ought to do in ſuch <hi>Imergencies,</hi> is patiently to ſuffer what we cannot avoid; to ſubmit to the <hi>viſible Power in being,</hi> whatſoever it be, or howſoever gotten, whilſt <hi>GOD</hi> permits it to rule over us, furniſhed with the moſt probable means to protect us in our obedience. We are alſo obliged, to act faithfully under it, and with it, in all <hi>Civil Truſts</hi> and <hi>Duties,</hi> whithout ſo much as ſpeaking any thing in publick or in private, which may weaken their hands, or infringe the <hi>Common Peace:</hi> yea, we muſt take as much care as poſſibly we can, not to permit our <hi>Conſciences</hi> or <hi>Judgements</hi> to be ſeduced by <hi>falſe appearances:</hi> which Grace we may obtain by <hi>Prayer,</hi> and by examining all we hear, before we entertain it with belief: for <hi>GOD</hi> hath afforded means whereby every man may be rightly informed; and calleth no man to any undertakng, whom he leaves unfurniſhed with what may enable him to effect it, ſo far forth as it ſhall be required, or may be proſecuted with a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Counſel which <hi>Gamaliel</hi> gave to the <hi>Jews,</hi> when deluded by a Zeal without knowledge, they perſecuted the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> will be ſeaſonable for us. We ſhall diſcern in a ſhort time, whether that which the <hi>Army</hi> hath done and deſigned to proſecute, be of GOD or not. If it be meerly of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> they, or their <hi>Deſigne,</hi> or both, will come to nought, as heretofore befel to thoſe, who proſecuted their carnal and politick ends, under colour of <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> If their Attempts be of <hi>GOD,</hi> they will proſper; and what ſhall we then get by reſiſting his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but <hi>guiltineſs,</hi> and the juſt rewards thereof? Whereas, we, who have neither <hi>calling,</hi> nor <hi>power</hi> to prevent it, when wickedneſs is intended, may ſit ſtill without trouble to our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> or hazard to our <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Eſtates,</hi> except by that which we ſhall ſuffer by other mens defaults, in the <hi>outward man.</hi> To conclude: whatſoever is intruded, or ſhall be done; GOD, who is kind to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to all who have an upright heart, will turn this, and every thing to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage at the laſt. I have ſomewhat elſe to ſay; but men cannot yet <hi>bear it,</hi> nor are they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled enough to <hi>hear it;</hi> neither am I fully enabled to <hi>expreſs it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider well of what I have written, and communicate it, as in your diſcretion, you finde it uſefull to other men at this time, as not meerly mine, but as dictates for common good, from a better Spirit then mine own, perhaps, not to be ſuppreſſed in your hands, till it be uſeleſs, though
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118433:23"/>you gave the occaſion of writing it. It fared with me in writing this Epiſtolary Diſcourſe, (and at other times when I am extraordinarily moved to expreſs my minde in things of this nature) as it fares with perſons accidentally entred into Diſcourſe, who when they began, neither knew what ſhould be the ſubject of their Communication, nor can well remember when they have done, on what ſeveral matters they talked: For, when I firſt took Pen to write this <hi>Letter,</hi> I knew not ſo much of the matter therein contained to be in my heart, with a purpoſe to expreſs it, as would have filled one of theſe Pages; and half a ſheet will hold as much as I remember of it now it is written, and as ever perhaps I ſhould remember thereof, unleſs by a review, or by putting my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory upon the rack; or, as GOD ſhall occaſionally bring the particulars to minde, when they are needful. His <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> be with us. Farewel.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>My <hi>Verſifyings,</hi> thus, are turn'd to <hi>Proſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, out of faſhion, <hi>Rime</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> growes.</l>
               <l>And, now, from publique <hi>Charmings</hi> I refrain,</l>
               <l>Becauſe, <hi>Deaf-Adders,</hi> charmed are in vain.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true Friend, <hi>George Wither.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>October 24. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Reader may pleaſe to take notice, that there is another Treatiſe extant, lately written by this Author, intituled, <hi>Epistolium-Vagum-Proſa-Metri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum:</hi> or, <hi>An Epistle at random, in Proſe and Metre.</hi> Wherein is diſcovered, that whereon the Peace of theſe Nations depends; and, what is, and what will be their ſad condition; as alſo, what New Purgatories, and Fiery Tryals they are like to paſs, if God in mercy prevent not. To be ſold alſo by the Printer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
